<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">AlphaFill: enriching AlphaFold models with ligands and cofactors</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Dutch Cancer Society and of the Dutch Ministry of Health, Welfare and Sport</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_CCtBzu9">
					<orgName type="full">iNEXT-Discovery</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2022-11-24">24 November 2022</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Maarten</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hekkelma</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-1151-6227</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Oncode Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Netherlands Cancer Institute</addrLine>
									<settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
									<country key="NL">the Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ida</forename><surname>De Vries</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-8313-7779</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Oncode Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Netherlands Cancer Institute</addrLine>
									<settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
									<country key="NL">the Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Robbie</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Joosten</surname></persName>
							<email>r.joosten@nki.nl</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-2323-2686</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Oncode Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Netherlands Cancer Institute</addrLine>
									<settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
									<country key="NL">the Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anastassis</forename><surname>Perrakis</surname></persName>
							<email>a.perrakis@nki.nl</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-1151-6227</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Oncode Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Netherlands Cancer Institute</addrLine>
									<settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
									<country key="NL">the Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Maarten</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hekkelman</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Ida de Vries</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">AlphaFill: enriching AlphaFold models with ligands and cofactors</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2022-11-24">24 November 2022</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3F1973628F1670F027E99700B5B15A1F</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 10 December 2021 Accepted: 18 October 2022</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-25T21:59+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[0], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>y already been placed within 3.5 Å of the centroid of the compound to be fitted (originating from a previously considered homolog). All AlphaFill models and metadata are stored in the AlphaFill databank.</p><p>Further details on the procedure are available in the Methods.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="13" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="14" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Artificial intelligence-based protein structure prediction approaches have had a transformative effect on biomolecular sciences. The predicted protein models in the AlphaFold protein structure database, however, all lack coordinates for small molecules, essential for molecular structure or function: hemoglobin lacks bound heme; zinc-finger motifs lack zinc ions essential for structural integrity and metalloproteases lack metal ions needed for catalysis. Ligands important for biological function are absent too; no ADP or ATP is bound to any of the ATPases or kinases. Here we present AlphaFill, an algorithm that uses sequence and structure similarity to 'transplant' such 'missing' small molecules and ions from experimentally determined structures to predicted protein models. The algorithm was successfully validated against experimental structures. A total of 12,029,789 transplants were performed on 995,411 AlphaFold models and are available together with associated validation metrics in the alphafill.eu databank, a resource to help scientists make new hypotheses and design targeted experiments.</p><p>Predicting the three-dimensional (3D) structure of a protein based on its amino-acid sequence alone has been a major scientific challenge for decades. Recently, artificial intelligence approaches, as implemented in the AlphaFold <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> and the RoseTTAfold 2 methods, have made protein structure prediction unprecedently reliable. Both approaches predict domain structures with impressive accuracy, but flexible parts of the protein (such as loops or intrinsically disordered regions) are understandably predicted with lower accuracy and confidence. Predictions for the proteomes of 48 different organisms, as well as all SWISS-PROT <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> entries, have been publicly available in the AlphaFold protein structure database <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> -about a million predicted protein structures-at the time of this study, and more than 200 million followed in July 2022. These predicted models are already providing invaluable new biological insights regarding protein function.</p><p>The artificial intelligence prediction algorithms have not been trained to solve the protein folding problem from first principles. They have merely, yet impressively, learned the inherent rules of protein folding based on extensive training on experimentally resolved structures. However, many proteins do not occur in nature without their cofactor: myoglobin or hemoglobin need a heme to fold; zinc-finger domains are not stable without a zinc ion and many proteins can only exist as homo-or hetero-multimers <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> . The multimer issue was addressed by the development of AlphaFoldMultimer <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> and RoseTTAFold <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">7</ref> , that can predict complex protein assemblies. However, predicted structural models exclusively account for the 20 canonical amino-acid residues, and do not predict the coordinates for small molecules, ligands and cofactors typically associated with a protein.</p><p>Here, we enrich the models in the AlphaFold database by 'transplanting' small molecules and ions that have been experimentally observed in homologous protein structures. The AlphaFill procedure we present has been validated against experimental structures and applied to all AlphaFold models to create a new resource, the AlphaFill databank, which is designed to help life scientist to easily generate new hypotheses for protein function and formulate relevant research questions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The AlphaFill databank</head><p>Applying the AlphaFill approach to the AlphaFold database available in February 2022 (995,411 models) resulted in 586,137 models that had at least one transplanted compound. A total of 12,029,789 compounds were transplanted into these models. A selection of frequently transplanted compounds is listed in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>, including their 'transplantation' frequency at four levels of sequence identity (25, 30, 50 and 70%), which we chose empirically. The numbers for all transplanted compounds at 25, 30, 40, 50, 60 and 70% are available from the AlphaFill website.</p><p>All AlphaFill models are available from <ref type="url" target="https://alphafill.eu">https://alphafill.eu</ref> through a web-based user interface. To enable integration of AlphaFill data in other websites, a 3D-Beacons API (<ref type="url" target="https://github.com/3D-Beacons">https://github.com/3D-Beacons</ref>) is implemented, which is already in use to show AlphaFill entries in the PDBe-Knowledge Base <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12</ref> . In addition, the whole databank, including</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Transplanting compounds to AlphaFold models</head><p>First, we search for sequence homologs for each structure in the Alpha-Fold database in the PDB-REDO databank <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">8</ref> . We consider structures with identity higher than 25% over an aligned sequence of at least 85 residues as hits. The most common ligands in the PDB, as well as cofactors and their analogs from the CoFactor database 9 are kept as candidates for the 'transplants'. Currently, we are transplanting 2,694 different compounds that represent over 95% of all ligand occurrences in the Protein Data Bank (PDB) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">10</ref> .</p><p>Next, the selection of structures with compounds of interest are structurally aligned <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">11</ref> on the Cα-atoms of the AlphaFold model, and the root-mean-square deviation (r.m.s.d.) is calculated (global r.m.s.d.). Starting from the closest homolog, all backbone atoms within 6 Å from the atoms of each compound that will be considered for 'transplantation' are selected and used for a local structural alignment to the AlphaFold model; the r.m.s.d. from this alignment is also calculated (local r.m.s.d.). Compounds are then transplanted into the AlphaFold model to make the AlphaFill model, unless the same compound has</p><p>Table 1 | Examples of frequently transplanted compounds in the AlphaFill databank for indicative levels of sequence identity: trans., transplants Sequence identity 25% 30% 50% 70% Compound code and name No. of entries No. of transplants No. of entries No. of transplants No. of entries No. of transplants No. of entries No. of transplants Nucleotides ADP Adenosine diphosphate 100,258 242,131 77,591 166,420 26,804 42,189 10,076 13,975 AMP Adenosine monophosphate 59,639 102,608 44,548 68,972 12,811 18,334 3,951 4,881 ATP Adenosine triphosphate 67,807 119,001 51,155 83,267 14,729 22,765 5,226 7,223 GDP Guanosine diphosphate 30,839 77,253 23,810 51,240 10,986 16,702 4,831 6,353 GTP Guanosine triphosphate 18,274 30,586 14,443 23,841 5,139 7,974 2,054 2,896 UDP Uridine diphosphate 17,717 25,197 11,119 14,091 2,787 3,184 858 1,040 Cofactors COA Coenzyme A 19,037 61,080 12,344 40,880 3,162 11,751 1,369 3,109 FAD Flavin adenine dinucleotide 18,406 50,295 10,851 23,667 3,111 4,564 1,470 1,958 FMN Flavin mononucleotide 11,892 26,072 7,732 15,929 2,611 4,054 1,225 1,719 GSH Glutathione 9,764 20,884 7,535 14,186 2,113 3,021 851 1,122 HEM Heme 18,675 45,968 11,586 28,849 6,000 13,737 4,242 7,850 NAD Nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide 35,016 82,533 24,284 50,799 8,542 14,186 3,087 4,898 NAI NADH 17,223 24,848 11,370 15,858 2,881 3,858 796 1,125 NAP NAD phosphate/NADP 26,467 67,179 18,142 38,576 4,355 8,286 1,577 2,311 NDP NADPH 21,598 42,241 14,291 26,603 3,660 7,383 1,535 2,937 PLP Pyridoxal phosphate 13,462 158,684 10,119 94,516 5,016 12,904 2,131 4,978 SAH S-Adenosyl-l-homocysteine 21,121 30,189 15,692 19,778 4,184 5,079 1,399 1,629 SAM S-adenosylmethionine 21,072 32,467 16,239 23,465 4,449 7,361 1,890 2,948 Miscellaneous CLA Chlorophyll A 3,505 443,127 3,217 425,290 1,502 171,022 1,375 157,851 CLR Cholesterol 8,533 53,500 4,310 18,184 532 1,654 339 866 Metal ions CA Calcium( 2+ ) ion 202,360 759,181 145,813 473,734 40,010 117,321 15,910 47,819 K Potassium( 1+ ) ion 117,813 270,758 86,633 189,961 23,999 51,361 7,239 13,707 MG Magnesium( 2+ ) ion 328,108 1,981,187 264,320 1,576,629 95,618 514,634 33,595 91,445 NA Sodium( 1+ ) ion 272,353 1,067,005 204,482 734,824 57,076 176,645 19,793 53,329 ZN Zinc( 2+ ) ion 186,268 639,282 135,426 417,736 41,808 99,486 16,675 36,315 Resource <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y</ref> </p><p>all relevant metadata (that is, the JSON format description of all transplants for each AlphaFill model, a JSON schema with a complete description of these files and the current CIF file that describes the compounds that are considered for transfer) can be downloaded through rsync. alphafill.eu.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Validation of the AlphaFill algorithm</head><p>To validate the AlphaFill algorithm, we compared the transplants created by AlphaFill to experimental structures with 100% sequence identity. We defined the local environment validation (LEV) score as the all-atom r.m.s.d. of any ligand atom and all proteins' atoms within 6.0 Å from the ligand, between the AlphaFill and experimental complexes. The distribution of the LEV score for all AlphaFill structures within this validation set (28,619 transplants) is presented in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>. As the LEV score can be known only when a sequence-identical experimental structure is available, we then compared it to the local r.m.s.d., which we calculate for every transplant as defined above. The LEV score and the local r.m.s.d. correlate well (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>). As the local r.m.s.d. can thus be used as a proxy for the quality of each transplant, we analyzed its distribution as a function of sequence identity between the donor and the acceptor model. As expected, local r.m.s.d. goes down with increasing sequence identity (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>).</p><p>An orthogonal way to validate the quality of a transplant is to evaluate possible clashes between ligand and protein atoms. For this purpose, we defined the transplant clash score (TCS) as a function of the van der Waals overlaps between a transplanted ligand and its binding site (see Methods for details). The distribution of the TCS for all multi-atomic transplants is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1d</ref>. Single atom compounds are overrepresented in the dataset (5,170,409 compounds) and have relatively few clashes, and were thus excluded in evaluating the TCS to avoid biasing the analysis. The TCS correlates well with the LEV score (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1e</ref>). High TCS can suggest an incompatible binding site, suboptimal performance of the AlphaFill algorithm in transplanting the ligand or that the AlphaFold model has local inaccuracies. In the last two cases, clashes could be resolved by local refinement. We thus implemented a procedure using YASARA <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">13</ref> to energy minimize a complex. To test this procedure, we chose four sets of 50 complexes each: two sets were defined as the transplants with the lowest and the highest TCS, and two additional categories were chosen around 0.25 and 0.50 Å based on visual inspection of the distribution (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1d</ref>). We then evaluated the TCS before and after energy minimization (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1f</ref>). The TCS slightly increased for some structures in the set with the lowest starting TCS, but is reduced (or unchanged in a few cases) in structures in the other three sets. As the four sets were chosen from the validation set above, we then compared the LEV score before and after energy minimization (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>). For the lowest and low set, the LEV score is not strongly affected by de-clashing. For medium and highest TCS scores, in many cases the LEV score improves while for others it does not, suggesting that such transplants should be treated with caution. .d. of all transplants in the AlphaFill models as boxplots in 10% identity ranges. Boxes are based on 3,594,940; 3,866,810; 2,079,705; 1,005,953; 495,357; 369,307; 268,904 and 252,681 transplants, respectively, and extend from first to third quartile with the median as the middle line. Whiskers extend to 1.5 times the interquartile range. For clarity, 332,771; 333,325; 181,126; 79,594; 42,273; 34,634; 29,368 and 24,263 outliers, respectively, are not shown. Maximum values are 107.4, 82.1, 40.6, 37.1, 61.5, 44.4, 35.6 and 35.5 Å. d, The distribution of the TCS for all transplants in the AlphaFill models (n = 6,859,380). Mono-atomic transplants (5,170,409 compounds) are left out (main text). e, The TCS correlates with the LEV score in the validation set (n = 8,039; mono-atomic transplants were used (main text)), Pearson correlation coefficient 0.51. f, Comparison of the TCS before and after energy minimization for four subsets of the validation set (each with n = 50), illustrating that TCS improves for low until highest TCS by refinement.</p><p>Resource <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis of the quality of AlphaFill databank transplants</head><p>The validation was then used to derive quality indicators to annotate the transplants in the AlphaFill databank. As the local r.m.s.d. correlates well with the LEV score (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>), we further analyzed its distribution as a function of sequence identity (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>) to annotate the transplant. The local r.m.s.d. distribution stays fairly stable for structures with sequence identity of 70% or more (933,117 transplants). We use the values of the local r.m.s.d. exceeding the third quartile plus 1.5 times the interquartile range 14 for all transplants with sequence identity of 70% or higher (0.92 Å) and for all transplants (3.10 Å) to annotate all AlphaFill transplants as 'medium confidence' and 'low confidence', respectively (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>). Using these cutoffs 65.3% of all transplants can be considered high confidence, 24.9% medium confidence and 9.9% low confidence. As the TCS also correlates well with the LEV score (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1e</ref>), we also use it to annotate transplants. Similar to the local r.m.s.d., we used the 1.5 interquartile range cutoff for 70% identity or higher (0.64 Å) and for all transplants (1.27 Å) (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>), to assign high-confidence (81.3%), medium-confidence (18.6%) and low-confidence (0.05%) transplants based on TCS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A web-based user interface for the AlphaFill databank</head><p>All AlphaFill entries are available for visual inspection through the AlphaFill website at <ref type="url" target="https://alphafill.eu">https://alphafill.eu</ref>. On the front page, models can be retrieved using the AlphaFold identifier, which is equivalent to the UniProt primary accession code <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">15</ref> . Individual entries can also be accessed directly using the same identifier, for example, <ref type="url" target="https://alphafill.eu/?id=P02144">https://  alphafill.eu/?id=P02144</ref> for human myoglobin. The website makes the compound prevalence available (on the Compounds page), as well as numbers of occurrence regarding transplanted compounds for each 'filled' AlphaFold model (on the Structures page). The information on the Compounds and Structures pages can be filtered based on sequence identity at cutoffs of 25, 30, 40, 50, 60 and 70%. On each entry page (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>) the selected AlphaFill model is displayed using the visualization software Mol* <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">16</ref> , allowing users full flexibility for inspection. The 'transplants' are listed in a table together with  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">AF-P29373</ref>). The Mol* viewer on the left can be controlled by the table of transplanted compounds on the right. Clicking a compound in the table brings up a zoom of the binding site. Compounds can be hidden or shown individually using the tick boxes. Transplants at 70% or more sequence identity are displayed. The identity cutoff can be changed using the selector above the table. In this example, retinal (RET) inherited from PDB-REDO entry 4i9s (ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">36</ref> ) is shown and flagged with a yellow box as medium confidence due to high TCS. All other transplanted compounds are hidden from view, providing the 'optimize' option for the selected transplant. After optimization (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>) the is TCS is reduced to 0.29 Å, which is considered high confidence. A sodium from PDB-REDO entry 2frs (ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">37</ref> ) is flagged for its high local r.m.s.d.</p><p>Resource <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y</ref>  transplants can be shown at the levels of sequence identity described above. By default, the cutoff is set to the highest identity that displays hits in the table. In practice, this means that if the AlphaFold model can be mapped to an experimental structure with 93% sequence identity, by default only compounds transplanted from structures with more than 70% identity are shown; if only a 28% identical structure exists the default threshold will be set to 25%. When there is no transplant from an experimental structure with greater than 25% identity, the table is blank. A model with all the ligands and the metadata can also be downloaded. If a single transplant is selected in the table, the option to energy minimize ("optimise") that particular transplant is made available to the user. Following optimization, the TCS score before and after refinement is shown, along with a ligand-focused view (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>), and that particular optimized complex can be downloaded.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Examples</head><p>In the case of models that have identical structures in the PDB, the AlphaFill databank in part reproduces information already in the PDBe-Knowledge Base <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12</ref> . However, AlphaFill also transplants compounds from homologous experimental structures that might have been determined in another species, and also to domains for which similar domains are available experimentally. Therefore, the databank offers additional functionality for the annotation of the models that can functionally assist users to make informed decisions about these structures. Here, we will discuss a few examples.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Myoglobin and heme</head><p>Human myoglobin is an ɑ-helical protein with heme B as cofactor, binding molecular oxygen and several other small molecules. The AlphaFold model (AF-P02144) is nearly identical to experimentally determined structures, and shows a heme-shaped cavity (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref>). In the AlphaFill databank, many heme analogs (containing metals other than iron) are 'mapped' back to heme B (HEM, in PDB nomenclature) based on the data in CoFactor database. The heme analogs 6HE and 7HE that lack a carboxyl tail are not mapped back to heme B, but are instead transferred as is. Additional compounds that are transplanted to the AlphaFold myoglobin model include molecular oxygen and carbon monoxide. The latter is fitted on two locations: one close to the iron atom in heme and the other on the far side of the heme. The second carbon monoxide, located at an unexpected position, is inherited from PDB-REDO entry 1dwt (ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">17</ref> ), in which it was modeled at 30% occupancy. This occupancy is retained in the AlphaFill model to allow users to take this into account when evaluating the model. The AlphaFill model of myoglobin also contains numerous metal ions. The cobalt and nickel ions should be treated with care as they are inherited from engineered myoglobin dimers (PDB-REDO entries 7dgk and 7dgl, ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">18</ref> ) that do not have a normal myoglobin fold. This is clearly reflected by the global r.m.s.d. values being above 20 Å.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Zinc binding sites</head><p>The most common transition-metal ion present in macromolecular structures is zinc (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>). Typically, it is involved in catalysis or in maintaining structural integrity <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19</ref> . The so-called 'structural zinc ions' typically involve a tetrahedral binding site containing a combination of four coordinating cysteine and/or histidine residues <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">20</ref> . As we found before, such tetrahedrals are often distorted in the X-ray models available in the PDB, but the corresponding structures available through PDB-REDO contain improved binding sites <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21</ref> and are better suited for usage in AlphaFill.</p><p>One of the proteins that contains both functional and structural zinc ions is the STAM-binding protein, a zinc metalloprotease that cleaves lysine-63-linked polyubiquitin chains (AF-O95630) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">22</ref> . Zinc ions have been transplanted to the AlphaFill model, both at the catalytic site and at the zinc-finger motif (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4a</ref>), originating from the PDB-REDO structure 3rzv (ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">22</ref> ). The structural zinc ion is coordinated by three histidine residues and one cysteine. Although this tetrahedral zinc binding site looks proper, the atomic distances between the zinc atom and its ligands deviate from previously established target values <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21</ref> . This limitation is a consequence of AlphaFold predicting the structure outside the context of key structural elements, in this case the zinc ions. By adding the zinc atom, qualitative information is provided (the zinc atom should be in this binding site), but no quantitative information about the zinc binding site should be extracted from the AlphaFill model. Further refinement of the AlphaFill model with geometric restraints can be applied to make the binding site look more normal. A similar situation is found for the two 'transplanted' zinc ions in the human BMI-1 protein (AF-P35226), which contains two zinc binding sites involved in structural integrity <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">23</ref> (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4b</ref>). The binding sites are distorted in terms of coordination geometry with nonoptimal coordination distances and cysteine side chain conformations, but the fact that these are structural zinc binding sites is very clear. The two zinc atoms were transferred by AlphaFill from PDB-REDO entry 3rpg (ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">23</ref> ), completing the structural overview of BMI-1 with respect to structural integrity.</p><p>For 'zinc-finger protein 91', an E3 ubiquitin ligase upregulated in prostate cancer, colon cancer and pancreatic cancer <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">24</ref> , no experimental structures are available, but the human structure is predicted by AlphaFold (AF-Q05481). All transplanted zinc atoms have high global r.m.s.d. values (from 5.71 to 21.87 Å), but many have good local r.m.s.d. and TCS values. One such zinc atom is Zn AB originated in PDB-REDO entry 5wjq (ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">25</ref> ) (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4c</ref>). The global r.m.s.d. is high (8.88 Å), but the local r.m.s.d. and TCS are good (0.49 and 0.23 Å, respectively); visual inspection shows that this zinc atom is biochemically sensible and has a normal binding site. Another zinc atom placed close to the same binding site (from PDB-REDO entry 6a57, ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">26</ref> ) is marked unreliable based on the local r.m.s.d. value (4.80 Å); the positioning of this zinc ion is most likely incorrect (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4c</ref>).</p><p>In the ectonucleotide pyrophosphatase/phosphodiesterase (ENPP) family of proteins a bimetallic zinc site is important for catalysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28</ref> . A structural alignment of the catalytic domain of PDB-REDO models of ENPP1-7 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4d</ref>) shows that the zinc atoms and residues that coordinate them occupy highly similar positions in all family members. The AlphaFold predictions of the same proteins (AF-P22413, AF-Q13822, AF-O14638, AF-Q9Y6X5, AF-Q9UJA9, AF-Q6UWR7, AF-Q6UWV6 for ENPP1-7, respectively) show more divergence, especially histidine R5 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4d</ref>). AlphaFill picks up the similarity between the AlphaFold and the PDB-REDO models and transplants both zinc ions into the protein</p><p>STAM binding protein BMI-1 Zinc finger protein 91 Identity, 99%, global r.m.s.d. 0.61 Å local r.m.s.d. 0.52 Å, TCS, 0.18 Å Identity, 100%, global r.m.s.d. 0.55 Å local r.m.s.d. 0.17 Å, TCS, 0.10 Å Identity, 36%, global r.m.s.d. 8.88 Å local r.m.s.d. 0.49 Å, TCS, 0.23 Å Identity, 99%, global r.m.s.d. 0.61 Å local r.m.s.d. 0.92 Å, TCS, 0.04 Å Identity, 100%, global r.m.s.d. 0.55 Å local r.m.s.d. 0.30 Å, TCS, 0.19 Å Identity, 36%, global r.m.s.d. 8.88 Å local r.m.s.d. 4.80 Å, TCS, 0.18 Å ENPP1-7 PDB-REDO AlphaFold AlphaFill zinc binding site in ENPP1-7 as found in PDB-REDO models (PDB identifiers for ENPP1-7: 6weu, ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">38</ref> ; 5mhp, ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">39</ref> ; 6c01, ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">40</ref> ; 4lqy, ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">41</ref> ; 5veo, ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">42</ref> ; 5egh, ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">43</ref> and 5tcd, ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">44</ref> , respectively), compared to the same binding site as found in the human ENPP1-7 models from AlphaFold and as available in AlphaFill, containing the two zinc ions. For clarity, only the backbone of ENPP1 is shown as a green ribbon diagram; side chains are colored green, blue, red, pink, orange, purple and gold for ENPP1-7, respectively.</p><p>Resource <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y</ref> models of ENPPs (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4d</ref>). Histidine R5 having different rotamers in the AlphaFold predictions, which based on the experimental structures should be a single rotamer, suggests that the bimetallic zinc site in the AlphaFill model(s) could benefit from additional refinement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Kinases and ATP</head><p>Kinases are known to have multiple states between the active conformation that offers an environment conducive to the phosphotransfer reaction, and the inactive state that does not fulfill the chemical constraints required for catalytic activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29</ref> . So far, AlphaFold provides only one conformation per protein. The state to which the AlphaFold models corresponds, is not known a priori. AlphaFill, however, transfers both ADP and ATP (or their analogs) to the AlphaFold model, provided that related experimental structures are available in the PDB-REDO databank, regardless of the functional state of the kinase as characterized by the conformation of specific residues. For the human tyrosine-protein kinase ABL1 (AF-P00519) the AlphaFill model shows an ADP molecule and an ATP molecule (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5a</ref>,<ref type="figure">b</ref>) allowing different hypotheses for the functional state of this model. The global r.m.s.d. for the ADP source is 2.54 and for ATP 1.36 Å, while the local r.m.s.d. for ADP is 0.99 Å and for ATP 0.65 Å. This suggests that the structure is more representative of the ATP-bound state. The AlphaFill entry page informs the user that the ATP molecule was inherited from the 'B' chain of the experimental structure 2g2f with bound AGS (ATP-γ-S) (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5d</ref>), an ATP analog that promotes an 'intermediate' state in ABL1 (ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">30</ref> ). Likewise, the ADP has been transplanted from PDB entry 2g2i (ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">30</ref> ) (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5c</ref>), which represents an active state. Thus, the AlphaFill interface correctly highlights such differences, and allows a simple lookup of the underlying experimental models as well as associated literature to draw relevant conclusions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>Analyzing the contacts of proteins to cofactors, ligands and ions, helps understand both the function and structural integrity of proteins. They can also be helpful for designing downstream experiments, either computational or in the wet laboratory. So far, the AlphaFold database does not include these compounds, but recognizes this need as for each predicted model links to experimental structures are provided through the PDBe-Knowledge Base <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12</ref> . Here, we have presented the AlphaFill algorithm to create a resource that takes this further: we do not limit the 'transplanting' to the exact same protein, but we extend it to homologs of this model. The current AlphaFill databank contains transplants of 2,694 different ligands, out of more than 30,000 in the PDB. These represent the most commonly occurring ligands as well as all the cofactors in CoFactor database, and cover about 95% of the cumulative occurrence of ligands in the PDB. We note, that the AlphaFill software is freely available (under the BSD license), which allows users to 'submit' any structural model for evaluation, and also the possibility to consider all &gt;30,000 nonpolymer ligands in the PDB. An API to allow users to upload and 'fill' their own models or additional structures in the AlphaFold databank (added after June 2022) will be made available, also providing access to additional nonpolymer compounds from the PDB. We note, that currently AlphaFill does not handle polymer ligands, such as peptides, nucleic acids or sugars. It also does not handle posttranslational modifications and, in particular, glycosylation, which is a complicated matter that requires special attention <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">31</ref> . Other posttranslational modifications such as phosphorylation, frequently induce conformational changes and are likewise not handled in AlphaFill.</p><p>An important decision parameter in the AlphaFill algorithm is the minimum sequence identity threshold to allow transfer of information from an experimental structure to an AlphaFold model. We superpose all experimental structures that showed more than 25% sequence identity with AlphaFold models, which also have an alignment length of at least 85 amino acids. This threshold is close to the minimal sequence identity requirement for structural homology <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">32</ref> . We note that based on our experience with homology restraints <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">8</ref> and homology-based annotation of experimental structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">33</ref> that a threshold closer to 70% is much more reliable for structural details such as local residue interactions; this threshold was also reflected in the validation analysis we present here (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>). To allow users to explore possibilities, we have introduced a selector in the web interface that sets the display to the desired identity level on a per-structure basis.</p><p>Validation of AlphaFill models against experimental structures with 100% identity, has shown that the local r.m.s.d. and the TCS are good indicators for the reliability of a transplant. A clear color coding to draw the user's attention to potentially erroneous transfers, indicating medium-and low-confidence transplants based on statistical distributions of these two criteria is used. We also offer the users to run on-the-fly energy minimization to optimize a particular complex of interest. We envisage that users will inspect choices, make selections and then optimize and download the optimized structures most relevant for their research.</p><p>The global r.m.s.d. is not a good indicators of transplant quality, but is useful to get a feeling of the similarity between the donor and acceptor structures: a structure with lower global r.m.s.d. but the same or similar identity, denotes a similar conformation. This is reflected in the kinase examples (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>). We also note that, for multi-domain proteins, the sequence alignment could span all structural domains, but the relative position of each domain might be different in the experimental structure and the model. In this case, the structural alignment may have inflated global r.m.s.d. values due to different relative domain positions. This was observed in the Zn transfer for zinc-finger protein 91 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4c</ref>).  <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">30</ref> ), which represents an active kinase state. d, ABL1 kinase bound with AGS in PDB-REDO entry 2g2f (ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">30</ref> ), which represents an 'intermediate' kinase state. The kinase is presented as gray ribbon diagram for all panels, ligands are in blue cylinders colored by atom type for noncarbon atoms, and magnesium ions are shown as blush pink spheres.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Resource</head><p><ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y</ref> </p><p>The AlphaFill structure models are not meant to be accurate or precise or complete representations of the full repertoire of ligands for a certain protein structure. They are meant as a tool for the nonexpert to help them explore complexes with common ligands. Structural biology or structural bioinformatics experts would find it trivial to select, superpose and 'transplant' a functional or structural cofactor or ion and take that information to be validated by molecular dynamics simulations and mutagenesis studies, or use it for discussing the structure of a model in light of new biochemical or biophysical insights.</p><p>It is good to keep in mind that the AlphaFill models are not very suitable for precise quantification of interactions between the transferred ligand(s) and the protein (for example, hydrogen bonds, π-π or cation-π interactions, van der Waals interactions, hydrophobic interactions, halogen bonds). Namely, this requires coordinate precision that is not provided by either the AlphaFold or the AlphaFill models (even after optimization). Hence, the models should be interpreted in a qualitative manner. Moreover, in some cases ligand interactions involve parts of the protein that are not modeled with high confidence by AlphaFold; while optimization might improve the local environment, we advise caution.</p><p>Besides using several optimized and robust defaults, the AlphaFill software is made to be flexible by design so that the used settings and cutoffs can easily be tailored to any user's own purposes. Similarly, the list of transferrable compounds can readily be updated based on user requirements; we invite users to provide constructive feedback to allow to further develop these services.</p><p>AlphaFill by definition depends on high-quality structure homologs as the first and main criterion for transferring ligands. However, it is well established that certain structural domains can occur outside the context of extensive sequence similarity as it has been shown for example by DALI <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">34</ref> and PDBeFold <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">35</ref> . Thus, AlphaFill could be complemented by structure-based transfer algorithms based on deep learning concepts similar to those used for the AlphaFold structure prediction revolution.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Resource</head><p><ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Detailed overview of the procedure</head><p>The AlphaFill procedure for filling up missing information to AlphaFold models goes through the following steps.</p><p>(1) The amino-acid sequence of each AlphaFold model is BLASTed <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">45</ref> against the sequence file of the LAHMA webserver <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">33</ref> , which contains all sequences present in the PDB-REDO databank. The alignments, that is individual high-scoring segment pairs (HSPs) are sorted by E value to capture both the sequence similarity and the length of the alignment as they are combined factors in conferring structural homology. A maximum of 250 hits, as is the default for BLAST, is returned. (2) The structure models corresponding to these hits are retrieved from the PDB-REDO databank and checked for compounds of interest for the AlphaFill algorithm (vide infra).</p><p>(3) The hits with compounds of interest are filtered to ensure that only sufficiently close homologs are used. Currently, we use a sequence identity cutoff of 25% over an aligned HSP of at least 85 residues. For such an alignment length, identities as low as 25% still confer overall structural homology <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">32</ref> . (4) This selection of hits is structurally aligned <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">11</ref> on the Cα-atoms of the residues that match in the BLAST alignment. The r.m.s.d. of this global alignment is stored in the AlphaFill metadata. Note that a single PDB-REDO model chain can have several HSPs. These are aligned individually. (5) Starting from the hit with the smallest BLAST E value, each compound of interest in the hit list is scanned for its local surroundings. All backbone atoms within 6 Å are then used for a local structural alignment to the AlphaFold model. The r.m.s.d. of this local alignment is also stored in the AlphaFill metadata. (6) Compounds are then integrated into the AlphaFold model to make its AlphaFill counterpart, unless the same compound has already been placed within 3.5 Å of the centroid of the compound to be fitted (originating from a previously considered homolog) or no protein atoms are present within 4.0 Å from the atoms of the compound to be fitted. If compounds have multiple conformations, all of these are included in the Alpha-Fill model. Descriptions of covalent bonds or metal binding captured in so-called struct_conn records are also added to the AlphaFill model. (7) For each transplant a TCS is calculated using equation (1) and stored in the metadata. The TCS is the r.m.s. van der Waals overlap over all atomic distances between the transplant atoms and the protein that are shorter than 4 Å. TCS = √ √ √ √ vd Waals overlap 2 i + vd Waals overlap 2 j + vd Waals overlap 2 k + … Number of distances considered (1)</p><p>The AlphaFill model with all transplanted compounds is finally stored as mmCIF coordinate file together with a JSON-formatted metadata file describing the provenance of each transplanted compound.</p><p>The running time per model depends strongly on the number of BLAST hits and compounds to be transferred. The mean running time is 2 minutes per model on a single CPU thread.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Input data: protein structure models</head><p>All AlphaFold models 1 (available 1 February 2021) were downloaded from the AlphaFold Protein Structure Database's FTP archive. A local copy of the PDB-REDO databank 8 was used to provide ligands for transfer.</p><p>To find all relevant PDB-REDO entries for a specific Alpha-Fold model through sequence-based retrieval with BLAST, a PDB-REDO-specific sequence database (as of 1 February 2021) was used. This database is created automatically as part of the weekly LAHMA and PDB-REDO databank updates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Input data: selection of chemical compounds</head><p>We decided to only consider compounds that likely represent common biological states and are likely suited for further study. Thus, a collection of common biologically relevant cofactors, ligands and metal ions was created.</p><p>The selection of biological relevant ligands to be added to the AlphaFold models was performed based on the number of their occurrences in the PDB. All ligands covering about 95% of the cumulative occurrence of all ligands in the PDB were in the initial AlphaFill compound list that was complemented with all cofactors and their analogs present in the organic CoFactor database 9 that were not within the 95% cumulative occurrence. To map cofactor analogs and adducts to their canonical cofactors where possible, analogs were mapped to their representative cofactor by atom renaming (and atom deletion); for example, adenosine-5′-(beta,gamma-methylene)triphosphate (methylene substituted ATP) is translated to ATP, as ATP is the compound involved in biological processes. Cofactor adducts such as CNC (vitamin B12 in complex with cyanide) are trimmed down to their parent (for example, vitamin B12 in the CNC case) by atom deletion. Cofactor analogs that have atoms missing with respect to their parent are kept as is. The required changes were found by visual inspection of the compounds via the Ligand-Expo website <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">46</ref> and the PDB web sites. Common crystallization agents (for example, poly-ethyleneglycol and chloride), some metals with unclear physiological importance (for example, cadmium ions), posttranslational modifications (modified amino acids) and other polymers (peptides, nucleic acids and carbohydrates) were purposely excluded. All information was stored in a CIF-formatted data file that can easily be extended.</p><p>The current collection of compounds to be transplanted consists of 2,694 entries. It is stored separate from the AlphaFill program to allow easy extension in future incarnations of the AlphaFill databank and is freely available.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The AlphaFill software</head><p>A new program, AlphaFill, was created for the purpose of this study. AlphaFill reads an AlphaFold model together with the compound list and the PDB-REDO-specific sequence database and structures, and returns a structure model consisting of the coordinates of the AlphaFold model plus all transferred compounds. See above for the compound transfer procedure. The AlphaFill program is based on the libzeep <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">48</ref> , libcif++ (ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">49</ref> ) (a general purpose C++ library for dealing with mmCIF data structures), libpdb-redo (a core library for PDB-REDO software) and clipper <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">50</ref> libraries, and contains its own BLAST implementation. The source codes of AlphaFill, libcif++ and libpdb-redo are available from <ref type="url" target="https://github.com/PDB-REDO">https://github.com/PDB-REDO</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Creation of the AlphaFill databank</head><p>The AlphaFill databank was created by running AlphaFill over all Alpha-Fold models. The computational workload is parallel that allows orchestration of the calculations by using the software make <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">51</ref> , as we have done previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">52</ref> , with the AlphaFold coordinate files as sources and the AlphaFill coordinate files as targets. The calculation took 15 days on a server with a total of 90 CPU threads.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The AlphaFill web interface</head><p>The web site was created as a web application using the libzeep library that offers an HTTP server, HTML templating and many other components for web server construction in C++. Handling of mmCIF files is done using libcif++. The data for the Models, Structures and Compounds pages are stored in a PostgreSQL <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">53</ref> database. The model is presented on the page using Mol* <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">16</ref> as an interactive web component. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Validation of the AlphaFill algorithm</head><p>To validate the AlphaFill algorithm, all transplanted compounds that were obtained from a donor PDB-REDO model with 100% sequence identity were selected as validation set (28,619 transplants). For each compound in this set, we calculated the all-atom r.m.s.d. with respect to the donor model for the transplant binding site that we called the LEV score. The transplant binding site consists of all nonhydrogen atoms of the transplant and all nonhydrogen protein atoms within 6.0 Å of the transplant atoms.</p><p>The LEV score was correlated to the local r.m.s.d. and to the TCS, which are both calculated in the AlphaFill algorithm for each transplant. The Pearson correlation coefficient was calculated using DataFrame. corr() in pandas v.1.2.4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Model refinement</head><p>The AlphaFill web interface allows the refinement of individual transplants in the context of the protein. When a single transplant is selected, a user can activate its refinement. A new structure file containing only the protein and the selected transplant is created and passed to the refinement engine that runs on the server backend. The refinement procedure is based on the 'Energy minimization' experiment in YASARA <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">13</ref> that consists of a steepest descent minimization followed by a short simulated annealing in the updated YASARA NOVA <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">54</ref> force field. All default settings are used and forcefield parameters for the transplant are generated on-the-fly by YASARA. After the energy minimization, the TCS of the transplant is recalculated. The original and new TCS values are displayed together with a Mol* viewer of the refined model. The refined model can also be downloaded.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Validation of the refinement procedure</head><p>The refinement engine provides the option to energy minimize a specific transplant in complex with the protein on demand.</p><p>To validate the refinement results, the TCS and LEV score before and after refinement were obtained and analyzed for four subsets of compounds in the validation set: (1) the 50 lowest TCS, (2) the 50 transplants with TCS closest to 0.25 Å, (3) the 50 transplants with TCS closest to 0.50 Å and (4) the 50 transplants with the highest TCS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Model and data analysis</head><p>The AlphaFill models were analyzed visually using Coot <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">55</ref> , the Alpha-Fill website and CCP4mg (ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">56</ref> ). Plots were made using Seaborn <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">57</ref> , molecular graphics figures were made with CCP4mg. Data analyses for validation were performed using Python v.3.7.9 with the numpy v.1.20.3 and pandas v.1.2.4 packages.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 |</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1 | Validation of the AlphaFill algorithm. a, Distribution of the LEV score of all transplants obtained with 100% sequence identity (the validation set with n = 28,619 independent observations). 408 transplants (1%) with LEV score &gt;2.5 are not shown for clarity. b, The local r.m.s.d. correlates with the LEV score in the validation set, Pearson correlation coefficient 0.51 (n = 8,039; mono-atomic transplants were not used (main text)). c, Distribution of the local r.m.s.d. of all transplants in the AlphaFill models as boxplots in 10% identity ranges. Boxes are based on 3,594,940; 3,866,810; 2,079,705; 1,005,953; 495,357; 369,307; 268,904 and 252,681 transplants, respectively, and extend from first to third quartile with the median as the middle line. Whiskers extend to 1.5 times the interquartile</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 |</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2 | Screenshot of the AlphaFill entry page for cellular retinoic acidbinding protein 2 (AF-P29373). The Mol* viewer on the left can be controlled by the table of transplanted compounds on the right. Clicking a compound in the table brings up a zoom of the binding site. Compounds can be hidden or shown individually using the tick boxes. Transplants at 70% or more sequence identity are displayed. The identity cutoff can be changed using the selector above the</figDesc><graphic coords="4,40.37,48.96,520.20,407.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><figDesc>Resource https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y the parent PDB-REDO entry, the global r.m.s.d. between the AlphaFold model and for the hit within the PDB-REDO entry (as a measure of the similarity between the donor and the acceptor structure), the name of the compound (plus the original name if it was mapped), the local r.m.s.d. and the TCS (as quality indicators). Transplants are grouped by compound and sorted by r.m.s.d. (global at the hit level and local at the individual compound level). Clicking a row in the table changes the focus of the viewer to that compound. Compounds can also be toggled on and off to reduce clutter. Transplants are colored in the table by the local r.m.s.d.-based and the TCS-based confidence level (as defined above). Medium-confidence transplants that should be handled with care are marked in yellow; low-confidence transplants requiring caution are marked in red. Using the selector above the table,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 |</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3 | Human myoglobin structures in AlphaFold and AlphaFill. a, The ribbon diagram of the AlphaFold model of human myoglobin. b, The heme-shaped cavity in the AlphaFold model, wherein the histidine side chains (gray cylinders colored by atom type) are ready to facilitate the heme biding. c, The heme-shaped cavity in the AlphaFill model, wherein the binding site is 'filled' with the transplanted heme group and the CO and O 2 ligands; ligands are shown in stickmode colored by atom type (heme) with the heme iron as a gray sphere.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,117.27,62.97,368.40,125.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 4 |</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4 | Examples of transplanted zinc ions (purple spheres). All proteins are presented as a ribbon diagram (each protein in a different color, for clarity); side chains coordinating the zinc ions are shown as cylinders colored by atom type for noncarbon atoms. a, A catalytic (top) and a structural (bottom) zinc ion in the STAM-binding protein. b, Two structural zinc ions in the human BMI-1. c, Zinc ion transferred into a structural zinc binding site in the zinc-finger protein 91 (top), wrongly placed zinc ion in the same protein (bottom). d, The bimetallic</figDesc><graphic coords="6,116.44,66.46,368.16,384.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 |</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5 | AlphaFill helps to understand the activation state of the Abl kinase AlphaFold model. a, AlphaFill model of the ABL1 kinase with ADP and magnesium ions shown. The state of the kinase is not known a priori. b, AlphaFill model of the ABL1 kinase with ATP (mapped from AGS) bound. c, ADP binding site of the human ABL1 kinase in PDB-REDO entry 2g2i (ref.<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">30</ref> ), which represents an active kinase state. d, ABL1 kinase bound with AGS in PDB-REDO entry 2g2f (ref.<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">30</ref> ), which represents an 'intermediate' kinase state. The kinase is presented as gray ribbon diagram for all panels, ligands are in blue cylinders colored by atom type for noncarbon atoms, and magnesium ions are shown as blush pink spheres.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,40.91,64.99,253.20,207.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><figDesc>Resourcehttps://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We thank the <rs type="institution" subtype="infrastructure">Research High Performance Computing facility</rs> of the <rs type="institution">Netherlands Cancer Institute</rs> for providing and maintaining computation resources and <rs type="person">S. McNicholas</rs> for support with CCP4mg. This work has been supported by <rs type="funder">iNEXT-Discovery</rs>, project number <rs type="grantNumber">871037</rs> to A.P., funded by the <rs type="programName">Horizon 2020 program</rs> of the European Commission and by an institutional grant of the <rs type="funder">Dutch Cancer Society and of the Dutch Ministry of Health, Welfare and Sport</rs>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. We thank all colleagues at <rs type="institution">B8</rs> for useful discussions and reading this manuscript, in particular, <rs type="person">J. Bak</rs>, <rs type="person">A. Murachelli</rs>, <rs type="person">R. Xie</rs>, <rs type="person">T. Brummelkamp</rs> and <rs type="person">T. Sixma</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_CCtBzu9">
					<idno type="grant-number">871037</idno>
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">Horizon 2020 program</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<listOrg type="infrastructure">
				<org type="infrastructure">					<orgName type="extracted">Research High Performance Computing facility</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data availability</head><p>All input data used in this study are freely available from PDB-REDO (<ref type="url" target="https://pdb-redo.eu">https://pdb-redo.eu</ref>), AlphaFold (<ref type="url" target="https://alphafold.ebi.ac.uk/">https://alphafold.ebi.ac.uk/</ref>) and CoFactor (<ref type="url" target="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/thornton-srv/databases/CoFactor/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/thornton-srv/databases/CoFactor/</ref>). All data discussed in this paper are publicly available from <ref type="url" target="https://alphafill.eu">https://  alphafill.eu</ref>. An individual AlphaFill entry (entryid) can be downloaded via the graphical user interface. In addition, structure files in mmCIF format are available for every entry at: <ref type="url" target="https://alphafill.eu/">https://alphafill.eu/</ref> v1/aff/${entryid}. JSON files with the metadata for the transplants are available at: <ref type="url" target="https://alphafill.eu/v1/aff/">https://alphafill.eu/v1/aff/</ref>${entryid}/json. The JSON schema providing details on the metadata is at <ref type="url" target="https://alphafill.eu/alphafill.json.schema">https://alphafill.eu/  alphafill.json.schema</ref>. The complete AlphaFill databank can be freely downloaded by the command: rsync -av rsync://rsync.alphafill.eu/ alphafill {destination folder}/.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Code availability</head><p>The AlphaFill code used for this study is available through Zenodo at <ref type="url" target="https://zenodo.org/record/6706668#.Y2EXV3bP2Uk">https://zenodo.org/record/6706668#.Y2EXV3bP2Uk</ref>. Current and future versions are open source with a BSD-2-clause license and available from <ref type="url" target="https://github.com/PDB-REDO/alphafill">https://github.com/PDB-REDO/alphafill</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Resource</head><p><ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y</ref> </p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Online content</head><p>Any methods, additional references, Nature Portfolio reporting summaries, source data, extended data, supplementary information, acknowledgements, peer review information; details of author contributions and competing interests; and statements of data and code availability are available at <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y">https://doi.org/10.1038/  s41592-022-01685-y</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reporting summary</head><p>Further information on research design is available in the Nature Portfolio Reporting Summary linked to this article.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author contributions</head><p>M.L.H. developed the AlphaFill software and web interface. I.d.V. analyzed chemical compounds for integration, worked on validation, data FAIRification and prepared the example cases and related figures. A.P. and R.P.J. conceived and supervised the project. All authors contributed to writing the manuscript, the experimental and algorithmic design and the analysis of the results.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Competing interests</head><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional information</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary information</head><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at <ref type="url" target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y</ref>.</p><p>Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to Robbie P. Joosten or Anastassis Perrakis.</p><p>Peer review information Nature Methods thanks the anonymous reviewers for their contribution to the peer review of this work. Arunima, Singh was the primary editor on this article and managed its editorial process and peer review in collaboration with the rest of the Nature Methods team.</p><p>Reprints and permissions information is available at <ref type="url" target="http://www.nature.com/reprints">www.nature.com/reprints</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>nature research | reporting summary</head><p>April 2020</p><p>Corresponding author(s):</p><p>Anastassis Perrakis (a.perrakis@nki.nl), Robbie P. Joosten (r.joosten@nki.nl) Last updated by author(s): Sep 5, 2022   Repor�ng Summary Nature Research wishes to improve the reproducibility of the work that we publish. This form provides structure for consistency and transparency in repor�ng. For further informa�on on Nature Research policies, see our Editorial Policies and the Editorial Policy Checklist.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sta�s�cs</head><p>For all sta�s�cal analyses, confirm that the following items are present in the figure legend, table legend, main text, or Methods sec�on.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>n/a Confirmed</head><p>The exact sample size (n) for each experimental group/condi�on, given as a discrete number and unit of measurement A statement on whether measurements were taken from dis�nct samples or whether the same sample was measured repeatedly</p><p>The sta�s�cal test(s) used AND whether they are one-or two-sided Only common tests should be described solely by name; describe more complex techniques in the Methods section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A descrip�on of all covariates tested</head><p>A descrip�on of any assump�ons or correc�ons, such as tests of normality and adjustment for mul�ple comparisons A full descrip�on of the sta�s�cal parameters including central tendency (e.g. means) or other basic es�mates (e.g. regression coefficient) AND varia�on (e.g. standard devia�on) or associated es�mates of uncertainty (e.g. confidence intervals) For null hypothesis tes�ng, the test sta�s�c (e.g. F, t, r) with confidence intervals, effect sizes, degrees of freedom and P value noted Give P values as exact values whenever suitable.</p><p>For Bayesian analysis, informa�on on the choice of priors and Markov chain Monte Carlo se�ngs For hierarchical and complex designs, iden�fica�on of the appropriate level for tests and full repor�ng of outcomes Es�mates of effect sizes (e.g. Cohen's d, Pearson's r), indica�ng how they were calculated Our web collection on statistics for biologists contains articles on many of the points above.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>So�ware and code</head><p>Policy informa�on about availability of computer code Data collec�on No specific data collec�on so�ware was used. The AlphaFill code used for this study is available through Zenodo with DOI: 10.5281/ zenodo.6706668. Current and future versions are open source with a BSD-2-clause license and available from h�ps://github.com/PDB-REDO/ alphafill.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data analysis</head><p>Data analyses for valida�on were performed using Python3.7.9 with the numpy version 1.20.3 and pandas version 1.2.4 packages. Visual examina�on of models was performed with Coot versions 0.8.9.2 to 0.9.8.3.</p><p>For manuscripts u�lizing custom algorithms or so�ware that are central to the research but not yet described in published literature, so�ware must be made available to editors and reviewers. We strongly encourage code deposi�on in a community repository (e.g. GitHub). See the Nature Research guidelines for submi�ng code &amp; so�ware for further informa�on.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Policy informa�on about availability of data</head><p>All manuscripts must include a data availability statement. This statement should provide the following informa�on, where applicable:</p><p>-Accession codes, unique iden�fiers, or web links for publicly available datasets -A list of figures that have associated raw data -A descrip�on of any restric�ons on data availability All input data used in this study are freely available from PDB-REDO (h�ps://pdb-redo.eu), AlphaFold (h�ps://alphafold.ebi.ac.uk/), and CoFactor (h�p:// <ref type="url" target="www.ebi.ac.uk/thornton-srv/databases/CoFactor/">www.ebi.ac.uk/thornton-srv/databases/CoFactor/</ref>). All data created and discussed in this paper are publicly available from h�ps://alphafill.eu. An individual AlphaFill entry (entryid) can be downloaded via the graphical user interface. In addi�on, structure files in mmCIF format are available for every entry at: "h�ps://alphafill.eu/v1/aff/${entryid}". JSON files with the meta-data for the transplants are available at: "h�ps://alphafill.eu/v1/aff/${entryid}/json". The JSON-schema providing details on the metadata is at "h�ps://</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Field-specific reporting</head><p>Please select the one below that is the best fit for your research. If you are not sure, read the appropriate sections before making your selection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Life sciences Behavioural &amp; social sciences Ecological, evolutionary &amp; environmental sciences</head><p>For a reference copy of the document with all sections, see nature.com/documents/nr-reporting-summary-flat.pdf</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Life sciences study design</head><p>All studies must disclose on these points even when the disclosure is negative.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sample size</head><p>The sample consisted of all AlphaFold entries (February 2022), n = 995411 Data exclusions No data were excluded</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Replication</head><p>The study was computational and non-stochastic which made replication unnecessary. That is, any repeat calculation with the same input will return exactly the same results.</p><p>Randomization Rather than performing calculations on random subsets of the AlphaFold Databank, the entire data set was considered. Therefore randomisation was not applicable as there is no sampling.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Blinding</head><p>The study was purely computational and contained no aspects where the use of blinding has any effect on the outcome of the performed calculations.</p><p>Reporting for specific materials, systems and methods</p><p>We require information from authors about some types of materials, experimental systems and methods used in many studies. Here, indicate whether each material, system or method listed is relevant to your study. If you are not sure if a list item applies to your research, read the appropriate section before selecting a response. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Highly accurate protein structure prediction with AlphaFold</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jumper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">596</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="583" to="589" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Jumper, J. et al. Highly accurate protein structure prediction with AlphaFold. Nature 596, 583-589 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate prediction of protein structures and interactions using a three-track neural network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Baek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">373</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="871" to="876" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Baek, M. et al. Accurate prediction of protein structures and interactions using a three-track neural network. Science 373, 871-876 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The SWISS-PROT protein sequence database and its supplement TrEMBL in 2000</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bairoch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Apweiler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bairoch, A. &amp; Apweiler, R. The SWISS-PROT protein sequence database and its supplement TrEMBL in 2000. Nucleic Acids Res. 28, 45-48 (2000).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Highly accurate protein structure prediction for the human proteome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tunyasuvunakool</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">596</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="590" to="596" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tunyasuvunakool, K. et al. Highly accurate protein structure prediction for the human proteome. Nature 596, 590-596 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AI revolutions in biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Perrakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sixma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">54046</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Perrakis, A. &amp; Sixma, T. K. AI revolutions in biology. EMBO Rep. 22, e54046 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Protein complex prediction with AlphaFold-Multimer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1101/2021.10.04.463034v1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/1" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Preprint at</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Evans, R. et al. Protein complex prediction with AlphaFold-Multimer. Preprint at https://www.biorxiv.org/content/1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1101/2021.10.04.463034v1</idno>
		<idno>1101/2021.10.04</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">463034</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">1101/2021.10.04.463034v1 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computed structures of core eukaryotic protein complexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Humphreys</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4805</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Humphreys, I. R. et al. Computed structures of core eukaryotic protein complexes. Science 10, eabm4805 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homology-based hydrogen bond information improves crystallographic structures in the PDB</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Van Beusekom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="798" to="808" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">van Beusekom, B. et al. Homology-based hydrogen bond information improves crystallographic structures in the PDB. Protein Sci. 27, 798-808 (2018).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The CoFactor database: organic cofactors in enzyme catalysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Holliday</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Thornton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2496" to="2497" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Fischer, J. D., Holliday, G. L. &amp; Thornton, J. M. The CoFactor database: organic cofactors in enzyme catalysis. Bioinformatics 26, 2496-2497 (2010).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein Data Bank: the single global archive for 3D macromolecular structure data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Burley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">528</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Burley, S. K. et al. Protein Data Bank: the single global archive for 3D macromolecular structure data. Nucleic Acids Res. 47, D520- D528 (2019).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The quaternion-based spatial-coordinate and orientation-frame alignment problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta. Cryst. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="432" to="457" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hanson, A. J. The quaternion-based spatial-coordinate and orientation-frame alignment problems. Acta. Cryst. A. 76, 432-457 (2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PDBe-KB: a community-driven resource for structural and functional annotations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pdbe-Kb</forename><surname>Consortium</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="344" to="D353" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">PDBe-KB consortium. PDBe-KB: a community-driven resource for structural and functional annotations. Nucleic Acids Res. 48, D344-D353 (2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">YASARA View-molecular graphics for all devices-from smartphones to workstations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Krieger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Vriend</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2981" to="2982" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Krieger, E. &amp; Vriend, G. YASARA View-molecular graphics for all devices-from smartphones to workstations. Bioinformatics 30, 2981-2982 (2014).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tukey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Exploratory Data Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tukey, J. W. Exploratory Data Analysis (Addison-Wesley, 1977).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">UniProt: the universal protein knowledgebase in 2021</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The UniProt Consortium</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="480" to="D489" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">The UniProt Consortium. UniProt: the universal protein knowledgebase in 2021. Nucleic Acids Res. 49, D480-D489 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mol* Viewer: modern web app for 3D visualization and analysis of large biomolecular structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sehnal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="W437" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sehnal, D. et al. Mol* Viewer: modern web app for 3D visualization and analysis of large biomolecular structures. Nucleic Acids Res. 49, W431-W437 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure of a ligand-binding intermediate in wild-type carbonmonoxy myoglobin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">403</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="921" to="923" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chu, K. et al. Structure of a ligand-binding intermediate in wild-type carbonmonoxy myoglobin. Nature 403, 921-923 (2000).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rational design of metal-binding sites in domain-swapped myoglobin dimers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nagao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Idomoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Shibata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Higuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hirota</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Inorg. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">217</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">111374</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nagao, S., Idomoto, A., Shibata, N., Higuchi, Y. &amp; Hirota, S. Rational design of metal-binding sites in domain-swapped myoglobin dimers. J. Inorg. Biochem. 217, 111374 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of zinc binding sites in protein crystal structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Alberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nadassy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wodak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1700" to="1716" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Alberts, I. L., Nadassy, K. &amp; Wodak, S. J. Analysis of zinc binding sites in protein crystal structures. Protein Sci. 7, 1700-1716 (1998).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolution of binding sites for zinc and calcium ions playing structural roles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Torrance</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Macarthur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Thornton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="813" to="830" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Torrance, J. W., MacArthur, M. W. &amp; Thornton, J. M. Evolution of binding sites for zinc and calcium ions playing structural roles. Proteins 71, 813-830 (2008).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Validation and correction of Zn-CysxHisy complexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Touw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Van Beusekom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M G</forename><surname>Evers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Vriend</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Joosten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Cryst. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1110" to="1118" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Touw, W. G., van Beusekom, B., Evers, J. M. G., Vriend, G. &amp; Joosten, R. P. Validation and correction of Zn-CysxHisy complexes. Acta Cryst. D. 72, 1110-1118 (2016).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural and thermodynamic comparison of the catalytic domain of AMSH and AMSH-LP: nearly identical fold but different stability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Paul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-I</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Das</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">413</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="416" to="429" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Davies, C. W., Paul, L. N., Kim, M.-I. &amp; Das, C. Structural and thermodynamic comparison of the catalytic domain of AMSH and AMSH-LP: nearly identical fold but different stability. J. Mol. Biol. 413, 416-429 (2011).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recognition of UbcH5c and the nucleosome by the Bmi1/Ring1b ubiquitin ligase complex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bentley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3285" to="3297" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bentley, M. L. et al. Recognition of UbcH5c and the nucleosome by the Bmi1/Ring1b ubiquitin ligase complex. EMBO J. 30, 3285-3297 (2011).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Zinc finger protein 91 accelerates tumour progression by activating β-catenin signalling in pancreatic cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Prolif</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13031</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tang, N. et al. Zinc finger protein 91 accelerates tumour progression by activating β-catenin signalling in pancreatic cancer. Cell Prolif. 54, e13031 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DNA conformation induces adaptable binding by tandem zinc finger proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">173</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Patel, A. et al. DNA conformation induces adaptable binding by tandem zinc finger proteins. Cell 173, 221-233.e12 (2018).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crystal structures of REF6 and its complex with DNA reveal diverse recognition mechanisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Tian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Discov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">17</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Tian, Z. et al. Crystal structures of REF6 and its complex with DNA reveal diverse recognition mechanisms. Cell Discov. 6, 17 (2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NPP-type ectophosphodiesterases: unity in diversity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Stefan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bollen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Biochem. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="542" to="550" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Stefan, C., Jansen, S. &amp; Bollen, M. NPP-type ectophosphodiesterases: unity in diversity. Trends Biochem. Sci. 30, 542-550 (2005).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and function of the ecto-nucleotide pyrophosphatase/ phosphodiesterase (ENPP) family: tidying up diversity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Borza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Salgado-Polo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Moolenaar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Perrakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">298</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">101526</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Borza, R., Salgado-Polo, F., Moolenaar, W. H. &amp; Perrakis, A. Structure and function of the ecto-nucleotide pyrophosphatase/ phosphodiesterase (ENPP) family: tidying up diversity. J. Biol. Chem. 298, 101526 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defining a new nomenclature for the structures of active and inactive kinases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Modi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Dunbrack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci</title>
		<meeting>Natl Acad. Sci<address><addrLine>USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6818" to="6827" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Modi, V. &amp; Dunbrack, R. L. Defining a new nomenclature for the structures of active and inactive kinases. Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA 116, 6818-6827 (2019).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Src-like inactive conformation in the Abl tyrosine kinase domain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Levinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">144</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Levinson, N. M. et al. A Src-like inactive conformation in the Abl tyrosine kinase domain. PLoS Biol. 4, e144 (2006). Resource https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01685-y</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The case for post-predictional modifications in the AlphaFold Protein Structure Database</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bagdonas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fogarty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fadda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Agirre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="869" to="870" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bagdonas, H., Fogarty, C. A., Fadda, E. &amp; Agirre, J. The case for post-predictional modifications in the AlphaFold Protein Structure Database. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol. 28, 869-870 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Database of homology-derived protein structures and the structural meaning of sequence alignment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Sander, C. &amp; Schneider, R. Database of homology-derived protein structures and the structural meaning of sequence alignment. Proteins 9, 56-68 (1991).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LAHMA: structure analysis through local annotation of homology-matched amino acids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Van Beusekom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta. Cryst. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">van Beusekom, B. et al. LAHMA: structure analysis through local annotation of homology-matched amino acids. Acta. Cryst. D. 77, 28-40 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Holm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Structural Bioinformatics: Methods and Protocols</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="42" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Holm, L. in Structural Bioinformatics: Methods and Protocols (ed. Gáspári, Z.) 29-42 (Springer, 2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Secondary-structure matching (SSM), a new tool for fast protein structure alignment in three dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Krissinel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Henrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Cryst. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2256" to="2268" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Krissinel, E. &amp; Henrick, K. Secondary-structure matching (SSM), a new tool for fast protein structure alignment in three dimensions. Acta Cryst. D. 60, 2256-2268 (2004).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rational design of a colorimetric pH sensor from a soluble retinoic acid chaperone</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Berbasova</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">135</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16111" to="16119" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Berbasova, T. et al. Rational design of a colorimetric pH sensor from a soluble retinoic acid chaperone. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 135, 16111-16119 (2013).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The structure of apo-wild-type cellular retinoic acid binding protein II at 1.4 Å and its relationship to ligand binding and nuclear translocation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vaezeslami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mathes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Vasileiou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Borhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Geiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">363</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="687" to="701" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Vaezeslami, S., Mathes, E., Vasileiou, C., Borhan, B. &amp; Geiger, J. H. The structure of apo-wild-type cellular retinoic acid binding protein II at 1.4 Å and its relationship to ligand binding and nuclear translocation. J. Mol. Biol. 363, 687-701 (2006).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crystal structures of human ENPP1 in apo and bound forms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Dennis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Cryst. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="889" to="898" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Dennis, M. L. et al. Crystal structures of human ENPP1 in apo and bound forms. Acta Cryst. D. 76, 889-898 (2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">-hydroxyazetidin-1-yl)-2-oxoethyl]piperazin-1-yl]-8-methylimidazo[1,2-a]pyridin-3-yl]methylamino]-4-(4-fluorophenyl)thiazole-5-carbonitrile(glpg1690), a first-in-class autotaxin inhibitor undergoing clinical evaluation for the treatment of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Desroy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>2-ethyl-6-[4-[2- (3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3580" to="3590" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Discovery of</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Desroy, N. et al. Discovery of 2-[[2-ethyl-6-[4-[2- (3-hydroxyazetidin-1-yl)-2-oxoethyl]piperazin-1-yl]- 8-methylimidazo[1,2-a]pyridin-3-yl]methylamino]-4- (4-fluorophenyl)thiazole-5-carbonitrile(glpg1690), a first-in-class autotaxin inhibitor undergoing clinical evaluation for the treatment of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. J. Med. Chem. 60, 3580-3590 (2017).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural basis for nucleotide recognition by the ectoenzyme CD203c</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gorelik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Randriamihaja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Illes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Nagar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FEBS J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">285</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2481" to="2494" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gorelik, A., Randriamihaja, A., Illes, K. &amp; Nagar, B. Structural basis for nucleotide recognition by the ectoenzyme CD203c. FEBS J. 285, 2481-2494 (2018).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular basis of purinergic signal metabolism by ectonucleotide pyrophosphatase/ phosphodiesterases 4 and 1 and implications in stroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Albright</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">289</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3294" to="3306" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Albright, R. A. et al. Molecular basis of purinergic signal metabolism by ectonucleotide pyrophosphatase/ phosphodiesterases 4 and 1 and implications in stroke. J. Biol. Chem. 289, 3294-3306 (2014).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A key tyrosine substitution restricts nucleotide hydrolysis by the ectoenzyme NPP5</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gorelik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Randriamihaja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Illes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Nagar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FEBS J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">284</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3718" to="3726" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gorelik, A., Randriamihaja, A., Illes, K. &amp; Nagar, B. A key tyrosine substitution restricts nucleotide hydrolysis by the ectoenzyme NPP5. FEBS J. 284, 3718-3726 (2017).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and biological function of ENPP6, a choline-specific glycerophosphodiester-phosphodiesterase</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Morita</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20995</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Morita, J. et al. Structure and biological function of ENPP6, a choline-specific glycerophosphodiester-phosphodiesterase. Sci. Rep. 6, 20995 (2016).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crystal structure of the human alkaline sphingomyelinase provides insights into substrate recognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gorelik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Illes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Nagar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">292</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7087" to="7094" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>References</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Gorelik, A., Liu, F., Illes, K. &amp; Nagar, B. Crystal structure of the human alkaline sphingomyelinase provides insights into substrate recognition. J. Biol. Chem. 292, 7087-7094 (2017). References</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Basic local alignment search tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Altschul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Myers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lipman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">215</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="410" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Altschul, S. F., Gish, W., Miller, W., Myers, E. W. &amp; Lipman, D. J. Basic local alignment search tool. J. Mol. Biol. 215, 403-410 (1990).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ligand Depot: a data warehouse for ligands bound to macromolecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2153" to="2155" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Feng, Z. et al. Ligand Depot: a data warehouse for ligands bound to macromolecules. Bioinformatics 20, 2153-2155 (2004).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MRS: a fast and compact retrieval system for biological data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hekkelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Vriend</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="766" to="W769" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hekkelman, M. L. &amp; Vriend, G. MRS: a fast and compact retrieval system for biological data. Nucleic Acids Res. 33, W766-W769 (2005).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hekkelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.5733933</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5733933" />
		<title level="m">mhekkel/libzeep: maintenance release</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Hekkelman, M. L. mhekkel/libzeep: maintenance release. Zenodo https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5733933 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PDBx/mmCIF ecosystem: foundational semantic tools for structural biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Westbrook</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">434</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">167599</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Westbrook, J. D. et al. PDBx/mmCIF ecosystem: foundational semantic tools for structural biology. J. Mol. Biol. 434, 167599 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Clipper C++ libraries for X-ray crystallography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kevind</forename><surname>Cowtan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IUCr Computing Commission Newsletter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Cowtan, KevinD. The Clipper C++ libraries for X-ray crystallography. IUCr Computing Commission Newsletter 2, 4-9 (2003).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Make-a program for maintaining computer programs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Feldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Softw. Pract. Exp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Feldman, S. I. Make-a program for maintaining computer programs. J. Softw. Pract. Exp. 9, 255-265 (1979).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A series of PDB related databases for everyday needs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Joosten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="D419" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Joosten, R. P. et al. A series of PDB related databases for everyday needs. Nucleic Acids Res. 39, D411-D419 (2011).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The design of POSTGRES</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stonebraker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIGMOD Rec</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="340" to="355" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Stonebraker, M. &amp; Rowe, L. A. The design of POSTGRES. SIGMOD Rec. 15, 340-355 (1986).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving physical realism, stereochemistry, and side-chain accuracy in homology modeling: four approaches that performed well in CASP8</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Krieger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="114" to="122" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Krieger, E. et al. Improving physical realism, stereochemistry, and side-chain accuracy in homology modeling: four approaches that performed well in CASP8. Proteins 77, 114-122 (2009).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Features and development of Coot</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Emsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lohkamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Cowtan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta. Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="486" to="501" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Emsley, P., Lohkamp, B., Scott, W. G. &amp; Cowtan, K. Features and development of Coot. Acta. Crystallogr. D. Biol. Crystallogr. 66, 486-501 (2010).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Presenting your structures: the CCP4mg molecular-graphics software</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mcnicholas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Potterton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E M</forename><surname>Noble</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta. Cryst. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="386" to="394" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">McNicholas, S., Potterton, E., Wilson, K. S. &amp; Noble, M. E. M. Presenting your structures: the CCP4mg molecular-graphics software. Acta. Cryst. D. 67, 386-394 (2011).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">seaborn: statistical data visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Waskom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Open Source Softw</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3021</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Waskom, M. L. seaborn: statistical data visualization. J. Open Source Softw. 6, 3021 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
