<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A general approach for the generation of orthogonal tRNAs</title>
				<funder ref="#_G5Ut4m5">
					<orgName type="full">National Institutes of Health</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2001-07-27">27 July 2001</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lei</forename><surname>Wang Ay</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Schultz</surname></persName>
							<email>schultz@scripps.edu</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California at Berkeley</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>94720</postCode>
									<settlement>Berkeley</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Scripps Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>10550 North Torrey Pines Road La Jolla</addrLine>
									<postCode>92037</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A general approach for the generation of orthogonal tRNAs</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2001-07-27">27 July 2001</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">86F268E1CF58170FFE600B78F4E75DD4</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 26 March 2001; accepted 29 May 2001</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-24T14:50+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[0], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase</term>
					<term>In vivo selection</term>
					<term>In vivo unnatural amino acid mutagenesis</term>
					<term>Orthogonal suppressor tRNA</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Background: The addition of new amino acids to the genetic code of Escherichia coli requires an orthogonal suppressor tRNA that is uniquely acylated with a desired unnatural amino acid by an orthogonal aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase. A tRNA Tyr CUA ^tyrosyl-tRNA synthetase pair imported from Methanococcus jannaschii can be used to generate such a pair. In vivo selections have been developed for selecting mutant suppressor tRNAs with enhanced orthogonality, which can be used to site-specifically incorporate unnatural amino acids into proteins in E. coli.</p><p>Results: A library of amber suppressor tRNAs derived from M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr was generated. tRNA Tyr CUA s that are substrates for endogenous E. coli aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases were deleted from the pool by a negative selection based on suppression of amber nonsense mutations in the barnase gene. The remaining tRNA Tyr CUA s were then selected for their ability to suppress amber nonsense codons in the L-lactamase gene in the presence of the cognate M. jannaschii tyrosyl-tRNA synthetase (TyrRS). Four mutant suppressor tRNAs were selected that are poorer substrates for E. coli synthetases than M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr CUA , but still can be charged efficiently by M. jannaschii TyrRS.</p><p>Conclusions: The mutant suppressor tRNA Tyr CUA together with the M. jannaschii TyrRS is an excellent orthogonal tRNAŝ ynthetase pair for the in vivo incorporation of unnatural amino acids into proteins. This general approach may be expanded to generate additional orthogonal tRNA^synthetase pairs as well as probe the interactions between tRNAs and their cognate synthetases.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="596.0" lry="794.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="596.0" lry="794.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="596.0" lry="794.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="596.0" lry="794.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="596.0" lry="794.0"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="596.0" lry="794.0"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="596.0" lry="794.0"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="596.0" lry="794.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>In vitro methods have been developed to site-speci¢cally introduce unnatural amino acids into proteins by suppression of amber mutations with chemically acylated tRNAs <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>. The ability to directly incorporate unnatural amino acids site-speci¢cally into proteins in living cells would greatly expand our ability to manipulate protein structure and function as well as probe cellular processes. Our strategy to expand the genetic code of Escherichia coli involves the generation of a suppressor tRNA that is not acylated by any of the E. coli synthetases (orthogonal suppressor tRNA), and a synthetase that does not acylate any E. coli tRNAs, but e¤ciently charges the orthogonal suppressor tRNA. The speci¢city of this synthetase is then altered so that it charges the orthogonal suppressor tRNA with a desired unnatural amino acid, and none of the common 20 amino acids <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>.</p><p>Several strategies have been developed to generate orthogonal suppressor tRNA^synthetase pairs in E. coli. One involves destroying an existing E. coli tRNA's a¤nity toward its cognate synthetase (but not its ability to function in translation) by mutating nucleotides at the tRNAŝ ynthetase interface. A mutant synthetase is then evolved that uniquely recognizes the orthogonal tRNA. Such an orthogonal tRNA has been generated from E. coli tRNA Gln  2 , but no mutant E. coli GlnRS has been evolved that charges the derived orthogonal tRNA more e¤ciently than wild-type E. coli tRNA Gln 2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. A second strategy involves importing a tRNA^synthetase pair from another organism into E. coli if cross-species aminoacylation is ine¤cient, and the suppressor tRNA derived from the tRNA is not charged by E. coli synthetases. Two orthog-onal suppressor tRNA^synthetase pairs have been developed based on the Saccharomyces cerevisiae tRNA Gln   2   ĜlnRS and tRNA Asp ^AspRS pairs <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>. Another approach involves the use of a heterologous synthetase as the orthogonal synthetase but a mutant initiator tRNA of the same organism or a related organism as the orthogonal tRNA. Two pairs have been generated, a mutant human initiator tRNA^E. coli GlnRS pair for use in S. cerevisiae and a mutant E. coli initiator tRNA fMet 2 ^mutant yeast TyrRS pair for use in E. coli <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</p><p>The development of additional orthogonal tRNA^synthetase pairs may allow the simultaneous incorporation of multiple unnatural amino acids into proteins. Moreover, di¡erent aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases may be better starting points for generating active sites with particular spe-ci¢cities, e.g. large hydrophobic vs. small hydrophilic amino acids. We recently reported the generation of an orthogonal tRNA Tyr  CUA ^TyrRS pair by expressing the Methanococcus jannaschii tRNA Tyr CUA ^TyrRS pair in E. coli <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. In comparison to the Gln and Asp orthogonal pair, the TyrRS charges its cognate amber suppressor tRNA with much higher e¤ciency. However, the tRNA Tyr  CUA derived from M. jannaschii is also a better substrate for the endogenous E. coli synthetases than the S. cerevisiae tRNA Gln CUA and tRNA Asp CUA . In order to improve the utility of this tRNA Tyr CUA ^TyrRS pair, and to develop additional such pairs, we have developed a general strategy for selecting mutant tRNAs with enhanced orthogonality. Mutant suppressor tRNAs selected from libraries derived from M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr  CUA have been generated and characterized.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Results and discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Suppressor tRNA library design and construction</head><p>Because of the complex nature of tRNA^synthetase interactions that are required to achieve a high degree of ¢delity in protein translation, the rational design of orthogonal tRNA^synthetase pairs is di¤cult. Consequently, we have taken an approach that exploits the poor cross recognition of some interspecies tRNA^synthetase pairs, coupled with subsequent in vivo evolution of tRNAs with enhanced orthogonality. The tRNA Tyr of M. jannaschii, an archaebacterium, has di¡erent identity elements from those of E. coli tRNA Tyr . In particular, the E. coli tRNA Tyr has a G1C72 pair in the acceptor stem while the M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr has a C1G72 pair. We have shown that an amber suppressor tRNA derived from M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr is not e¤ciently aminoacylated by the E. coli synthetases, but functions e¤ciently in protein translation in E. coli <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. In addition, the M. jannaschii TyrRS, which has only a minimalist anticodon-loop-binding domain, does not aminoacylate E. coli tRNAs <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, but still e¤ciently aminoacylates its own suppressor tRNA Tyr CUA <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</p><p>To test the orthogonality of this suppressor tRNA in E. coli, an amber codon was introduced at a permissive site (Ala184) in the L-lactamase gene <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Those tRNAs that can be charged by E. coli synthetases will suppress the amber codon and allow cells to live in the presence of ampicillin. The M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr CUA suppresses the amber codon in the L-lactamase gene with an IC 50 value of 56 Wg/ml ampicillin <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. In contrast, the orthogonal tRNA Gln  CUA derived from S. cerevisiae tRNA Gln 2 has an IC 50 of 21 Wg/ml ampicillin when tested in the same assay <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. The IC 50 for E. coli in the absence of any suppressor tRNA is 10 Wg/ml ampicillin. This result shows that the M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr CUA is a better substrate for E. coli synthetases than the tRNA Gln CUA . Consequently, if the M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr  CUA is used in vivo to deliver unnatural amino acids into proteins in E. coli, it may also be mischarged with natural amino acids by E. coli synthetases, leading to heterogeneous amino acid incorporation.</p><p>The improvement of the orthogonality of the M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr CUA requires the introduction of `negative recognition determinants' to prevent recognition by endogenous E. coli synthetases. On the other hand, these mutations should not strongly interfere with the tRNA's interaction with its cognate M. jannaschii TyrRS or the ribosome. Since M. jannaschii TyrRS lacks most of the anticodon-binding domain <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, mutations introduced at the anticodon loop of the tRNA are expected to have a minimal e¡ect on TyrRS recognition. An anticodon-loop library with four randomized nucleotides was constructed to test this notion (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). Given the various combinations and locations of identity elements for various E. coli tRNAs, mutations at additional positions may increase the likelihood of ¢nding a mutant tRNA with the desired properties. Thus, a second library containing mutations at nonconserved positions in all of the tRNA loops (allloop library) was also constructed (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). Conserved nucleotides were not randomized so as to maintain the tertiary interactions that stabilize the `L'-shaped structure of the tRNA <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>. Stem nucleotides were also not mutated since substitution of one such nucleotide requires a compensatory mutation. The 11 nucleotides (C16, C17, U17a, U20, C32, G37, A38, U45, U47, A59, and U60) were therefore randomized (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). The theoretical size of this library is 4.19U10 6 , and a library with a size of 1.93U10 8 colony forming units was constructed to ensure complete coverage of the mutant library.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">A general selection for orthogonal suppressor tRNAs in E. coli</head><p>To select for a member of the M. jannaschii tRNA library with enhanced orthogonality, we used a combination of negative and positive selections in the absence and presence of the cognate synthetase (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>). In the negative selection, amber nonsense codon(s) are introduced in a toxic gene at a nonessential position. When a member of the suppressor tRNA library is aminoacylated by endogenous E. coli synthetases (i.e. it is not orthogonal to the E. coli synthetases), the amber codon is suppressed and the toxic gene product produced leads to cell death. Only cells harboring orthogonal tRNAs or nonfunctional tRNAs can survive. All survivors are then subjected to a positive selection in which an amber codon is placed in a drug resistance gene at a nonessential position. tRNAs are then selected for their ability to be aminoacylated by the coexpressed cognate synthetase and to insert an amino acid in response to this amber codon. Cells harboring nonfunctional tRNAs, or tRNAs that cannot be recognized by  the synthetase of interest will be sensitive to antibiotic. Therefore, only tRNAs that (1) are not substrates for endogenous E. coli synthetases; (2) can be aminoacylated by the synthetase of interest ; (3) are functional in translation will survive both selections.</p><p>A negative selection was chosen that takes advantage of the toxicity of barnase when produced in E. coli in the absence of its natural inhibitor barstar <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>. Amber codons were introduced at nonessential positions in the barnase gene based on analysis of the three-dimensional structure of barnase <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Because of barnase's extreme autotoxicity, a low copy number pSC101 origin was placed in the plasmid expressing barnase. In addition, di¡erent numbers of amber codons were tested to modulate the stringency of the selection. Plasmid pSCB2 was used to express a barnase mutant with two amber stop codons at Gln2 and Asp44 ; plasmid pSCB3 contained an additional amber stop codon at Gly65.</p><p>To optimize the selection conditions, two suppressor tRNAs were used that are known to be poorly recognized by the E. coli synthetases. A mutant suppressor tRNA Tyr derived from S. cerevisiae (sc-tRNA Tyr CUA , expressed in pAC-YYG1) suppresses the amber codon (Ala184TAG) in the L-lactamase gene a¡ording an IC 50 value of 12 Wg/ml ampicillin for E. coli cells ; and the suppressor tRNA Tyr derived from M. jannaschii (mj-tRNA Tyr CUA , expressed in pAC-JY) a¡ords an IC 50 of 56 Wg/ml ampicillin for host cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. For comparison, the suppressor tRNA Gln  CUA derived from S. cerevisiae tRNA Gln 2 has an IC 50 of 21 Wg/ml ampicillin when tested in the same assay, and has been demonstrated to be orthogonal to E. coli synthetases in vitro and in vivo <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. Therefore, a negative selection that eliminates cells expressing mj-tRNA Tyr  CUA , but allows the growth of cells expressing sc-tRNA Tyr  CUA should delete nonorthogonal suppressor tRNAs. Cells were grown in liquid minimal media containing 1% glycerol and 0.3 mM leucine (GMML) with appropriate antibiotics to maintain plasmid pSCB2 and the pAC plasmid. Arabinose was added to one set of cells (set 1) to induce the expression of the barnase, while in set 2 no arabinose was added. The fraction of cells surviving the selection was determined by the ratio of cell densities in set 1 relative to set 2 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>): cells harboring the control plasmid pAC-Cm (without suppressor tRNA) and plasmid pAC-YYG1 survived, while cells harboring plasmid pAC-JY largely died. When plasmid pSCB3 was used, cells harboring plasmid pAC-JY started to grow in 24 h (data not shown). Therefore, the negative selection was carried out using pSCB2, which encodes the barnase gene containing two amber codons under the above conditions for the library selection.</p><p>The positive selection is based on suppression of an amber stop codon introduced at position Ala184 in the TEM-1 L-lactamase gene. Plasmid pBLAM-JYRS encodes  the gene for the M. jannaschii tyrosyl-tRNA synthetase and a L-lactamase with an amber mutation at Ala184. pAC plasmids isolated from cells surviving the negative selection were cotransformed with pBLAM-JYRS into E. coli DH10B cells. Cells harboring nonfunctional tRNAs or tRNAs that are poor substrates for the M. jannaschii synthetase die; those with tRNAs that can be charged by the synthetase survive. To test the feasibility of the positive selection, two model suppressor tRNAs were tested in the presence of M. jannaschii TyrRS. The sc-tRNA Tyr CUA has a G1:C72 base pair and is not charged e¤ciently by M. jannaschii TyrRS. When they were coexpressed in cells with the Ala184amber L-lactamase mutant, cells survived to an IC 50 of 18 Wg/ml ampicillin. In contrast, cells containing the M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr CUA and the cognate TyrRS survive to an IC 50 of 1220 Wg/ml ampicillin <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. The model positive selection was ¢rst tried in liquid 2UYT medium. The growth of cells harboring pBLAM-JYRS and di¡erent pAC plasmids in liquid 2UYT medium with various concentrations of ampicillin are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4A</ref>. Cells transformed with the mj-tRNA Tyr  CUA grew at a faster rate and at higher concentrations of ampicillin. However, if cells were grown longer than 24 h, cells transformed with either pAC-Cm or pAC-YYG1 also grew to saturation, making the selection problematic. Therefore, the positive selection was carried out on plates with initial cell densities between 10 3 and 10 5 per plate (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B</ref>). The survival ratio (number of colonies on plates with ampicillin relative to plates without ampicillin) did not change signi¢cantly with di¡erent initial cell densities, and was stable over the growth time. The positive selection on ampicillin plates resulted in preferential growth of cells with mj-tRNA Tyr CUA expressed. Therefore, for the library selec-tion the positive selection was carried out on plates instead of in liquid medium.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Selection results</head><p>The negative and positive selections were carried out tandemly as described above on both the anticodon-loop and all-loop libraries. The selected suppressor tRNAs were isolated and retransformed into E. coli DH10B harboring pBLAM to test the tRNA's orthogonality to E. coli synthetases. The tRNAs were then retransformed into E. coli harboring pBLAM-JYRS to test how e¤ciently the tRNA can be charged by M. jannaschii TyrRS. Sequencing of the clones resulting from one round of negative and positive selection of anticodon-loop library revealed that three independent tRNAs were isolated (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>). When cotransformed with pBLAM, all had lower IC 50 values than the parent M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr CUA , indicating they are poorer substrates for E. coli synthetases (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). Mutant AA2 also had very high a¤nity for M. jannaschii TyrRS. Unfortunately, although this mutant tRNA could be stably maintained in E. coli, it slowed the growth rate of cells for unknown reasons. This e¡ect likely led to the emergence of mutants AA3 and AA4, which both had a mutation outside of the randomization region. Cells harboring AA3 or AA4 grew normally. Nevertheless, AA3 and AA4 were relatively poor substrates for the M. jannaschii TyrRS.</p><p>Four independent tRNAs were selected from two rounds of negative and positive selections using the allloop library (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>). All were poorer substrates for the E. coli synthetase than the parent M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr  CUA , yet were still e¤ciently charged by the M. jannaschii TyrRS as shown by the in vivo L-lactamase assay (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). The IC 50 value for cells expressing the best mutant, J17, was 12 Wg/ml ampicillin, which is even lower than that of cells with the orthogonal tRNA Gln CUA derived from S. cerevisiae expressed (21 Wg/ml ampicillin). When J17 was coexpressed with the M. jannaschii TyrRS, cells survived to an IC 50 value of 436 Wg/ml ampicillin, providing a selection window (ratio of IC 50 value with TyrRS to IC 50 value without TyrRS) of 35-fold. In addition, the expression of all these mutant tRNAs did not a¡ect the growth of E. coli cells.</p><p>To con¢rm the properties of the selected suppressor tRNAs, they were tested in another in vivo assay based on the suppression of an amber codon in the chloramphenicol acetyltransferase (CAT) gene. In contrast to L-lactamase which is secreted into the periplasm, CAT localizes in the cytoplasm. Moreover, ampicillin is bacteriocidal while chloramphenicol is bacteriostatic. As shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>, the selected suppressor tRNAs also were orthogonal in the CAT assay, indicating their suitability for CAT selections.</p><p>For comparison, we randomly picked four colonies that passed the negative selection only, and tested the tRNAs using the in vivo complementation assay. All of them had very low IC 50 values when transformed with pBLAM, indicating the negative selection worked well (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). The IC 50 values were also low when cotransformed with pBLAM-JYRS, revealing that the positive selection functions to delete tRNAs that cannot be charged by the M. jannaschii TyrRS.</p><p>Analysis of the DNA sequences of the selected tRNAs yielded a characteristic pattern of nucleotide substitutions (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>). tRNAs that passed both negative and positive selections all had C32 and T60 unchanged, while G37 was mutated to A, and T17a was mutated to either A or G. Some semi-conserved changes included mutation of A38 to either C or A; mutation of T45 to either T or A; mutation of T47 to either G or T. Other mutations had no obvious common pattern. We also sequenced 20 tRNAs that passed the negative selection only, four of which are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>, and found they all lacked at least one of the common mutations listed above. The preferred nucleotides in the selected mutant suppressor tRNAs may play the following roles: (i) they may function as negative determinants for recognition by the E. coli synthetases; (ii) they may be identity elements for aminoacylation by M. jannaschii TyrRS; or (iii) they may also optimize the tRNA's interaction with E. coli's translational machinery so as to increase the suppression e¤ciency of the tRNA. It is noteworthy that the G37A mutation was found in tRNAs selected from both the anticodon-loop and all-loop library. This mutation is consistent with previous studies, both theoretical <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> and experimental <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref>, showing that adenine at position 37 enhances amber suppression e¤ciency. Fechter et al. recently reported that the complete identity set for M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr is six nucleotides (C1G72, A73, and anticodon G34U35A36) <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. The presence of C32 and T60 in all selected mutant suppressors therefore is not required for recognition by M. jannaschii TyrRS. All E. coli tRNAs have T at position 60 except four tRNAs which have C <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. Based on the crystal structure of yeast tRNA Phe <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, nucleotide 60 does not interact with other nucleotides. Thus, T60 may maintain the shape of the T8C loop for productive interaction with the E. coli translational machinery. The change of the T8C loop structure may a¡ect translational ¢delity, as the insertion of a nucleotide between T60 and the conserved C61 enables a glycine tRNA to shift reading frame <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. The role of C32 is not obvious ^position 32 in E. coli tRNAs includes T, C, and A, and two E. coli tRNA Tyr s do have C32. As for position 17a, only tRNA Thr has an A at this position. Plasmid pBLAM was used to express the L-lactamase gene with an amber codon at Ala184; plasmid pBLAM-JYRS expressed the amber mutant and the TyrRS of M. jannaschii. Suppressor tRNAs were encoded on pAC plasmid and cotransformed with pBLAM or pBLAM-JYRS in the assay. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Signi¢cance</head><p>All of the selected suppressor tRNAs are poorer substrates for E. coli synthetases relative to the M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr CUA , resulting in less mischarging when introduced into E. coli. These tRNAs can also be stably maintained in E. coli without adverse e¡ects on the growth of host cells. Moreover, they can still be charged e¤ciently by M. jannaschii TyrRS. All these properties make the mutant suppressor tRNA together with the M. jannaschii TyrRS a robust orthogonal tRNA^synthetase pair for the selective incorporation of unnatural amino acids into proteins in vivo. Indeed, we have used the J17 mutant suppressor tRNA and an engineered mutant TyrRS to deliver Omethyl-L-tyrosine in response to a TAG codon with a ¢delity rivaling that of the common 20 amino acids <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. The in vivo selection strategy described here may be useful for the generation of more orthogonal tRNA^synthetase pairs, and for studies of interactions between tRNAs and synthetases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Materials and methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Strains and plasmids</head><p>E. coli strain DH10B was obtained from Gibco/BRL. Suppressor tRNA expression plasmids were derived from pAC123 <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Plasmids for negative selections were derived from pBATS <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, pYsupA38B2 and pYsupA38B3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> as described below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Negative selection</head><p>A PCR fragment containing the L-lactamase gene and the pSC101 origin was generated from pBATS using the following oligonucleotides : LW115, 5P-ATGCATGCTGCATTAATGAA-TCGGCCAACG-3P; LW116, 5P-TCCCCGCGGAGGTGGCA-CTTTTCGGGG-3P. DNA encoding barnase containing two (residues Gln2 and Asp44) or three (residues Gln2, Asp44 and Gly65) amber codons were obtained from pYsupA38B2 and pY-supA38B3, respectively, by digestion with SacII and SphI. Ligation of the above fragments a¡orded plasmids pSCB2 and pSCB3. The expression of barnase was under arabinose induction. Genes encoding di¡erent suppressor tRNAs for in vivo expression were constructed from two overlapping synthetic oligonucleotides (Operon, CA, USA) by Klenow extension and inserted between the EcoRI and PstI sites of pAC123 to generate pAC-YYG1 and pAC-JY, respectively, placing transcription under control of the lpp promoter and the rrnC terminator. pAC-Cm is the control plasmid without any tRNA. To optimize the negative selection conditions, competent DH10B cells harboring pSCB2 or pSCB3 were transformed by electroporation with pAC-Cm, pAC-YYG1, and pAC-JY, separately. Single colonies were picked and grown in 2UYT with chloramphenicol (Cm, 34 Wg/ml) and ampicillin (Amp, 100 Wg/ml). Cell cultures grown overnight were washed twice with minimal media containing 1% glycerol and 0.3 mM leucine (GMML), and resuspended in GMML with Cm and Amp to an OD 600 of 0.1. After recovering at 30³C for 10 min, into one culture (set 1) was added 20 mM of arabinose to induce the expression of barnase; no arabinose was added to the second culture (set 2). At di¡erent time points, a small amount of cell culture was diluted and plated on 2UYT agar with Cm and Amp to measure cell density. For negative selections of the suppressor tRNA libraries, the pAC plasmids containing the library were transformed into DH10B cells harboring pSCB2. Cells were quenched by addition of SOC medium and recovered at 30³C for 1 h, then were washed with phosphate bu¡er and GMML, and cultured in 1 l GMML. After recovering at 30³C for 30 min, Cm, Amp, and 20 mM arabinose were added. After 36 h, cells were pelleted and pAC plasmids were isolated and puri¢ed by agarose gel electrophoresis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Positive selection</head><p>Plasmid pBLAM-JYRS was constructed by inserting the M. jannaschii TyrRS gene from pBSA50 <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> between NdeI and PstI sites of pBLAM-YQRS <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> using oligonucleotides LW104, 5P-GGAATTCCATTAGGACGAATTTGAAATG-3P; and LW105, 5P-AAACTGCAGTTATAATCTCTTTCTAATTGGC-TC-3P. To optimize the positive selection conditions, competent DH10B cells harboring pBLAM-JYRS were transformed with pAC-Cm, pAC-YYG1, and pAC-JY, separately. Single colonies were picked and grown in 2UYT with Cm and tetracycline (Tet, 40 Wg/ml). In liquid selections, overnight cell cultures were diluted into 2UYT with Cm and Tet at a starting OD 600 of 0.1. Various concentrations of Amp were added, and cell growth was monitored by OD 600 . In plate selections, approximately 10 3 to 10 5 cells were plated on two sets of 2UYT agar plates containing Cm and Tet, one set of which contained 500 Wg/ml Amp. For selections involving the mutant tRNA library, pAC plasmids isolated from the cells from the negative selection were transformed into competent DH10B cells harboring pBLAM-JYRS. Cells were recovered at 37³C for 45 min, and approximately 10 5 cells were plated onto each 2UYT agar plate containing Cm, Tet and 500 Wg/ml of Amp. After 24 h, colonies were picked and re-grown in 6 ml 2UYT containing Cm, Tet and 200 Wg/ml of Amp. DNA was isolated and pAC plasmid was puri¢ed by agarose gel electrophoresis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">Construction of the suppressor tRNA library</head><p>The sequences of the two overlapping oligonucleotides used to construct the anticodon-loop library are (the tRNA sequence underlined): LW125, 5P-GGAATTCCCGGCGGTAGTTCAG-CCTGGTAGAACGGCGGANNCTANNTCCGCATGTCG-3P; LW126, 5P-AAAACTGCAGTGGTCCGGCGGGCCGGATTT-GAACCAGCGACATGCGGANNTAGNNTCCGCCGTTCT-AC-3P (where N is equimolar of A, C, T or G). The sequences of oligonucleotides for the all-loop library are: LW145, 5P-GGAA-TTCCCGGCGGTAGTTCAGNNNGGNAGAACGGCGGAN-TCTANNTCCGCANGNCGCTGGTTC-3P and LW146, 5P-AA-AACTGCAGTGGTCCGGCGGGCCGGNNTTGAACCAGC-GNCNTGCGGANNTAGANTCCGCCGTTC-3P. These genes were inserted into pAC123 similarly as described above to a¡ord the tRNA libraries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5.">In vivo complementation assays</head><p>The in vivo complementation assay which is based on suppression of an amber codon in the L-lactamase gene was carried out as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>. In the chloramphenicol acetyltransferase (CAT) assay, an amber codon was substituted for Asp112 in the CAT gene of pACYC184 to a¡ord pACMD112TAG <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The genes encoding the suppressor tRNAs under the control of the lpp promoter and rrnC terminator were excised from pAC plasmids with NcoI and AvaI, and inserted into the pre-digested pACMD112TAG to a¡ord plasmids pYC-JY, pYC-J15, pYC-J17, pYC-J18, and pYC-J22, respectively. Plasmid pBK-JYRS, a derivative of pBR322, was used to express the M. jannaschii TyrRS under the control of the E. coli GlnRS promoter and terminator. The survival of E. coli DH10B cells transformed with pYC plasmid alone or cotransformed with pYC and pBK-JYRS was titrated against a wide range of chloramphenicol concentrations added to the growth media, and IC 50 values were interpolated from the curves.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Anticodon-loop tRNA library (left) and all-loop tRNA library (right) derived from M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr CUA . Randomly mutated nucleotides (N) are shaded in black.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,79.54,73.65,437.11,247.18" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. A general selection for suppressor tRNAs that are poor substrates for the E. coli synthetases and charged e¤ciently by a cognate synthetase of interest.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,81.07,451.58,433.56,264.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Negative selection based on the suppression of two amber codons in the barnase gene. Selections were carried out in GMML liquid medium, and 20 mM of arabinose was used to induce barnase expression.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,52.50,511.62,226.80,184.54" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. Positive selection based on the suppression of an amber codon in the L-lactamase gene. pAC plasmid encoding the suppressor tRNA was cotransformed with pBLAM-JYRS in E. coli DH10B cells: (A) selection was carried out in liquid 2UYT media with various concentrations of ampicillin; (B) selection was carried out on 2UYT agar plates with 500 Wg/ml ampicillin.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,316.52,74.12,226.80,358.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5. DNA sequences of mutant suppressor tRNAs selected from anticodon-loop library and all-loop library. JY stands for the wild-type M. jannaschii tRNA Tyr CUA . Wild-type nucleotides are shaded in blue; mutated nucleotides in red; and semi-conserved nucleotides in gray.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,91.05,490.48,414.36,225.65" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>In vivo L-lactamase assay of selected suppressor tRNAs</figDesc><table><row><cell>Suppressor tRNA</cell><cell cols="2">IC 50 (Wg/ml of ampicillin)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Coexpressed with</cell><cell>Coexpressed with</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>pBLAM</cell><cell>pBLAM-JYRS</cell></row><row><cell>mj-tRNA Tyr CUA No tRNA Tyr CUA</cell><cell>56 10</cell><cell>1220 10</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Mutant tRNAs selected from anticodon-loop library</cell></row><row><cell>AA2</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>1420</cell></row><row><cell>AA3</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>110</cell></row><row><cell>AA4</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>135</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Mutant tRNAs selected from all-loop library</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Mutant tRNAs surviving both selections</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>J15</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>845</cell></row><row><cell>J17</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>436</cell></row><row><cell>J18</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>632</cell></row><row><cell>J22</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>459</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Mutant tRNAs surviving negative selection only</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>N11</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>16</cell></row><row><cell>N12</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>18</cell></row><row><cell>N13</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>12</cell></row><row><cell>N16</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>9</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>In vivo chloramphenicol acetyltransferase assay of selected suppressor tRNAs</figDesc><table><row><cell>Suppressor tRNA</cell><cell cols="2">IC 50 (Wg/ml of chloramphenicol)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>pYC only</cell><cell>pYC+pBK-JYRS</cell></row><row><cell>mj-tRNA Tyr CUA No tRNA Tyr CUA</cell><cell>27 3</cell><cell>308 3</cell></row><row><cell>J15</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>297</cell></row><row><cell>J17</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>240</cell></row><row><cell>J18</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>284</cell></row><row><cell>J22</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>271</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">pYC plasmids encoded the chloramphenicol acetyltransferase gene with</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">an amber codon at Asp112 and di¡erent suppressor tRNAs listed in the</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">left column of the table. pBK-JYRS was used to express the TyrRS of</cell></row><row><cell>M. jannaschii.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Present address: Department of Chemistry, The Scripps Research Institute, 10550 North Torrey Pines Road, La Jolla, CA 92037, USA.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We thank <rs type="person">Professor David R. Liu</rs> for helpful discussions, <rs type="person">Professor William H. McClain</rs> for plasmid pBATS, <rs type="person">Dr. Brian Steer</rs> and <rs type="person">Professor Paul Schimmel</rs> for plasmid pBAS50. This research was supported by <rs type="funder">National Institutes of Health</rs> under Contract <rs type="grantNumber">62159-01</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_G5Ut4m5">
					<idno type="grant-number">62159-01</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A general method for site-speci¢c incorporation of unnatural amino acids into proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Noren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Anthony-Cahill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gri¤th</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Schultz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">244</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">188</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">C.J. Noren, S.J. Anthony-Cahill, M.C. Gri¤th, P.G. Schultz, A gen- eral method for site-speci¢c incorporation of unnatural amino acids into proteins, Science 244 (1989) 182^188.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biosynthetic site-speci¢c incorporation of a non-natural amino acid into a polypeptide</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Glabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dix</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Chamberlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Diala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">8014</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">J.D. Bain, C.G. Glabe, T.A. Dix, A.R. Chamberlin, E.S. Diala, Bio- synthetic site-speci¢c incorporation of a non-natural amino acid into a polypeptide, J. Am. Chem. Soc. 111 (1989) 8013^8014.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expanding the genetic code of Escherichia coli</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Schultz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>submitted</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">L. Wang, A. Brock, P.G. Schultz, Expanding the genetic code of Escherichia coli, Science, submitted.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Engineering a tRNA and aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase for the site-speci¢c incorporation of unnatural amino acids into proteins in vivo</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Magliery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pastrnak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Schultz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10097</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">D.R. Liu, T.J. Magliery, M. Pastrnak, P.G. Schultz, Engineering a tRNA and aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase for the site-speci¢c incorpo- ration of unnatural amino acids into proteins in vivo, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 94 (1997) 10091^10097.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterization of an `orthogonal&apos; suppressor tRNA derived from E. coli tRNA Gln 2</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Magliery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Schultz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">691</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">D.R. Liu, T.J. Magliery, P.G. Schultz, Characterization of an `or- thogonal&apos; suppressor tRNA derived from E. coli tRNA Gln 2 , Chem. Biol. 4 (1997) 685^691.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Progress toward the evolution of an organism with an expanded genetic code</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Schultz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4785</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">D.R. Liu, P.G. Schultz, Progress toward the evolution of an organ- ism with an expanded genetic code, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 96 (1999) 4780^4785.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new orthogonal suppressor tRNA/aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase pair for evolving an organism with an expanded genetic code</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pastrnak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Magliery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Schultz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Helv. Chim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">286</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Pastrnak, T.J. Magliery, P.G. Schultz, A new orthogonal suppres- sor tRNA/aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase pair for evolving an organism with an expanded genetic code, Helv. Chim. Acta 83 (2000) 22772 286.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Twenty-¢rst aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase-suppressor tRNA pairs for possible use in site-spe-ci¢c incorporation of amino acid analogues into proteins in eukaryotes and in eubacteria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kowal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ko «hrer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rajbhandary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">273</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">A.K. Kowal, C. Ko «hrer, U.L. RajBhandary, Twenty-¢rst aminoacyl- tRNA synthetase-suppressor tRNA pairs for possible use in site-spe- ci¢c incorporation of amino acid analogues into proteins in eukary- otes and in eubacteria, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 98 (2001) 22682 273.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new functional suppressor tRNA/aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase pair for the in vivo incorporation of unnatural amino acids into proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Magliery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Schultz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5011</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">L. Wang, T.J. Magliery, D.R. Liu, P.G. Schultz, A new functional suppressor tRNA/aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase pair for the in vivo incorporation of unnatural amino acids into proteins, J. Am. Chem. Soc. 122 (2000) 5010^5011.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Major anticodon-binding region missing from an archaebacterial tRNA synthetase</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Steer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schimmel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">274</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">35606</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">B.A. Steer, P. Schimmel, Major anticodon-binding region missing from an archaebacterial tRNA synthetase, J. Biol. Chem. 274 (1999) 35601^35606.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dirheimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Keith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dumas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Westhof</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Primary, secondary, and tertiary structures of tRNAs</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>So « Ll</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rajbhandary</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ASM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="126" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>tRNA Structure, Biosynthesis, and Function</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">G. Dirheimer, G. Keith, P. Dumas, E. Westhof, Primary, secondary, and tertiary structures of tRNAs, in: D. So « ll, U.L. RajBhandary (Eds.), tRNA Structure, Biosynthesis, and Function, ASM Press, Washington, DC, 1995, pp. 93^126.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Universal rules and idiosyncratic features in tRNA identity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Giege</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">¨</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sissler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Florentz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5035</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">R. Giege ¨, M. Sissler, C. Florentz, Universal rules and idiosyncratic features in tRNA identity, Nucleic Acids Res. 26 (1998) 5017^5035.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expression of its cloned inhibitor permits expression of a cloned ribonuclease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hartley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">202</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">915</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Barnase and barstar</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">R.W. Hartley, Barnase and barstar. Expression of its cloned inhibitor permits expression of a cloned ribonuclease, J. Mol. Biol. 202 (1988) 913^915.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Translational e¤ciency of transfer RNA&apos;s: Use of an expanded anticodon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yarus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">218</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">652</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Yarus, Translational e¤ciency of transfer RNA&apos;s: Use of an expanded anticodon, Science 218 (1982) 646^652.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">tRNA Gln 2 Su 2 mutants that increase amber suppression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Soll</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Bacteriol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">145</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">712</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">D. Bradley, J.V. Park, L. Soll, tRNA Gln 2 Su 2 mutants that increase amber suppression, J. Bacteriol. 145 (1981) 704^712.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Construction of Escherichia coli amber suppressor tRNA genes. II. Synthesis of additional tRNA genes and improvement of suppressor e¤ciency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kleina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Masson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Normanly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Abelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">213</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">717</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">L.G. Kleina, J. Masson, J. Normanly, J. Abelson, J.H. Miller, Con- struction of Escherichia coli amber suppressor tRNA genes. II. Syn- thesis of additional tRNA genes and improvement of suppressor e¤ciency, J. Mol. Biol. 213 (1990) 705^717.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Major tyrosine identity determinants in Methanococcus jannaschii and Saccharomyces cerevisiae tRNA Tyr are conserved but expressed di¡erently</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Fechter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rudinger-Thirion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tukalo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Giege</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">¨</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">268</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">767</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">P. Fechter, J. Rudinger-Thirion, M. Tukalo, R. Giege ¨, Major tyro- sine identity determinants in Methanococcus jannaschii and Saccha- romyces cerevisiae tRNA Tyr are conserved but expressed di¡erently, Eur. J. Biochem. 268 (2001) 761^767.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compilation of tRNA sequences and sequences of tRNA genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sprinzl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Horn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Loudovitch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Steinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">153</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Sprinzl, C. Horn, M. Brown, A. Loudovitch, S. Steinberg, Com- pilation of tRNA sequences and sequences of tRNA genes, Nucleic Acids Res. 26 (1998) 148^153.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crystal structure of yeast phenylalanine transfer RNA. I. Crystallographic re¢nement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Sussman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Holbrook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Warrant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Church</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">630</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">J.L. Sussman, S.R. Holbrook, R.W. Warrant, G.M. Church, S.-H. Kim, Crystal structure of yeast phenylalanine transfer RNA. I. Crys- tallographic re¢nement, J. Mol. Biol. 123 (1978) 607^630.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atkins, Glycine tRNA mutants with normal anticodon loop size cause 31 frameshifting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>O'mahony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hims</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Murgola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">983</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">D.J. O&apos;Mahony, B.H. Hims, S. Thompson, E.J. Murgola, J.F. At- kins, Glycine tRNA mutants with normal anticodon loop size cause 31 frameshifting, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 86 (1989) 79797 983.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A set of plasmids constitutively producing di¡erent RNA levels in Escherichia coli</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gabriel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Mcclain</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">290</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">389</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">K. Gabriel, W.H. McClain, A set of plasmids constitutively produc- ing di¡erent RNA levels in Escherichia coli, J. Mol. Biol. 290 (1999) 385^389.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
