<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">74263E32ED954E3A6884147926825CFB</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41592-022-01763-1</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-25T22:03+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[0], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.276" lry="790.866"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="13" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="14" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="15" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="16" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="17" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="18" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="19" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="20" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="21" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="22" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="23" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="24" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="25" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="26" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="27" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="28" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="29" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="30" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="31" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="32" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="33" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="34" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="35" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="36" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="37" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="38" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="39" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="40" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="41" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="42" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="43" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="44" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="45" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="46" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="47" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="48" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="49" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="50" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="51" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="52" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="53" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="54" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="55" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="56" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Scenarios</head><p>Six scenarios demonstrate the feasibility of the EnzymeML toolbox and the promises of a standardized data exchange format in biocatalysis. The scenarios cover a broad range of typical applications in biocatalysis. In all scenarios, EnzymeML was applied to integrate tools for data acquisition and kinetic modelling, as well as data repositories, thus enabling the seamless flow of enzymatic data from experiment to publication. The reporting of experimental data and modelling results follow the FAIR principles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scenario 1: Analysing initial rate data by Michaelis-Menten kinetics</head><p>Fe-S clusters are versatile inorganic cofactors that act as catalysts or redox sensors in a large variety of cell pathways. Fe-S cluster biogenesis is initiated by a pyridoxal phosphate (PLP)dependent cysteine desulfurase, which produces L-alanine and enzyme-bound persulfide from L-cysteine. The persulfide is then transferred to a protein scaffold, where it comes together with iron (Fe2+) to give rise to Fe-S clusters <ref type="bibr">1</ref> . In the present work, the bacterial Fe-S cluster biogenesis machinery was used as a model to study the enzymatic processes associated with Fe-S cluster production. More specifically, the kinetics of sulfur production by IscS (cysteine desulfurase, EC 2.8.1.7) in the presence of IscU (iron-sulfur cluster assembly enzyme) as protein scaffold (Scheme 1) were characterised with the goal of subsequently studying the effect of putative kinetic modulators on this system. The corresponding genes were recombinantly expressed in E. coli and purified by nickel-affinity and size-exclusion chromatography. In our assay, DTT (dithiothreitol) is used to reduce persulfide groups, and the solutions N,N-Dimethyl-p-phenylenediamine dihydrochloride (DPD.2HCl) in 7.2 N HCl and FeCl3 in 1.2 N HCl are added for Methylene blue development and quantification at λ=670 nm (Scheme 1). Scheme 1 Formation of L-alanine and from L-cysteine, catalysed by the cysteine desulfurase IscS. The reaction progress was followed using the methylene blue assay. Timepoints were obtained in triplicate for 0, 1 and 2.5 min for six initial substrate concentrations between 5 and 500 µM, at IscS and IscU concentrations of 1 and 2 µM, respectively. The time-course data were documented as a case study for the usage of the modelling webtool interferENZY, being available on Zenodo (<ref type="url" target="https://zenodo.org/record/3957403#.YMtH3qgzY2y">https://zenodo.org/record/3957403#.YMtH3qgzY2y</ref>). Kinetic parameters were estimated by interferENZY and experimental conditions were as reported in the PhD thesis of Maria F. Pinto (<ref type="url" target="https://hdl.handle.net/10216/126202">https://hdl.handle.net/10216/126202</ref>).</p><p>To demonstrate the application of the EnzymeML toolbox, an EnzymeML spreadsheet was generated from the reported data (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S10</ref>). The EnzymeML spreadsheet was converted to an EnzymeML document (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S10</ref>), and a document describing the experimental details was added.</p><p>The time course of product concentration at six different initial substrate concentrations was then fitted by a Michalis-Menten model using two alternative tools: by upload of the EnzymeML document to interferENZY, and by using a Jupyter Notebook for fitting of a Michaelis-Menten model. The EnzymeML document was converted into the input files of interferENZY with the help of a Jupyter Notebook-based function. This file was then uploaded to the webserver and modelling was performed resulting in the previously reported values for the parameters KM = 6.90 ± 1.26 µM and vmax = 1.81 ± 0.11 µM/min. As an alternative, the data were modelled using a Jupyter Notebook (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S10</ref>), resulting in KM = 7.85 ± 1.31 µM and vmax of 1.91 ± 0.07 µM/min (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref>). The estimated kinetic parameters agree well with the values determined by interferENZY, taking into account that interferENZY uses an integrated form of the Michaelis-Menten equation suitable for assay interference detection <ref type="bibr">2</ref> .</p><p>After the modelling process, the kinetic parameters were added to the EnzymeML document by integrating the interferENZY generated output file into the workflow. The EnzymeML document including the modelling results obtained by interferENZY was uploaded to SABIO-RK (<ref type="url" target="http://sabiork.h-its.org/newSearch/index?q=entryID:73347">http://sabiork.h-its.org/newSearch/index?q=entryID:73347</ref>).</p><p>In addition, both EnzymeML documents with the results from the different analysis tools were stored in the EnzymeML Dataverse (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S10</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scenario 2: Analysing time-course data by Michaelis-Menten kinetics</head><p>The putative large subunit of the acetohydroxyacid synthase from Helicobacter canadensis (HcAHAS) was produced recombinantly in E. coli BL21DE3 and purified using nickel chelate chromatography. To test for the acetohydroxyacid reaction, the decrease in the concentration of pyruvate according to the following reaction (Scheme 2) was measured and fitted by the Michaelis-Menten model. The data at pH 7 were visualised and fitted by five different kinetic models within a Jupyter Notebook (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S10</ref>). The time-course data were extracted with the REST-API. For the five models the kinetic rate equations (SI equation 1a -5) were defined in Python. The first four models were the irreversible Michaelis-Menten model for one substrate and three extensions thereof. The fifth was derived from the steady-state rate equation for enzymes with two substrates 37 . All models were fitted against all data points. The EnzymeML document contained only absorbance measurements. Using the Lambert-Beer law, A = ε • c • d, with the absorbance A, the concentration c, the optical path length d, and the extinction coefficient ε, absorbance is proportional to the molar concentration, and therefore absorbance was directly used for the computation and model discrimination.</p><p>The most suitable model was chosen based on the comparison of the estimated errors of the parameters and the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) (Table <ref type="table">S3</ref>). The AIC estimates the relative quality of a model based on the quality of the fit and the simplicity of the underlying model. Based on these criteria, model 4, the irreversible Michaelis-Menten model with both a lag phase and a substrate bias, was selected. The bias parameter accounts for the constant background absorbance as indicated by the control measurements. Parameter estimation resulted in vmax = 0.282 ± 0.011 min -1 , cS0 = 0.861 ± 0.005, bias = 0.097 ± 0.004, KM = 0.048 ± 0.011 and a = 1.70 ± 0.155 min -1 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>). The parameters were converted from absorbance to concentration by applying the Lambert Beer law, using an extinction coefficient of 24.8 L‧ mol -1 ‧ cm -1 and an optical path length of 1 cm (Table <ref type="table">S4</ref>), resulting in a vmax of 11.4 ± 0.4 mM‧ min -1 and a value of 38.6 ± 0.4 mM for cS0 + bias. However, this value is less than the initial concentration of 50 mM of pyruvate used for the experiment. Kinetic parameters for HcAHAS have not yet been reported in literature. As compared the AHAS isoenzyme II from Escherichia coli (EcAHASII), the specific activity (estimated by model 4) was 2.9 times higher and the KM value 2.6 times smaller <ref type="bibr">3</ref> .</p><p>The extinction coefficient of 24.8 L‧ mol -1 ‧ cm -1 was previously determined without the addition of the enzyme (C. Schmitz, personal communication, <ref type="url" target="https://juser.fz-">https://juser.fz-</ref>juelich.de/record/22658). In comparison, the actual extinction coefficient in the experiment with enzyme and substrate was evaluated by ε = A / (c • d) from the fitted value of A = cS0 + bias, c = 50 mM, and d = 1 cm as 19.2 L‧ mol -1 ‧ cm -1 . Using this value of ε, vmax resulted in 14.7 ± 0.6 mM‧ min -1 . (Table <ref type="table">S5</ref>).</p><p>The experiment and the analysis were first reported in the Bachelor thesis by Stephan Malzacher <ref type="bibr">4</ref> : vmax was calculated from the slope assuming cS0 &gt; 10•KM and an extinction coefficient of 24.8 L‧ mol -1 ‧ cm -1 . The vmax value of 9.9 mM‧ min -1 obtained from the analysis of the slope was slightly lower than the value of 11.4 mM‧ min -1 obtained by fitting the time course data. Finally, the EnzymeML document was uploaded to DaRUS (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S10</ref>).</p><p>This scenario demonstrates that it is essential to report the details of the experimental and the modelling procedures in order to enable a reanalysis. Performing a reanalysis of previously collected experimental data can help to test new kinetic models for old data, or to discover so far unnoticed experimental effects, such as a possible gradual decomposition of the concentrated pyruvate in the stock solution which might account for the deviation between extinction coefficient and initial substrate concentration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scenario 3: Collecting data by BioCatHub and visualisation</head><p>Thiamine diphosphate (ThDP)-dependent enzymes are known for catalysing C-C bond forming and breaking reactions. The reaction catalysed for this data is the ligation of aliphatic aldehydes to α-hydroxy ketones. Here, the benzaldehyde lyase from Pseudomonas fluorescens (PfBAL) was used for the formation of the 2-hydroxy ketone propioin (4-hydroxy-3-hexanone) from propanal (Scheme 3) <ref type="bibr">5</ref> . Scheme 3 Ligation of two propanal molecules to propioin, catalysed by the benzaldehyde lyase from Pseudomonas fluorescens (PfBAL).</p><p>The solvent system for this reaction is a micro-aqueous reaction system (MARS), which has advantages especially regarding downstream processing or the usage of hydrophobic substrates <ref type="bibr">6</ref> . The enzyme was added formulated as lyophilized whole cells to shield the enzyme from the organic solvent cyclopentyl methyl ether (CPME). In addition to the solvent, 1 µL/mg enzyme of 1 M triethanolamine buffer (TEA) was added, to sustain a hydration shell around the enzymes for activity. The enzyme in this formulation is still present within the cells. The aqueous buffer is absorbed by the cells and excludes thereby most of the CPME. The more hydrophilic propanal can then enter the cells and is converted to propioin. The reaction was performed as a technical triplicate, with an initial concentration of 200 mM for the propanal in all cases. The reaction was followed over the course of two hours using GC analysis, with increasing time distance between the sample points. Data collection for this experiment was performed in BioCatHub (<ref type="url" target="https://biocathub.net/">https://biocathub.net/</ref>). BioCatHub is a research data management platform, which focusses on the question how to realize research data management in particular in biocatalysis. It provides a user interface which queries the experimenter for metadata based on the STRENDA recommendations and collects primary data in form of time dependent data.</p><p>As soon as primary as well as metadata is collected, the data is stored in EnzymeML and can be shared with other experimenters or published on databases. With the help of this platform, the dataset containing the ligation reaction was exported in the EnzymeML format.</p><p>Afterwards, the EnzymeML document was read into a Jupyter Notebook (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S10</ref>) by the PyEnzyme software. The workflow starts by presenting an overview of the metadata, followed by a visualization of the time-course data with matplotlib (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>). Finally, the EnzymeML document was uploaded to DaRUS (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S10</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scenario 4: Insights into laccase catalysis by kinetic modelling</head><p>Laccase activity was examined for the oxidation of two different substrates, 2,2'-azino-bis(3ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) (ABTS) (Scheme 4). The laccase from Trametes pubescens was added in purified form. The oxidation reactions were performed at 25°C in 50 mM sodium acetate buffer at pH 5.0 with initial ABTS concentrations from 5 to 150 μM. The concentration of ABTS was followed spectrophotometrically (at 354 nm) for 20 minutes. All measurements were performed in triplicate.</p><p>The unpublished dataset was originally given as a completed template used for the upload of data to the BioCatNet database. Data were then transferred into the EnzymeML spreadsheet and converted into the EnzymeML format. Scheme 4 Oxidation of ABTS catalysed by the laccase from Trametes pubescens, including the oxidation of ABTS. The brackets indicate the oxidized state of the products, for which the exact molecular structure is not known. By using a Jupyter Notebook (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S10</ref>), the data for the oxidation of ABTS were extracted using the PyEnzyme library, visualized using matplotlib, and modelled by six kinetic models (SI equation 6 -8, with and without bias). The models were based on an irreversible Michaelis-Menten model, extended by assuming a bias or enzyme inactivation.</p><p>All models estimated a KM value higher than the highest initial substrate concentration of 150 µM (Table <ref type="table">S7</ref>). The resulting estimated parameters were not reliable and had very high estimated standard errors. The model with time-dependent enzyme inactivation and bias (model 4) showed the best fit statistics and the smallest errors of the six models (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>). It resulted in a KM value of 190 ± 22 µM and kcat of 1.05 ± 0.08 s -1 for ABTS oxidation. The KM value is higher than what was previously reported monitoring initial reaction rates of product formation: 43 µM <ref type="bibr">7</ref> and 50 and 60 µM for two isoforms of T. pubescens laccase <ref type="bibr">8</ref> . Similarly, higher kcat values were observed in the previous studies. This might be explained by the fact that the complete time course was fitted by including an enzyme inactivation term. The enzyme inactivation parameter ki was 0.0018 ± 0.0001 s -1 . Using the equation 41 t1/2 = (ln2) / kI, this value corresponds to a half-life time of 6.5 minutes. The red curves resulted from the estimated parameters of model 4.</p><p>Due to the high estimated KM value, a second round of experiments and modelling with higher initial substrate concentrations could be performed.</p><p>Finally, model 4 with its estimated parameters was added to the EnzymeML document, and the document was uploaded to DaRUS (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S10</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scenario 5: Measuring and modelling of an enzyme cascade</head><p>The biocatalytic synthesis of β-lactam antibiotics is a promising method for efficient production of multiple β-lactam antibiotics <ref type="bibr">9</ref> . Xanthomonas campestris pv. campestris α-amino acid ester hydrolase (AEH, EC 3.1.1.43) is capable of stereoselective, single-step synthesis of several semi-synthetic β-lactam antibiotics, and is a promising catalyst for the synthesis of cephalexin <ref type="bibr">10</ref> , ampicillin, and other β-lactam antibiotics with unsubstituted phenyl side chains.</p><p>AEHs catalyse the direct coupling of an activated acyl donor (ester or amide) with a β-lactam ring-containing nucleophile to form an amide bond and generate the antibiotic product (Scheme Detailed kinetic models are necessary for accurate prediction of reactor design and configuration, but until recently, such mechanisms for AEH did not exist. In a previous study by Lagerman et al. <ref type="bibr">10</ref> , potential kinetic models for AEH catalysed synthesis of cephalexin that include the primary reactions shown in Scheme 5 were identified and fitted to eight time-course reactions at a wide range of initial concentrations of substrates, both the electrophile (R)phenylglycine methyl ester and the nucleophile 7-aminodesacetoxycephalosporanic acid (7-ADCA). The kinetic models and the corresponding parameters are depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref>.  <ref type="bibr">10</ref> . The identified kinetic model allowed for simulation of several reactor configurations for AEH catalyzed synthesis of cephalexin, and substrate inhibition was found to limit the use of AEH in several reactor configurations <ref type="bibr">11</ref> .</p><p>The dataset was provided as an EnzymeML spreadsheet and converted to an EnzymeML document. The EnzymeML document was extended by the kinetic model 4 proposed by Lagerman et al. <ref type="bibr">10</ref> , and the modelling platforms PySCeS and COPASI were used for parameter estimation via dedicated thin layer modules that are part of the EnzymeML toolbox. The resulting estimated parameters were finally added to the EnzymeML document.</p><p>Using the dedicated thin layer modules, the parameters estimated by COPASI and PySCeS were similar (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>), but differed from the published values. As pointed out by Lagerman et al. <ref type="bibr">10</ref> , not all parameters were uniquely identifiable from the available experimental data, which might explain the deviation from the published parameters. Although COPASI and PySCeS used the same initial values and optimization algorithms, there were still some differences, in some cases &gt;30%. This indicates that modelling the same reaction cascade via mass action kinetics can dramatically affect parameter estimation when parameters cannot be uniquely identified from the experimental data. On the other hand, a simulation of the concentration of the intermediates using the estimated parameters confirmed the previous steady state approximation <ref type="bibr">34</ref> .</p><p>Differences in results obtained through mass action kinetics versus steady state kinetics may be explained through experimental system deviations from model assumptions such as incomplete equilibrium or the system not fully in steady state. This scenario demonstrates the need of comparing different modelling approaches and the usefulness of providing experimental data in a standardized format. Having the capability to analyze enzyme kinetics through different models with a single platform can give users further insight into discrepancies and underlying mechanisms. Furthermore, the usage of PyEnzyme allows researchers to modify models on the fly to enable model exploration. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scenario 6: Measuring the stability of enzymes</head><p>As the enzyme-based industry continues to grow, the stability of enzymes remains an issue, particularly under industrial process conditions. Exposure to harsh environments compromises the structural conformation, causing them to unfold and lose their function and activity.</p><p>Therefore, it is crucial to investigate and understand enzyme stability, which for now is a fundamental research question that remains unanswered <ref type="bibr">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> . What is mainly unknown is how the enzymes are deactivated in the presence of different process conditions, such as agitation and a gas-liquid interface. Numerous enzyme-based reactions require a sufficient gas supply to produce the desired product, but the presence of a gas-liquid interface induces enzyme deactivation. Investigating the gas-liquid interface is especially interesting when working with oxidases, as they allow the use of molecular oxygen as an electron acceptor under mild conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> .</p><p>Thus, a particular target in the present work was to investigate the stability of glucose oxidase (GOx EC: 1.1.3.4) <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> , which was characterised as the loss of activity over time caused by the conditions <ref type="bibr">12</ref> . The experiments were performed in a stirred tank reactor (2.5 L) with an enzyme concentration of 0.01 g/L in demineralized water where no reaction was taking place. The process conditions in the experiments were kept constant, including the concentration of GOx and the temperature of 50 °C. The investigated conditions include different stirring speeds, aeration flow and bubble size. A colourimetric enzyme assay measured the initial rate of the activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> . GOx catalyses the oxidation of glucose to gluconolactone, which further spontaneously hydrolyses to gluconic acid. The activity of GOx is determined based on a simultaneous reaction catalysed by horse-radish peroxidase (HRP), producing a pink product from the generated hydrogen peroxide reacting with 4-aminoantipyrine (AAP) and 3,5dichloro-2-hydroxybenzenesulfonic acid (DCHBS) (Scheme 6). The accumulation of the pink product was measured by the increase in absorbance by a spectrophotometer.</p><p>Cl Cl OH SO 3 H N N CH 3 N H 2 O CH 3 C 6 H 5 H 2 O 2 N N N HO 3 S O Cl O C 6 H 5 CH 3 CH 3 O H O H H O H H H OH H OH OH + O H 2 + GO x O 2 OH COOH H O H H O H H OH H OH + H 2 O 2 O H 2 + + + HRP 0 4-Aminoantipyrine (4-AAP) 3,5-Dichloro-2-hydroxybenzenesulfonic acid (DCHBS) N-(4-antipyryl)-3-3chloro-5-sulfonate-pbenzoquinone-monoamine (Pink product)</p><p>Scheme 6 Simultaneous reactions taking place in the enzyme assay. In the first step, glucose is oxidized by GOx to gluconolactone. Next, the generated hydrogen peroxide reacts in a horseradish peroxidase assay (HRP), forming a pink product that can be detected.</p><p>The pink product's accumulation rate measures the catalytic rate of glucose oxidase when there is an excess of HRP, making GOx the limiting factor. The use of the PyEnzyme software generated the EnzymeML document for the dataset. The absorbance triplicates measured after the individual time periods were assigned to the same measurement in all cases (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7</ref>). The name of the measurement indicated the time interval after which the triplicates were obtained.</p><p>A Jupyter Notebook (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S10</ref>) was created to read the EnzymeML document with the PyEnzyme software. After an overview of the metadata and a visualisation of the measurements with matplotlib, initial rates were calculated with linear regression of the SciPy library (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">8</ref>). The results were identical to those in the Excel sheet, where the rate was calculated from the slope of the absorbance according to the Lambert-Beer law and the extinction coefficient of the pink product at 515 nm <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> . Finally, the EnzymeML document was uploaded to DaRUS (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S10</ref>).  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure S2</head><p>The structure of an EnzymeML document.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The EnzymeML spreadsheet</head><p>The spreadsheet is structured into subsheets, referring to different aspects of the experiment (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2</ref>, <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">S3</ref>).</p><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_20">S3</ref> General structure of the EnzymeML spreadsheet. Shown is the first subsheet, containing information about the creator of the dataset and references to available publications. By filling in the spreadsheet, the different species, the vessel, and the reactions are assigned to an internal identifier. Experimental conditions, including the temperature, pH value, and nonaqueous solvents can be specified in the 'Reactions' section. The 'Data' section contains time courses for the individual experiments and replicates, together with the initial concentrations of all species. Both concentration and absorbance values can be given over the time. The selected kinetic model and the estimated kinetic parameters can be specified in the spreadsheet. They are not mandatory for the conversion of the spreadsheet to an EnzymeML document, but can be added later to an existing EnzymeML document by calling the add model function of the RESTful API. The spreadsheet also allows to link to existing publications referring to the dataset, alternatively a DOI can be given if available. It can be found on the PyEnzyme GitHub repository (<ref type="url" target="https://github.com/EnzymeML/PyEnzyme/blob/main/templates/EnzymeML_Template.xlsm">https://github.com/EnzymeML/PyEnzyme/blob/main/templates/EnzymeML_Template.xlsm</ref>) The PyEnzyme REST-API The Python library PyEnzyme, which is used to interact with EnzymeML documents, is also available as a REST-API service. It has been implemented using the Open API specification 3 and FastAPI, which is a Python library to build REST endpoints. In Figure S4 screenshots display the SWAGGER documentation page of all given endpoints. Endpoints facilitate core operations and are divided into three groups (Table S1): (1) Basic operations are given that directly facilitate reading, writing and modification of an EnzymeML document. (2) Conversion operations allow users to turn EnzymeML spreadsheets and validation templates into EnzymeML documents and validation YAML files, respectively. (3) Database operations are performed to validate an EnzymeML document and upload it to a Dataverse installation.</p><p>Table S1 Endpoints available for the PyEnzyme REST-API. Group refers to the type of operation the endpoint corresponds to. Endpoint specifies the address from which the service is reached. Type specifies the HTTP request. Description briefly outline functionality. Group Endpoint Type Description Basic /create POST Creates an EnzymeML document from a JSON body Basic /read POST Reads an EnzymeML document saved in an OMEX archive to a JSON representation. Basic /add_measurement POST Adds a measurement to an existing EnzymeML document. Conversion /template/download GET Download the EnzymeML spreadsheet Conversion /template/upload GET HTML website to upload the EnyzmeML spreadsheet document and conversion to EnzymeML. Conversion /template/convert POST Converts an EnzymeML spreadsheet template to an EnzymeML document. Conversion /validation/download GET Download the EnzymeML validation template. Conversion /validation/upload GET HTML website to upload the EnzymeML Validation template and convert it to a YAML file. Conversion /validation/convert POST Convert the EnzymeML Validation template to a YAML template to use it for validation on server site. Database /validation POST Validates an EnzymeML document based on a given EnzymeML Validation YAML file. Returns a boolean and report, if validation has failed. Database /upload/dataverse POST Uploads an OMEX archive to a Dataverse installation. Jupyter Notebook-based workflow platform All scenarios are accompanied by a Jupyter Notebook. These notebooks describe the process of the data analysis including the kinetic modelling and generate the figures shown in the paper, thus making the analysis reproducible. All Jupyter Notebooks and the respective EnzymeML documents are available at GitHub: <ref type="url" target="https://github.com/EnzymeML/Lauterbach_2022">https://github.com/EnzymeML/Lauterbach_2022</ref>. The folder structure of the GitHub repository follows the structure of the paper. For running a notebook, we recommend to use Binder, with a clickable Binder badge on GitHub. Alternatively, they can be run by Google Colaboratory (Colab) via the Colab badges in the notebooks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Modelling by COPASI and PySCeS</head><p>Kinetic modelling was performed by using PyEnzyme's thin layer implementation for PySCeS (TL_PySCeS) and COPASI (TL_COPASI). The OMEX file was loaded using the class method fromFile in the EnzymeMLDocument class. The resulting EnzymeMLDocument object was transferred to the Thin Layers' optimize method followed by the write method, which returned a modified EnzymeMLDocument with the estimated parameters for each rate law. Finally, the document was written to an OMEX archive using the EnzymeMLDocuments object method toFile.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PySCeS Thin Layer</head><p>The Python Simulator for Cellular Systems (PySCeS) library is a simulation framework used in Systems Biology and in the course of this work has been adapted to kinetic modelling of enzymatic reactions. For this, a new Thin Layer (TL_PySCeS) has been developed that utilizes the simulation power of PySCeS in conjunction with the optimization library lmfit. In addition, the Thin Layer has been implemented on a new base class BaseThinLayer, which is inherited and automatically extracts content relevant for modelling. This includes the SBML model, proposed rate laws for each reaction as well as the experimental data that have been collected using EnzymeML.</p><p>The Thin Layer implementation starts by converting the SBML model found in the EnzymeML document to a PSC model file using PySCeS's convertSBML2PSC-method. The saved file is then parsed using PySCeS model-method. In order to proceed, the Thin Layer initializes an lmfit Parameters-object by utilizing the values given in the initial_value attribute if given.</p><p>Otherwise it is also possible to provide a YAML file that holds initial values for each parameter per reaction that will set given values to the initial_values attribute. The advantage of an external file is that these values can be altered without manipulating the EnzymeML document.</p><p>Thus many different initial guesses can be applied to the same document. Once initialization has been done, the lmfit Minimizer object will be instantiated to iteratively optimize the given PySCeS model instance based on the calculate_residuals method. The latter recursion simulates the model given the current set of parameters and calculates the residuals per iteration.</p><p>After each iteration the parameters will be altered.</p><p>At convergence the optimization algorithm stops and the write-method is called, which copies the given EnzymeMLDocument and adds the estimated parameters to each KineticParameter -25 -value attribute per reaction model. Finally, the resulting EnzymeMLDocument object can be used for further analysis or be written to an OMEX archive using the objects toFile-method.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Modelling by interferENZY</head><p>The Jupyter Notebook for the modelling by interferENZY exists in two versions, using either the PyEnzyme library or the read function of the RESTful API. In both cases, relevant information such as enzyme and initial substrate concentrations, the name of the dataset, all units, and the time-course data are read in. Time-course values must be measured for at least five different substrate concentrations and fixed enzyme concentration. Continuous assays, stopped assays, product and substrate concentrations can be modelled. The user can choose which reactant concentrations should be modelled. Then, the data are formatted using regular expressions and written into a separate tab-delimited text (.txt) file, which is uploaded to interferENZY. Results are stored in a separate .txt file, which are integrated into the Jupyter Notebook. In this second step, the kinetic parameters are added to the existing EnzymeML document. Alternatively, the parameters can be added manually to the document.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Validation of EnzymeML documents</head><p>EnzymeML documents are validated by PyEnzyme prior to a database upload, if the database provides an EnzymeML validation schema. An EnzymeML validation schema is a YAML file, which specifies the requirements of the database for each object present in PyEnzyme. For instance, if the database requires a protein sequence, it will be marked as "mandatory" in the EnzymeML validation schema, otherwise it is marked as "optional" or "not supported". The EnzymeML validation schema can be created by using the EnzymeML validation spreadsheet or a YAML template.</p><p>An EnzymeML document is validated using the EnzymeMLDocument classes validate method by fetching the YAML file from the database server and inferring the existence and type of a field. Validation is successful, if all mandatory fields exist in the given EnzymeML document.</p><p>In addition, the user is informed if and where validation failed, in order to enable adjustment of the EnzymeML document. In the case of a Dataverse upload, validation is performed by pyDaRUS, because the importance of each field is given in the EnzymeML metadata block.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Test suite</head><p>With increasing complexity of PyEnzyme, the library has been equipped with a comprehensive test suite to not only guarantee consistent functionality when developing new features, but also to allow outside collaborators to contribute safely. In total 76 tests were implemented to cover all interface functionalities as well as important sub-processes. Finally, the test process was implemented in a Continuous Integration pipeline, which performs testing upon committing new source code.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Upload to SABIO-RK</head><p>The EnzymeML document of Scenario 1, containing the kinetic parameters obtained by interferENZY was uploaded to SABIO-RK. The following entry was generated (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">S5</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scenario 1: Analysing a series of initial rate data using Michaelis-Menten kinetics</head><p>Detailed description of the method (this document is part of the OMEX archive)</p><p>Recombinant bacterial cysteine desulfurase (IscS) and iron-sulfur cluster assembly enzyme (IscU) were obtained as previously described <ref type="bibr">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr">[3]</ref> , with minor alterations. The corresponding genes were previously subcloned into pET-derived plasmid vectors, which were used as fusion proteins containing a C-terminal His6-tag or His6-tagged glutathione-S-transferase (GST) tag, for IscS and IscU, correspondingly. Both constructs contained a tobacco etch virus (TEV)</p><p>protease cleavage site for tag removal. Briefly, IscS and IscU were overexpressed in Escherichia coli BL21(DE3) and subsequently purified by nickel-affinity and size-exclusion chromatography.</p><p>Catalysis of L-cysteine by IscS in the presence of IscU to L-alanine and persulfide was measured by sulfide (S 2-) quantification through the methylene blue assay. A modified version of the method described by Siegel (1965) <ref type="bibr">4</ref> was employed to quantify persulfide as a product of the enzymatic reaction, through its conversion to hydrogen sulfide (H2S) gas and subsequent incorporation into methylene blue <ref type="bibr">5</ref> . Enzymatic reactions were performed in Tris 50 mM pH H2S gas loss was avoided by using 10 mm wide rubber septa stoppers in 10x75 mm test tubes for each sample: rubber stoppers were pierced using Hamilton ® GASTIGHT ® syringes (1710 RN, 100:1 µl, ga22s/51mm/pst2) to add the reagents for reaction quenching. After methylene blue development, samples were transferred to new tubes and centrifuged for 5 minutes at &gt;17,000xg. Methylene blue was then quantified by absorbance at λ=670 nm 6 using a Cary 50 Bio (Varian) spectrophotometer. Assays were performed in triplicate. A calibration curve was built using solutions with known concentration of Na2S in Tris 50 mM pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl (without DTT) for conversion of the resulting methylene blue absorbance to concentration of product S 2-.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scenario 2: Analysing time-course data using Michaelis-Menten kinetics</head><p>Detailed description of the method (this document is part of the OMEX archive)</p><p>In this method, the decrease in pyruvate was determined photometrically at a wavelength of 333 nm. Pyruvate consumption can be followed from the absorbance, since the absorbance of the product, acetolactate is negligible at 333 nm <ref type="bibr">7</ref> . The procedure was divided into the following steps:</p><p>(a) 850 µL of the assay buffer (Table <ref type="table">S2</ref>) was mixed with 100 µL of the AHAS subunits (2 mg/mL) in a cuvette and incubated for 10 min at 37 °C.</p><p>(b) Addition of 50 µL of a 1 M pyruvate solution and subsequent mixing of the reaction mixture started the reaction. The absorbance of the mixture at 333 nm was measured over a period of 5 min.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table S2</head><p>Different reagents and their corresponding concentrations in the used buffer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Buffer</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reagent concentration [mM]</head><p>Reaction buffer pH 7.6 Buffer (K2HPO4 -/KH2PO4 -) (KPi) 100 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Modelling</head><p>For the modelling in Scenario 2, the following equations were defined in Python. Table S3 Mathematical definition of variables used in the equations S1-S5. Variable Description unit vmax maximal enzymatic reaction rate at the given conditions mM/min cS substrate concentration mM KM Michaelis-Menten constant mM v enzymatic reaction rate dependent on enzyme activation mM/min a rate of enzyme activation 1/min ΔcS residual between measured and calculated substrate concentration mM cS_measured measured substrate concentration mM cS_modelled substrate concentration calculated with the model mM bias static bias to account for absorbance independent of pyruvate mM Ki dissociation constant of the enzyme for S mM Ks concentration of S that gives 1/3 vmax for Ki &lt;&lt;Ks mM</p><p>From this, five models were derived and fitted against all data points. The substrate concentration is defined as cS (Table <ref type="table">S2</ref>).  measurement by assuming by assuming a gradual activation of the enzyme until it reaches its maximum activity (equation S2 in combination with equation S1b). This gradual activation term introduces one additional parameter a describing the rate of enzyme activation, thus three parameters are fitted. Model 4 considers both a bias and a lag phase, resulting in the aforementioned four parameters, vmax, KM, bias and a, to be fitted.</p><p>Since the dataset included only measurements of the absorbance but not the concentration values, the initial value cS0 needed to be determined. Therefore, cS0 was set as an additional variable parameter for all models. Model 5 is derived from the steady-state rate equation for enzymes with two substrates 8 . In this case both substrates are pyruvate, so A=B=S and assuming Ka = Kb = KS for both pyruvates (equation S5). Combined with equation S2 and S4, model 5 was fitted against the data. For all models, curve-fitting was performed with the Python libraries lmfit and SciPy (Table <ref type="table">S4</ref>). All results were converted from absorbance to concentration (Table <ref type="table">S4</ref>, S5).</p><p>Table <ref type="table">S4</ref> From absorbance measurement by lmfit estimated parameters with standard errors before conversion to concentration and Akaike Information Criterion (AIC). The parameters are given in relative units of absorbance.</p><p>Model 1 Model 2 Model 3 Model 4 Model 5 c S0 1.03 ± 0.06 0.919 ± 0.006 0.951 ±0.004 0.861 ± 0.005 0.882 ± 0.02 bias 0.105 ± 0.004 0.097 ± 0.004 0.078 ± 0.02 v max [min -1 ] 0.262 ± 0.008 0.225 ± 0.003 0.59 ± 0.12 0.28 ± 0.01 0.259 ± 0.03 K M 0.096 ± 0.015 0.002 ± 0.004 0.50 ± 0.14 0.048 ± 0.011 a [min -1 ] 0.86 ± 0.16 1.7 ± 0.2 1.9 ± 0.3 K i 1 ± 7 K s 0.004 ± 0.02 AIC -1290 -1380 -1439 -1499 -1500</p><p>Table S5 Estimated parameters for the five different models applied to the time-course data of Scenario 2, with standard errors after conversion to concentration using an extinction coefficient of 24.8 L‧ cm -1 ‧ mol -1 Model 1 Model 2 Model 3 Model 4 Model 5 c S0 [mM] 41.7 ± 0.2 37.0 ± 0.2 38.3 ± 0.2 34.7 ± 0.2 25.6 ± 0.8 bias [mM] 4.2 ± 0.2 3.9 ± 0.2 3.1 ± 0.8 v max [mMmin -1 ] 10.6 ± 0.3 9.1 ± 0.1 24 ± 5 11.4 ± 0.4 10.5 ± 1 Specific activity [Umg -1 ] 53 ± 2 46 ± 1 121 ± 25 57 ± 2 53 ± 5 K M [mM] 3.9 ± 0.6 0.07 ± 0.16 20 ± 6 1.92 ± 0.44 a [min -1 ] 35 ± 7 69 ± 6 76 ± 10 K i [mM] 39 ± 285 K s [mM] 0.17 ± 1 c S0 +bias [mM] 41.7 ± 0.2 41.3 ± 0.4 38.3 ± 0.2 38.6 ± 0.4 38.7 ± 1.6</p><p>Table S6 Estimated parameters for the five different models applied to the time-course data of Scenario 2, with standard errors after conversion to concentration using an extinction coefficient of 19.2 L‧ cm -1 ‧ mol -1 Model 1 Model 2 Model 3 Model 4 Model 5 c S0 [mM] 53.8 ± 0.3 47.9 ± 0.3 49.5 ± 0.2 44.8 ± 0.3 45.9 ± 1 bias [mM] 5.5 ± 0.2 5.1 ± 0.2 4.1 ± 1 v max [mMmin -1 ] 13.7 ± 0.4 11.7 ± 0.2 31 ± 7 14.7 ± 0.56 13.5 ± 1 Specific activity [Umg -1 ] 69 ± 2 59 ± 1 155 ± 32 74 ± 3 68 ± 6 K M [mM] 5.0 ± 0.8 0.09 ± 0.2 26 ± 7 2.5 ± 0.6 a [min -1 ] 45 ± 8 88 ± 8 98 ± 13 K i [mM] 51 ± 368 K s [mM] 0.2 ± 1 c S0 +bias [mM] 53.8 ± 0.3 53.3 ± 0.5 38.3 ± 0.2 49.9 ± 0.5 50 ± 2  Subsequently, a second equation was added, resulting in a system of two coupled differential equations (equation S6 and equation S7). This extended the Michaelis-Menten kinetic with a time-dependent enzyme inactivation, by the additional parameter ki describing the rate of the enzyme inactivation. The fit was performed once with a fixed bias of 0 for model 3 and a variable bias for model 4. Figure S15 Time course of the reaction ABTS + O2 → radical form + H2O, catalysed by laccase at pH 5 for 9 different initial concentrations, all measurements were performed in triplicates.</p><p>The red curve resulted from the estimated parameters of model 4.</p><p>As in Scenario 2, for all six models, curve fitting was performed with lmfit. The results are shown in Table <ref type="table">S8</ref>.</p><p>Table S8 Estimated kinetic parameters by applying six different kinetic models Model 1 Model 2 Model 3 Model 4 Model 5 Model 6 k cat [1/s] 37 ± 2210 38 ± 193 1.5 ± 0.2 1.05 ± 0.08 49 ± 258 58 ± 340 K M [µM] 15400 ± 16800 15400 ± 78600 340 ± 47 190 ± 23 15400 ± 81500 15400 ± 54000 bias [µM] 0.66 ± 0.38 2.03 ± 0.32 2.84 ± 0.35 k i [1/s] 1.6‧ 10 -3 ± 10 -4 1.8‧ 10 -3 ± 10 -4 1.4‧ 10 -5 ± 10 -6 1.8‧ 10 -5 ± 10 -6 AIC 1996 1995 1590 1555 1822 1747 RMSE 5.79 5.78 4.04 3.91 4.96 4.64 the measurement data reported by Lagerman et al. 10 . Next, we demonstrate how to fit a single measurement, we extract the measurement of substrate s0 of the first reaction and create a Pandas DataFrame for them. At this point we load the EnzymeML document into basico, where we rename the species for more convenient display, and assign missing initial concentrations. Now the model can be simulated, and we show how to assign some kinetic equations to the reaction. This can be done by picking a suitable kinetic for the function database (we show this by applying Mass Action kinetics first), then we create a kinetic manually with a specific expression. Once that is done, we define that all parameters of that kinetic should be estimated, set the measurement data as experimental data, and run the parameter estimation. The results retrieved are the same as demonstrated in modelling the same dataset and reaction in Python (<ref type="url" target="https://github.com/EnzymeML/Lauterbach_2022/blob/main/Scenario5/LMFit/Model_Lagerm">https://github.com/EnzymeML/Lauterbach_2022/blob/main/Scenario5/LMFit/Model_Lagerm</ref> ann_s0.ipynb). Next, we create a new COPASI model in basico, where we use the ODEs provided by Lagerman et al 10 , to directly create a kinetic model for them. For simplicity, we define several helper functions, to create all parameters, and the parameter estimation setup. We then run the parameter estimation. Since it is unlikely that running methods just once will lead the best results, we describe how to prepare the model for submission to cluster environments and demonstrate how to run them using the command line version of COPASI. The final section of the Notebook demonstrates how to create a kinetic model from scratch, and we manually specify all individual reaction steps using mass action kinetics, following the reaction scheme a displayed in the Lagerman 2021 publication. Using the same functions from earlier, we also set up the parameter estimation and initial values. Using a global method this time, we start a first fit. Again, the model is prepared for running in cluster environments by choosing random start values, save the file. The best fits obtained are stored in the result folder. From there one would look at whether the parameters are identifiable and robust (see <ref type="bibr">11</ref> for more details).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Modelling by PySCeS</head><p>For the application in Scenario 5 the newly developed PySCeS Thin Layer was utilized, but first the given EnzymeML document had to be adapted to the micro-kinetic model proposed by Lagerman et al. using the PyEnzyme library. For this, the macro-kinetic reaction has been removed and replaced by a set of reactions that represent the micro-kinetic model. Prior to that, any intermediate substance as well as any protein-substrate complex were added to the model using the Reactant and Complex classes respectively. The latter were introduced to the PyEnzyme library in the scope of this work and are a collection of participating species (proteins and reactants) that form the complex. In the resulting SBML model these will still act as normal species and thus maintain compatibility towards SBML-based modelling tools such as COPASI and PySCeS. Finally, the resulting EnzymeML document was loaded as input to the PySCeS Thin Layer in conjunction with a YAML file that holds initial estimates for each parameter per reaction in the model to perform the optimization. Once the parameter estimation had finished, the gathered values were documented in an EnzymeMLDocument object and written to an OMEX archive. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_26">S21</ref> depicts the global fit to the data from all the experiments when modelled with the optimized parameter values.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Comparison of the modelling results</head><p>To compare different modelling tools, kinetic modelling based on the data by Lagerman et al.</p><p>was performed with COPASI and PySCeS, using the PyEnzyme API as a common interface.</p><p>This allowed the same OMEX archive (with the experimental data and kinetic model definition)</p><p>and YAML file (containing initial parameter estimates) to be used as input for both modelling tools. The estimated parameters differed slightly between COPASI and PySCeS, although the agreement was surprisingly good with differences &gt;30% being rare (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). In addition, the estimated parameters were also different from the original values reported in Lagerman et al.;     this was most probably the result of correlations between some parameters (Table <ref type="table">S9</ref>). The limited identifiability of the system was already observed the original authors. These correlations also caused differences between the results of COPASI and PySCeS, although these were not as big because the same Levenberg-Marquardt optimization algorithm was used in both tools.</p><p>The results presented here are significant for two reasons: first, two simulation platforms give similar parameter estimates even under conditions where parameters correlate, and second, PyEnzyme with its Thin Layers provides a unified interface to these simulation platforms, allowing the use of the same input data in standard formats. As a next step, the modelling tools can be used to further adjust the model and to resolve these ambiguities. However, this goes beyond the scope of the current workflow example.</p><p>Table S9 Correlations between parameters as calculated by COPASI. discovered by the authors. These correlations also cause r K_si K_n K_s k_2 k_6 k_3 K_pg k_5 k_4 k_4b K_p K_n 0.99 K_s 0.11 0.24 k_2 1.00 0.99 0.11 k_6 -0.06 0.06 0.85 -0.06 k_3 0.99 1.00 0.21 0.99 0.07 K_pg 0.99 1.00 0.25 0.99 0.05 0.99 k_5 0.24 0.21 -0.27 0.24 0.13 0.28 0.19 k_4 0.26 0.22 -0.28 0.26 0.13 0.30 0.20 0.98 k_4b -0.45 -0.46 -0.21 -0.44 -0.14 -0.46 -0.46 -0.12 -0.12 K_p -0.63 -0.65 -0.23 -0.63 -0.14 -0.65 -0.64 -0.20 -0.20 0.97 k_d -0.26 -0.28 -0.21 -0.26 -0.03 -0.27 -0.31 0.20 0.20 -0.09 -0.02 Table 1: Correlations between parameters as calculated by COPASI.</p><p>peroxide present to produce the pink product. The rate of the accumulation of the pink product is a measure of the glucose oxidase catalysed reaction when there is an excess of HRP compared to GOx. Experiments were carried out to ensure an excess of HRP, making GOx the limiting factor. Provided that GOx is the limiting factor, adding the double amount of GOx results in a doubled reaction rate. Whereas adding more HRP should not have any effect on the rate of reaction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scheme 1:</head><p>Simultaneous reactions taking place in the enzyme assay.</p><p>The procedure for enzyme assay is illustrated in the following (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S22</ref>). The first step was to sample each reactor/flask, which only contained GOx and water. The samples were analysed three times to ensure valid data. Subsequently, glucose, HRP, DCHBS, 4-APP, and buffer (total of 1 mL) was added to a cuvette and mixed. Experiments were performed to determine the added amount (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S10</ref>). Next, GOx was added to the cuvette, which again was mixed and added to the spectrophotometer. This step had to be very fast, as the aim was to measure the initial velocity. The change in absorbance was measured at 515 nm for 59 seconds.</p><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S10</ref> Overview of the amount and the concentration of solutions used in the enzyme assay.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Component</head><p>Concentration Used amount [µL] GOx 0.5 g/L 20 HRP 1 g/L 200 Glucose 1 M 100 4-AAP 1.0 mM 100 DCHBS 10 mM 100</p><p>Kpi buffer 50 mM 480 replicates per measurement was taken. With the mean, the initial rates and the residual activity were calculated as described above. Finally, initial rates and residual activity were visualised.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Additional Material</head><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S11</ref> Links to Jupyter Notebooks and datasets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Jupyter Notebooks Links</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2 Time-course data of the reaction from cysteine to alanine by the cysteine desulfurase, starting from different substrate concentrations. The kinetic parameters were estimated according to the Michaelis-Menten model, in a Jupyter Notebook-based workflow, resulting in the fit shown in red.</figDesc><graphic coords="5,120.05,70.85,355.20,312.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Scheme 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Scheme 2 Carboligation of two molecules pyruvate, yielding acetohydroxyacid, catalysed by the large subunit of the acetohydroxyacid synthase from Helicobacter canadensis (HcAHAS). Absorbance values at 333 nm for the carboligation of pyruvate were measured over the course of 5 minutes. The time courses were repeated for six different pH values, between 5.5 and 8, the measurements were conducted as technical triplicates. The time course data were entered in the EnzymeML spreadsheet, as they were measured at 333 nm and converted to an EnzymeML document. Two control measurements of the absorbance of the reaction mixture without pyruvate or without enzyme showed a constant absorbance at 333 nm of 0.058 ± 0.001 and 0.864 ± 0.007, respectively.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,169.80,70.85,255.62,73.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3 Time course of the reaction 2 pyruvate → acetolactate + CO2, catalysed by an acetohydroxyacid synthase at pH 7. The measurement was performed in triplicate (blue dots).</figDesc><graphic coords="7,120.90,70.85,353.50,242.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4 Time course for the reaction 2 propanal → propioin, catalysed by a benzaldehyde lyase from Pseudomonas fluorescens, the reaction was performed in a technical triplicate.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,116.90,252.44,361.35,248.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5 Time course of the reaction ABTS + O2 → radical form + H2O, catalysed by laccase at pH 5.0 for 9 different initial concentrations. All measurements were performed as triplicates.</figDesc><graphic coords="11,130.90,70.85,333.48,236.45" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>5 ,Scheme 5 :</head><label>55</label><figDesc>Scheme 5: Reactions catalysed by α-amino acid ester hydrolase (AEH, EC 3.1.1.43) including direct synthesis of the antibiotic (Reaction 1), hydrolysis of the activated acyl donor (Reaction 2), and hydrolysis of the antibiotic (Reaction 3).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6 Kinetic model scheme for the AEH catalysed synthesis of cephalexin, as defined in Lagerman et al. The reaction scheme includes eight time-course reactions onto which the measured data was fitted. Initial (R)-phenylglycine methyl ester concentration ranged from 20 -140 mM at constant 40 mM 7-ADCA in one set of reactions and 7-ADCA ranged from 10 -60 mM at constant 20 mM (R)-phenylglycine methyl ester in another set. Focus was given to high initial substrate concentrations to identify sources of observed substrate inhibition by (R)-phenylglycine methyl ester. The reactions were performed using 200 nM purified AEH at 25 °C in 100 mM sodium phosphate buffer held at pH 7.0. Substrate and product concentrations were measured over the course of 30 minutes using HPLC. Potential kinetic models were fit before conversion into the EnzymeML format using nonlinear fitting algorithms in Matlab. Lagerman et al. found substrate inhibition by (R)-phenylglycine methyl ester even at moderate concentrations (KSI =20 mM)10  . The identified kinetic model allowed for simulation of several reactor</figDesc><graphic coords="13,140.75,70.85,313.80,221.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7 Time-course data of the change in absorbance over 1 minute. The different curves correspond to different exposure times of the enzyme to the conditions within the stirred tank reactor. Each measurement consists of three replicates, and the curves show the average.</figDesc><graphic coords="17,104.90,70.85,385.48,307.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8 Calculated relative activity of the initial rates. The data points are the mean of the three replicates, measured after the indicated time interval. Each data point also includes error bars of the standard deviation over all replicates. The activity is compared to the immediate measurement without delay.</figDesc><graphic coords="17,103.08,440.80,389.15,241.49" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure S4 '</head><label>S4</label><figDesc>Figure S4 'Reactants' and 'Data' subsheet of the EnzymeML spreadsheet, shown for the oxidation of syringaldazine with data from Sandile Ngubane.</figDesc><graphic coords="21,70.85,166.92,453.60,133.05" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure S4</head><label>S4</label><figDesc>Figure S4 Screenshot of the PyEnzyme REST-API documentation, which can be reached at https://enzymeml.sloppy.zone</figDesc><graphic coords="22,70.85,91.55,453.60,314.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure S6</head><label>S6</label><figDesc>Figure S6 Screenshot of the SABIO-RK entry generated from the dataset of Maria Pinto (Entry-ID: 73347). The entry to the database was generated by upload of an EnzymeML document.</figDesc><graphic coords="28,91.40,70.85,412.00,485.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>7. 5 ,</head><label>5</label><figDesc>150 mM NaCl, with 1 μM IscS, 2 μM IscU, and 3 mM DTT. Reactions were started by addition of the substrate L-cysteine (Sigma) and quenched at different time intervals at 37 °C in a stopped assay procedure. Replicate samples with reaction volume 800 μL were analysed for each intended timepoint. All solutions were equilibrated to reaction temperature for at least 30 minutes prior usage. Reaction quenching was done by the addition of 100 μL of 20 mM N,N-Dimethyl-p-phenylenediamine dihydrochloride (DPD.2HCl) in 7.2 N HCl followed by the addition of 100 μL of 30 mM FeCl3 in 1.2 N HCl. The samples were manually shaken for 1 minute and incubated in the dark at 20 °C for at least 1 hour for methylene blue development.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>FAD</head></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><figDesc>c S_measured -c S_modelled (equation S3) ∆c S = c S_measured -c S_modelled + bias (equation S4) dc S dt = -vc S 2 /(k i k s + 2k s c S + c S 2 ) (equation S5)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Model 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>is the irreversible Michaelis-Menten model (equation S1a). It describes the change of the concentration of substrate cS and includes the parameter vmax and the Michaelis-Menten constant KM. For saturating substrate concentrations, the parameter vmax gives the maximal enzymatic reaction rate and corresponds to the steepest slope of the measured time course.After integration with Scipy, the residual ΔcS was computed (equation S3). The two parameters vmax and KM, were fitted to this model.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Figure S7</head><label>S7</label><figDesc>Figure S7 Time course of the reaction 2 pyruvate → acetolactate + CO2, catalysed by an acetohydroxyacid synthase at pH 7. The measurement was performed in triplicate (blue dots). The red curve resulted from the estimated parameters of the unmodified irreversible Michaelis-Menten kinetic (model 1).</figDesc><graphic coords="32,109.38,195.04,376.54,271.05" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Figure S9</head><label>S9</label><figDesc>Figure S9 Time course of the reaction 2 pyruvate → acetolactate + CO2, catalysed by an acetohydroxyacid synthase at pH 7. The measurement was performed in triplicate (blue dots). The red curve resulted from the estimated parameters of the irreversible Michaelis-Menten kinetic extended by a second differential equation for the change of the enzymatic reaction rate (model 3).</figDesc><graphic coords="34,110.93,174.34,373.41,268.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Figure S10</head><label>S10</label><figDesc>Figure S10 Time course of the reaction 2 pyruvate → acetolactate + CO2, catalysed by an acetohydroxyacid synthase at pH 7. The measurement was performed in triplicate (blue dots). The red curve resulted from the estimated parameters of the combination of the irreversible Michaelis-Menten kinetic with static bias and the change of the enzymatic reaction rate (model 4).</figDesc><graphic coords="35,107.78,195.04,379.73,273.35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Figure S11</head><label>S11</label><figDesc>Figure S11 Time course of the reaction 2 pyruvate → acetolactate + CO2, catalysed by an acetohydroxyacid synthase at pH 7. The measurement was performed in triplicate (blue dots). The red curve resulted from the estimated parameters of the combination of the simplified irreversible Michaelis-Menten kinetic for two substrates with static bias and the change of the enzymatic reaction rate (model 5).</figDesc><graphic coords="36,108.30,132.94,378.66,255.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Scenario 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Collecting data by BioCatHub and visualisationDetailed description of the method (this document is part of the OMEX archive)Production of catalystThe biocatalyst was formulated as lyophilized whole cells (LWC). Genes encoding PfBAL were cloned and expressed heterologously in Escherichia coli (BL21) in autoinduction medium. The cultures grew for 2 h at 37 °C and subsequently for 48 h at 20 °C before the cells were harvested at 4 °C at 8000 rpm for 45 min. The cell pellets were frozen at -20 °C and then lyophilized at -54 °C and 0.01 mbar for 48 h and crushed after lyophilization using a spatula.The catalyst was stored at -20 °C until usage.Enzymatic ligation of propanalIn 1.5 mL glass vials, 30 mg of lyophilized whole cells containing PfBAL were added to 1 mL of reaction solution, consisting of cyclopentyl methyl ether (CPME) as a reaction solvent with 200 mM propanal as substrate. The enzymatic reaction was started by the addition of 30 µl 1 M TEA buffer pH 9 with 0.1 mM ThDP and 2.5 mM MgCl2. The reaction was incubated at 30 °C and 1000 rpm in an Eppendorf shaker for 24 h and samples were analysed via gas chromatography. A Thermo Fisher Trace 1310 GC was used with an Agilent CP-Chirasil-Dex CB chiral column (inner diameter 0.25 mm; 25 m x 0.25 µm). The oven was heated in a gradient (40 °C hold 0.5 min, to 55 °C with 17 °C/min, hold 0.5 min to 73 °C with 10 °C/min to 82 °C with 15 °C/min hold 2.5 min to 117 °C with 20 °C/min hold 2.2 min to 140 °C with 26 °C/min to 190 °C with 50 °C/min). Retention time of (R)-propioin was 8.4 min, for (S)-propioin 8.577 min.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>Figure S13</head><label>S13</label><figDesc>Figure S13 Time course of the reaction ABTS + O2 → radical form + H2O, catalysed by laccase at pH 5 for 9 different initial concentrations, all measurements were performed in triplicates.The red curve resulted from the estimated parameters of model 2.</figDesc><graphic coords="42,102.65,70.85,389.25,277.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head>Figure S14</head><label>S14</label><figDesc>Figure S14 Time course of the reaction ABTS + O2 → radical form + H2O, catalysed by laccase at pH 5 for 9 different initial concentrations, all measurements were performed in triplicates.The red curve resulted from the estimated parameters of model 3.</figDesc><graphic coords="43,103.03,70.85,389.25,277.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head>Figure S18</head><label>S18</label><figDesc>Figure S18Resulting fit obtained in the procedure described above.</figDesc><graphic coords="47,70.85,319.23,432.00,288.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_24"><head>Figure S19</head><label>S19</label><figDesc>Figure S19 Example fit, as obtained by running the Notebook on the ODE model. Basico can display them by running `plot_per_experiment()`. The notebook displays all of them.</figDesc><graphic coords="48,70.85,70.85,432.00,288.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_25"><head>Figure S20</head><label>S20</label><figDesc>Figure S20Running the Mass action based model, also returns a fit as obtained by `plot_per_dependent_variable()`. This returns a plot for each measured species.</figDesc><graphic coords="49,70.85,70.85,432.00,288.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_26"><head>Figure S21</head><label>S21</label><figDesc>Figure S21 Best global fit of the optimized microkinetic model (lines) to the experimental data from Lagerman et al. (points). Parameter optimization was performed with the PySCeS Thin Layer as described in the text by simultaneous fitting to all eight data sets, with different initial concentrations (m0 -m8). Optimized parameter values are given in Table 1. Key: s0 -PGME; s1 -7-ADCA; s2 -CEX; s3 -PG.</figDesc><graphic coords="50,92.15,70.85,411.00,616.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="20,109.15,140.94,376.70,208.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="20,100.15,500.80,394.93,206.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="24,268.95,253.64,220.75,426.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="33,112.95,174.34,369.39,265.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="41,103.03,373.23,389.25,277.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><graphic coords="54,70.85,70.85,446.89,183.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Parameter estimation result of Scenario 5. Given are the original estimations by Lagerman et al. as well as those from PySCeS and COPASI modelling.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Parameter</cell><cell>Units</cell><cell>Lagerman et al.</cell><cell>COPASI</cell><cell>PySCeS</cell></row><row><cell>KS</cell><cell>mM</cell><cell>14  6</cell><cell>5.7</cell><cell>5.1</cell></row><row><cell>k2</cell><cell>s -1</cell><cell>432  4</cell><cell>10861</cell><cell>9491</cell></row><row><cell>KN</cell><cell>mM</cell><cell>290  7</cell><cell>6.5</cell><cell>11.0</cell></row><row><cell>k3</cell><cell>s -1</cell><cell>417  1</cell><cell>0.15</cell><cell>0.26</cell></row><row><cell>k4</cell><cell>s -1</cell><cell>73600  5</cell><cell>31114</cell><cell>26291</cell></row><row><cell>k5</cell><cell>s -1</cell><cell>491  2</cell><cell>11153</cell><cell>14743</cell></row><row><cell>k6</cell><cell>s -1</cell><cell>1660  2</cell><cell>6539</cell><cell>4159</cell></row><row><cell>KSi</cell><cell>mM</cell><cell>20  10</cell><cell>6.3</cell><cell>5.4</cell></row><row><cell>Kp</cell><cell>mM</cell><cell>39  2</cell><cell>0.9</cell><cell>1.3</cell></row><row><cell>k-4</cell><cell>s -1</cell><cell>9126  10</cell><cell>709</cell><cell>613</cell></row><row><cell>[E]0</cell><cell>mM</cell><cell>1.98  0.1 10 -4</cell><cell>210 -4</cell><cell>210 -4</cell></row><row><cell>kd</cell><cell>s -1</cell><cell>6.43  2.1 10 -4</cell><cell>0.008</cell><cell>0.005</cell></row><row><cell>KPG</cell><cell>mM</cell><cell>12  7</cell><cell>49</cell><cell>130</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary information on scenarios, and more details on methods and results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table of contents EnzymeML metadata block for Dataverse as publication platform</head><p>The configuration of the EnzymeML metadata block as TSV-File is published under DOI: 10.18419/darus-2105. Model 2 extends model 1 with an additional parameter to describe a constant bias to all measured substrate concentrations cS_measured, resulting in three parameters to be fitted. Therefore, the residual ΔcS was modified (equation S4). The bias accommodates for the absorbance of other compounds than pyruvate, such that the absorbance does not reach zero when all pyruvate has been converted. The enzyme (40.34 µM, 6.57 U/mg), ABTS (0.1 -2.0 mM), buffer (50 mM sodium acetate, pH 5.0), and 3.5 ml quartz cuvettes were separately pre-incubated at appropriate temperatures (25°C, 30°C, 40°C, 50°C or 60°C) for 5 minutes. The reaction mixture comprised 2.499 ml of buffer, 0.33 ml of ABTS and 0.171 ml of the enzyme. The blanking solution contained buffer, enzyme and distilled water. ABTS oxidation was monitored at 354 nm with an Agilent Cary 60 UV-Vis spectrophotometer (Agilent Technologies, US) at 60-second intervals for 20 minutes.</p><p>A solution containing ABTS and buffer only was used at time zero. All readings were carried out in triplicate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Determination of temperature stability of Trametes pubescens laccase</head><p>Laccase (40.34 µM, 6.57 U/mg), ABTS (0.1 -2.0 mM), buffer (50 mM sodium acetate, pH 5.0), and 3.5 ml quartz cuvettes were incubated separately at appropriate temperatures (30°C, 40°C, 50°C, or 60°C) for the duration of the experiment (i.e. 5 hours per ABTS concentration).</p><p>Laccase activity was monitored hourly over the 5-hour period. The reaction mixture contained 2.499 ml of buffer, 0.33 ml of ABTS and 0.171 ml of the enzyme. All reactions were carried at the appropriate temperature (30°C, 40°C, 50°C or 60°C). ABTS oxidation was monitored with an Agilent Cary 60 spectrophotometer (Agilent Technologies, US) at 60-second intervals for 20 minutes. All absorbance readings were carried out in triplicate.</p><p>Effect of pH on laccase-catalysed oxidation of 2,2'-Azinobis (3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6sulphonic acid) (ABTS)</p><p>The effect of pH on laccase-catalysed oxidation of ABTS was determined within the range pH 3.0 -9.0 by performing the reactions in different buffers [50 mM sodium citrate buffer (pH 3.0 -5.5), 50 mM sodium phosphate buffer (pH 6.0 -8.0) and 25 mM sodium tetraborate-HCl buffer (pH 8.5 -9.0)] at 60°C. ABTS oxidation was monitored at 354 nm with an Agilent Cary 60 UV-Vis spectrophotometer (Agilent Technologies, US) at 60-second intervals for 20 minutes. The same buffers were used to determine the rate of laccase deactivation at different pH values. All readings were carried out in triplicate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Determination of pH stability of Trametes pubescens laccase</head><p>The pH stability of laccase was monitored within the range pH 3.0 -9.0 by incubating the enzyme (40.34 µM, 6.57 U/mg) at each pH value for 5 hours. Residual enzyme activity was monitored hourly. The reaction mixtures contained 2.499 ml of buffer, 0.33 ml of ABTS and 0.171 ml of the enzyme. All reactions were carried out at the enzyme optimum temperature (60°C). ABTS oxidation was monitored with an Agilent Cary 60 spectrophotometer (Agilent Technologies, US) at 60-second intervals for 20 minutes. All absorbance readings were carried out in triplicate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Effect of organic solvents on laccase activity</head><p>Laccase was analysed for its ABTS oxidation rate in the presence of various organic solvents (i.e. DMSO, acetone, ethyl acetate, methanol, dioxane or ethanol) at varying concentrations (25%, 50% or 75%). The reaction mixtures contained 2.499 ml of buffer/organic solvent, 0.33 ml of ABTS and 0.171 ml of the enzyme. ABTS oxidation was monitored at 354 nm with an Agilent Cary 60 UV-Vis spectrophotometer (Agilent Technologies, US) at 60-second intervals for 20 minutes at 60°C. All readings were carried out in triplicate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Determination of enzyme stability in organic solvents</head><p>The enzyme was pre-incubated in each co-solvent system consisting of organic solvent (DMSO, acetone, ethyl acetate, methanol, dioxane or ethanol) at varying concentrations (25%, 50% or 75%), and a 50 mM sodium acetate buffer (pH 5.0) for the duration of the experiment (5 hours).</p><p>All reactions were carried out at 60°C. Enzyme activity was monitored hourly over the 5-hour incubation period. The reaction mixtures contained 2.499 ml of buffer/organic solvent, 0.33 ml of ABTS and 0.171 ml of the enzyme. ABTS oxidation was monitored with an Agilent Cary 60 spectrophotometer (Agilent Technologies, US) at 60-second intervals for 20 minutes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Modelling</head><p>For the modelling in Scenario 4 the following equations were defined. In model 2, the bias was included as an additional parameter to be fitted. were all obtained from TCI America (Portland, OR).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Time-course reactions</head><p>For the time-course reactions, reaction mixtures were maintained at 25.0 °C and gently shaken in an Eppendorf ThermoMixer. An AEH concentration of 200 nM was used in each experiment.</p><p>All reactions were conducted in 100 mM sodium phosphate buffer and maintained at pH 7.0.</p><p>PGME was varied from 20 -140 mM while maintaining a constant 7-ADCA concentration at 40 mM. Additional experiments maintained PGME at 20 mM while varying 7-ADCA from 10 -60 mM. Samples of 50 μL were periodically withdrawn over 30 minutes and diluted 5fold in 80% methanol to quench the reaction for measurement on HPLC.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HPLC analysis</head><p>Kinetic analysis was conducted using HPLC with a Shimadzu-LC-20AT pump, Hichrom Ultrasphere C18, 4.6 mm × 25 cm column packed with 5 μm particles, and SPD-M20A</p><p>prominence diode array detector (PDA) monitored at 215 nm. For measurement of substrates and products during cephalexin synthesis reactions, the mobile phase was run as a gradient at 1.0 mL/min starting with 95% 10 mM sodium phosphate buffer, pH 7.0 and 5% methanol for 1.5 minutes before decreasing to 85% phosphate buffer linearly from 1.5 -4 minutes and decreasing again to 50% phosphate at 7 minutes. The mobile phase was held at 50% phosphate buffer for 2 minutes before equilibration at 95% phosphate buffer for 10 minutes. All components, PG, PGME, 7-ADCA, and cephalexin were analysed on the HPLC with &gt;95% mass balance closure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Modelling by COPASI</head><p>The Jupyter Notebook for the modelling by COPASI uses basico <ref type="bibr">9</ref> (a high-level python API providing access to COPASI's model editing and simulation and analysis methods) and the PyEnzyme library. The Jupyter Notebook starts by reading in the EnzymeML document with Scenario 6: Measuring the stability of enzymes Detailed description of the method (this document is part of the OMEX archive)</p><p>The experimental work aims to understand the loss of the activity of glucose oxidase (GOx) caused by several industrial representative conditions. The stability of GOx was characterised as the loss of deactivation over time caused by the conditions. The process conditions in the experiments were kept constant, including the concentration of GOx, and no reaction was taking place. The activity of GOx was determined based on a simultaneous reaction catalysed by horseradish peroxidase (HRP), producing a pink product from the generated hydrogen peroxide reacting with 4-aminoantipyrine (AAP) and 3,5-dichloro-2-hydroxybenzenesulfonic acid (DCHBS). Suppose any produced hydrogen peroxide immediately reacts in the HRP catalysed reaction to form the pink product. In that case, the rate of accumulation of the pink product is a measure of the glucose oxidase catalysed reaction rate. The accumulation of the pink product was measured by the increase in absorbance by a spectrophotometer. The advantage of this method is that it shows the result after just 1 minute, but the disadvantage is that the concentration of oxygen cannot be measured or controlled.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental setup</head><p>The experiments were carried out in a 2.5 L stirred tank reactor (Sartorius bioreactor biostatA).</p><p>The reactor was equipped with a metal sparger that supplied oxygen from the bottom of the reactor by sparging. Two spargers are available: ring formed sparger and micro-sparger with 20 µm pores. Additionally, the reactors were equipped with two Rushton turbines (diameter 5 cm) to ensure mixing, a sampling tube, and a temperature probe with a control system. The conditions within the reactors were controlled at an interface on a computer. Two reactors were available in the laboratory.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Enzyme Assay</head><p>The protocol for determining the kinetic parameters for glucose oxidase has been published previously <ref type="bibr">12</ref> . GOx catalyses glucose oxidation to hydrogen peroxide (H2O2) and D-Glucono-1,5-lactone, which is spontaneously hydrolysed to gluconic acid in the presence of water (Scheme 1). The reaction was carried out in an open system. Hence the oxygen used in the reaction is atmospheric air. The produced hydrogen peroxide reacts in the simultaneous Horseradish peroxidase (HRP) catalysed reaction where a pink product is produced (Scheme 1). The HRP catalysed reaction is extremely fast and immediately uses hydrogen </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Modelling</head><p>The initial rate (V) is calculated from the slope of the absorbance time-course data using the Lambert-Beer equation. The extinction coefficient of the pink product at 515 nm is 26 mM - 1 cm -1 <ref type="bibr">12</ref> .</p><p>The initial rate is equal to the change in concentration over time, and the slope of the absorbance curves shows the change in absorbance over time, thus the equation can be written as:</p><p>The enzyme stability is documented as the residual activity compared to an initial measured activity (a0):</p><p>Residual activity = a a 0 • 100%</p><p>The modelling was reproduced in a Jupyter Notebook. As in the previous scenarios, the data were extracted with the PyEnzyme software and the time-course data were visualised. For the calculation of the initial rates, linear regression of the Python library Scipy was used. For each time-course, the slope of the first 30 data points was calculated, then the mean of the three</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Iron-sulfur cluster biosynthesis. Characterization of frataxin as an iron donor for assembly of [2Fe-2S] clusters in ISU-type proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cowan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6078" to="6084" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Yoon, T. &amp; Cowan, J. A. Iron-sulfur cluster biosynthesis. Characterization of frataxin as an iron donor for assembly of [2Fe-2S] clusters in ISU-type proteins. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 125, 6078-6084 (2003).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">interferENZY: A Web-Based Tool for Enzymatic Assay Validation and Standardized Kinetic Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Pinto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">433</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">166613</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Pinto, M. F. et al. interferENZY: A Web-Based Tool for Enzymatic Assay Validation and Standardized Kinetic Analysis. J. Mol. Biol. 433, 166613 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Binding and Activation of Thiamin Diphosphate in Acetohydroxyacid Synthase</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bar-Ilan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11946" to="11954" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bar-Ilan, A. et al. Binding and Activation of Thiamin Diphosphate in Acetohydroxyacid Synthase. Biochemistry 40, 11946-11954 (2001).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Expression, Reinigung und Identifizierung putativer Acetolactatsynthasen aus Clostridium aceticum und Helicobacter canadensis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Malzacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Klonierung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5281/ZENODO.6090180</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Malzacher, S. Klonierung, Expression, Reinigung und Identifizierung putativer Acetolactatsynthasen aus Clostridium aceticum und Helicobacter canadensis. (2017). doi:10.5281/ZENODO.6090180.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymmetric Synthesis of Aliphatic 2-Hydroxy Ketones by Enzymatic Carboligation of Aldehydes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>María</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>De</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European J. Org. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2940" to="2944" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007. 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">María, P. D. de et al. Asymmetric Synthesis of Aliphatic 2-Hydroxy Ketones by Enzymatic Carboligation of Aldehydes. European J. Org. Chem. 2007, 2940-2944 (2007).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Applied biocatalysis beyond just buffersfrom aqueous to unconventional media. Options and guidelines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M C H</forename><surname>Schie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Van</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-D</forename><surname>Spöring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bocola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>María</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rother</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Green Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3191" to="3206" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Schie, M. M. C. H. van, Spöring, J.-D., Bocola, M., María, P. D. de &amp; Rother, D. Applied biocatalysis beyond just buffers -from aqueous to unconventional media. Options and guidelines. Green Chem. 23, 3191-3206 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterization of the major laccase isoenzyme from Trametes pubescens and regulation of its synthesis by metal ions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Galhaup</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Goller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Peterbauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Strauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Haltrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Microbiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2159" to="2169" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Galhaup, C., Goller, S., Peterbauer, C. K., Strauss, J. &amp; Haltrich, D. Characterization of the major laccase isoenzyme from Trametes pubescens and regulation of its synthesis by metal ions. Microbiology 148, 2159-2169 (2002).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isolation and Purification of enzymes from ligninolytic complex of the basidial fungus Trametes pubescens (Schumach.) Pilát and study of their properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Nikitina</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemistry. (Mosc)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1274" to="1279" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nikitina, O. V. et al. Isolation and Purification of enzymes from ligninolytic complex of the basidial fungus Trametes pubescens (Schumach.) Pilát and study of their properties. Biochemistry. (Mosc). 70, 1274-1279 (2005).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Model development for enzymatic reactive crystallization of β-lactam antibiotics: A reaction-diffusion-crystallization approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Salami</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">React. Chem. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2064" to="2080" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Salami, H. et al. Model development for enzymatic reactive crystallization of β-lactam antibiotics: A reaction-diffusion-crystallization approach. React. Chem. Eng. 5, 2064- 2080 (2020).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinetic model development for α-amino ester hydrolase (AEH)-catalyzed synthesis of β-lactam antibiotics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lagerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Grover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Rousseau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bommarius</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Eng. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">426</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">131816</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lagerman, C. E., Grover, M. A., Rousseau, R. W. &amp; Bommarius, A. S. Kinetic model development for α-amino ester hydrolase (AEH)-catalyzed synthesis of β-lactam antibiotics. Chem. Eng. J. 426, 131816 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reactor Design and Optimization of α-Amino Ester Hydrolase-Catalyzed Synthesis of Cephalexin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lagerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Grover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Rousseau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bommarius</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Bioeng. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">0</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">301</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lagerman, C. E., Grover, M. A., Rousseau, R. W. &amp; Bommarius, A. S. Reactor Design and Optimization of α-Amino Ester Hydrolase-Catalyzed Synthesis of Cephalexin. Front. Bioeng. Biotechnol. 0, 301 (2022).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stabilizing biocatalysts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bommarius</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Paye</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Soc. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6534" to="6565" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bommarius, A. S. &amp; Paye, M. F. Stabilizing biocatalysts. Chem. Soc. Rev. 42, 6534- 6565 (2013).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bubble Column Enables Higher Reaction Rate for Deracemization of (R,S)-1-Phenylethanol with Coupled Alcohol Dehydrogenase/NADH Oxidase System</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dias Gomes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Synth. Catal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">361</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2574" to="2581" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Dias Gomes, M. et al. Bubble Column Enables Higher Reaction Rate for Deracemization of (R,S)-1-Phenylethanol with Coupled Alcohol Dehydrogenase/NADH Oxidase System. Adv. Synth. Catal. 361, 2574-2581 (2019).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reaction Engineering for the Industrial Implementation of Biocatalysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Woodley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Top. Catal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1202" to="1207" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Woodley, J. M. Reaction Engineering for the Industrial Implementation of Biocatalysis. Top. Catal. 62, 1202-1207 (2019).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Online Measurement of Oxygen-Dependent Enzyme Reaction Kinetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Meissner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nordblad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Woodley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ChemBioChem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="113" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Meissner, M. P., Nordblad, M. &amp; Woodley, J. M. Online Measurement of Oxygen- Dependent Enzyme Reaction Kinetics. ChemBioChem 19, 106-113 (2018).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovery, characterization, and kinetic analysis of an alditol oxidase from Streptomyces coelicolor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P H M</forename><surname>Heuts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Van Hellemond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Janssen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Fraaije</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://github.com/EnzymeML/Lauterbach_2022/tree/main/Scenario1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">282</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20283" to="20291" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Heuts, D. P. H. M., Van Hellemond, E. W., Janssen, D. B. &amp; Fraaije, M. W. Discovery, characterization, and kinetic analysis of an alditol oxidase from Streptomyces coelicolor. J. Biol. Chem. 282, 20283-20291 (2007). Scenario 1 https://github.com/EnzymeML/Lauterbach_2022/tree/main/Scenario1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.18419/darus-248310.18419/darus-2470Scenario</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.18419/darus-2466" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Datasets Links Scenario</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Scenario 2 https://github.com/EnzymeML/Lauterbach_2022/blob/main/Scenario2/AnalysingTimeCourseDataUsingMichaelisMenten.ipynb Scenario 3 https://github.com/EnzymeML/Lauterbach_2022/blob/main/Scenario3/CollectingDataByBioCatHubAndVisualisation.ipynb Scenario 4 https://github.com/EnzymeML/Lauterbach_2022/blob/main/Scenario4/InsightIntoMechanismByModelling.ipynb Scenario 5 https://github.com/EnzymeML/Lauterbach_2022/tree/main/Scenario5/ Scenario 6 https://github.com/EnzymeML/Lauterbach_2022/blob/main/Scenario6/MeasuringTheStabilityOfEnzymes.ipynb Datasets Links Scenario 1 Scenario 2 https://doi.org/10.18419/darus-2483 https://doi.org/10.18419/darus-2470 Scenario 3 https://doi.org/10.18419/darus-2466</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.18419/darus-2467</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.18419/darus-2467" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Scenario 4 https://doi.org/10.18419/darus-2467</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.18419/darus-2468</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.18419/darus-2468" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Scenario 5 https://doi.org/10.18419/darus-2468</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.18419/darus-2469</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.18419/darus-2469" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Scenario 6 https://doi.org/10.18419/darus-2469</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Table S12 Software, databases, and formats BioCatHub https</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Table S12 Software, databases, and formats BioCatHub https://</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solution structure of the bacterial frataxin ortholog, CyaY: Mapping the iron binding sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nair</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Structure</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2037" to="2048" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Nair, M. et al. Solution structure of the bacterial frataxin ortholog, CyaY: Mapping the iron binding sites. Structure 12, 2037-2048 (2004).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A structural approach to understanding the iron-binding properties of phylogenetically different frataxins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Adinolfi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Trifuoggi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Politou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pastore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mol. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1865" to="1877" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Adinolfi, S., Trifuoggi, M., Politou, A. S., Martin, S. &amp; Pastore, A. A structural approach to understanding the iron-binding properties of phylogenetically different frataxins. Hum. Mol. Genet. 11, 1865-1877 (2002).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bacterial frataxin CyaY is the gatekeeper of iron-sulfur cluster formation catalyzed by IscS</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="390" to="396" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S, A. et al. Bacterial frataxin CyaY is the gatekeeper of iron-sulfur cluster formation catalyzed by IscS. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol. 16, 390-396 (2009).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A direct microdetermination for sulfide</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Siegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Siegel, L. M. A direct microdetermination for sulfide. Anal. Biochem. 11, 126-132 (1965).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Catalysis of L-cysteine by IscS in the presence of IscU (dataset formatted for analysis by interferENZY)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Pinto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5281/zenodo.3957403</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Pinto, M. F. Catalysis of L-cysteine by IscS in the presence of IscU (dataset formatted for analysis by interferENZY). (2020) doi:10.5281/zenodo.3957403.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effector role reversal during evolution: the case of frataxin in Fe-S cluster biosynthesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bridwell-Rabb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Iannuzzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pastore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Barondeau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2506</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bridwell-Rabb, J., Iannuzzi, C., Pastore, A. &amp; Barondeau, D. P. Effector role reversal during evolution: the case of frataxin in Fe-S cluster biosynthesis. Biochemistry 51, 2506 (2012).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Purification and Properties of Salmonella typhimurium Acetolactate Synthase Isozyme II from Escherichia coli HB101/pDU9t</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Schloss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="922" to="925" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Schloss, J. V et al. Purification and Properties of Salmonella typhimurium Acetolactate Synthase Isozyme II from Escherichia coli HB101/pDU9t. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A 24, 922-925 (1985).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Roskoski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Michaelis-Menten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kinetics</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/B978-0-12-801238-3.05143-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ref. Modul. Biomed. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Roskoski, R. Michaelis-Menten Kinetics. Ref. Modul. Biomed. Sci. (2015) doi:10.1016/B978-0-12-801238-3.05143-6.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bergmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lilijap</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.5281/ZENODO.5654594</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bergmann, F. &amp; lilijap. copasi/basico: Release 0.4. (2021) doi:10.5281/ZENODO.5654594.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinetic model development for α-amino ester hydrolase (AEH)-catalyzed synthesis of β-lactam antibiotics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lagerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Grover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Rousseau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bommarius</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Eng. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">426</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">131816</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Lagerman, C. E., Grover, M. A., Rousseau, R. W. &amp; Bommarius, A. S. Kinetic model development for α-amino ester hydrolase (AEH)-catalyzed synthesis of β-lactam antibiotics. Chem. Eng. J. 426, 131816 (2021).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Easy parameter identifiability analysis with COPASI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schaber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biosystems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="183" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Schaber, J. Easy parameter identifiability analysis with COPASI. Biosystems. 110, 183-185 (2012).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovery, characterization, and kinetic analysis of an alditol oxidase from Streptomyces coelicolor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P H M</forename><surname>Heuts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Van Hellemond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Janssen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Fraaije</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">282</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20283" to="20291" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Heuts, D. P. H. M., Van Hellemond, E. W., Janssen, D. B. &amp; Fraaije, M. W. Discovery, characterization, and kinetic analysis of an alditol oxidase from Streptomyces coelicolor. J. Biol. Chem. 282, 20283-20291 (2007).</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
