<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">DIRECTED EVOLUTION: CREATING BIOCATALYSTS FOR THE FUTURE</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">U.S. Department of Energy&apos;s program in Biological and Chemical Technologies Research within the Office of Industrial Technologies, Energy Efficiency and Renewables</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">U.S. Office of Naval Research</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability  status="unknown">
					<licence/>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="1995-09-21">21 September 1995</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Frances</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Chemistry and Chemical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">California Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>210-41</addrLine>
									<postCode>CA91125</postCode>
									<settlement>Pasadena</settlement>
									<country key="US">U.S.A</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">DIRECTED EVOLUTION: CREATING BIOCATALYSTS FOR THE FUTURE</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="1995-09-21">21 September 1995</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F67BBDF48A34CE312ACEA7A83360CFCD</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 10 October 1995; accepted 28 January 1996</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-24T14:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[0], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>An effective approach to engineering new enzymes is to direct their evolution in vitro. By mimicking key processes of Darwinian evolution in the test tube, the functions of enzymes can be explored free from the constraints of function within a living system. Efficient strategies for engineering new enzymes by multiple generations of random mutagenesis and recombination coupled with screening for improved variants have been developed. Our results with industrially important biocatalysts underscore the advantages of this 'evolutionary' approach to protein engineering. (From a talk presented at the first National Academy of Engineering "Frontiers of Engineering" Symposium,</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="533.0" lry="771.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="533.0" lry="771.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="533.0" lry="771.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="533.0" lry="771.0"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="533.0" lry="771.0"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="533.0" lry="771.0"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="533.0" lry="771.0"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="533.0" lry="771.0"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="533.0" lry="771.0"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="533.0" lry="771.0"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="533.0" lry="771.0"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="533.0" lry="771.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Biological systems are the masters of chemical synthesis. The remarkable specificity of their catalysts, the enzymes, allows hundreds of reactions to proceed simultaneously inside the tiny reactor that is a living cell. Enzymes' ability to carry out complex chemical reactions, and to do so under very mild conditions with virtually no waste products, has earned them the admiration of chemists and biochemists. It is easy to envision that a future chemical industry sensitive to both energy needs and the environment could be modeled after these highly efficient chemical factories.</p><p>The molecules responsible for this remarkable performance are the enzymes. Enzymes are proteins, linear chains of typically hundreds of amino acids that fold up into unique, well-defined three-dimensional structures. The backbone of the polymer chain folds into a structure that is unique to the particular catalyst, as illustrated in <ref type="bibr">Fig. l(a)</ref> for the enzyme subtilisin. The enzyme's substrate (gray), the compound on which the reaction is catalysed, fits snugly into the substrate binding pocket. The enzyme positions specific catalytic amino acid side chains (red) where they can assist the chemical reaction to proceed. In <ref type="bibr">Fig. l(b)</ref> the structure of subtilisin showing its amino acid side chains illustrates the complexity of these molecular machines. This complexity allows enzymes to perform the truly impressive functions that support life and create new life. The result of considerable finetuning over eons of evolution, this complexity also makes it difficult to manipulate these structures to obtain new and interesting properties.</p><p>An enzyme is defined by a unique sequence of amino acids, which in turn is dictated by the organ-ism's DNA code (the gene) and assembled in the cell (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>). This amino acid sequence determines how the chain folds and, ultimately, how the enzyme functions. By modifying the amino acid sequence, we can alter the enzyme's function--this field is known as protein engineering. Despite intense research into fundamental features governing protein folding and function, there are enormous gaps in our understanding of two critical processes: the relationship between sequence and structure and the relationship between structure and function. As a result, the rational design of new proteins by the classical 'reductionist' approach can be a frustrating exercise indeed. In this article I will introduce a new and highly effective approach to enzyme design and engineering that bypasses the need to understand these processes before embarking on a protein engineering project. But first I will explain why the enzymes provided by nature are not sufficient.</p><p>Chemical engineers who try to design real industrial processes using biological catalysts are constantly stymied by a simple fact: biological systems have evolved over billions of years to perform very specific biological functions and to do so within the context of a living organism. Some of the features required for function in a complex chemical network are undesirable when the catalyst is lifted out of context. Conversely, many of the properties we wish an enzyme would have clash with the needs of the organism, or at least were never required. The chemical engineer is hardly impressed by a catalyst whose inability to tolerate the most common of industrial conditions necessitates complicated hardware and reactors of the size of football fields. We need catalysts which are stable to high temperatures, can function in solvents other than water, tolerate wider ranges of pH,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="20">natural amino acids, (~ (~) assembled in the cell according to DNA instructions (~ "°"</head><p>Function, " properties ' ,0A ' Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. Protein engineering involves the manipulation of protein structures and functions at the level of the amino acid (or DNA) sequence. Significant gaps in our understanding of the relationships between sequence, structure and function severely limit our ability to 'rationally design' new functions.</p><p>catalyse reactions on substrates not encountered in nature, and even catalyse new reactions not found in nature.</p><p>Many clues as to how to engineer better enzymes come from studying how nature has created enzymes. By studying the evolution of natural proteins, we have learned in fact that they are highly adaptable, constantly changing molecules, at least over evolutionary time scales. They can adapt to new environments and they can even take on new tasks. We know, for example, that many enzymes catalysing very different reactions have come about by divergent evolution from a common ancestral protein of the same general structure, acquiring diverse capabilities by processes of random mutation, recombination, and natural selection. For example, the versatile protein structure known as the ~/fl barrel diverged somewhere in the distant past to create a whole series of enzymes we know today <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Reardon and Farber, 1995)</ref>. The four enzymes shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">3</ref>(a), for example, catalyse quite different reactions; their physical properties and amino acid sequences are also quite disparate. It is useful to note that, while the barrel-like protein fold is highly conserved, the amino acid sequences and functions of these enzymes are not.</p><p>A fascinating recent example of enzyme evolution is the appearance of phosphotriesterase, an a/fl barrel enzyme that hydrolyses, at diffusion-limited rates, pesticides and chemical warfare agents that have existed only for about 50 years. It has been suggested that this enzyme, discovered in a soil bacterium, evolved during the last 50 years from a related sequence identified in the common E. coli bacterium and now known as the 'phosphotriesterase homology protein' <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Scanlan and Reid, 1995)</ref>. The biological function of this latter protein is unknown.</p><p>We also know that enzymes of a given function (for example, all catalysing a particular step in a metabolic pathway) can exhibit widely different properties (stability, solubility, tolerance to pH, etc.), depending on where they are found. For example, the three glyceraldehyde phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) enzymes listed in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">3</ref> quite different stabilities and amino acid sequences <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Buehner et al., 1974;</ref><ref type="bibr">Skarzynski et al., 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Korndoerfer et al., 1995)</ref>.</p><p>that they, too, diverged from some common ancestor a long time ago to occupy their current niches. The Thermotoga maritima bacterium thrives at very high temperatures in ocean thermal vents; consequently, its enzymes can tolerate much higher temperatures than the analogous enzymes from an organism which grows under less extreme conditions, such as B.</p><p>stearothermophilis. The Thermotoga protein unfolds at 98°C, while the same enzyme from the American lobster unfolds at only 50°C. As with the ~t//~ barrel enzymes, the structural fold of the GAPDHs is highly conserved, while the detailed amino acid sequences and specific properties are not.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DIRECTED EVOLUTION: EXPLORING NEW FUTURES</head><p>The explosion of tools that has come out of molecular biology during the last 20 years has made it possible for us to consider 'evolving' the components of biological systems--DNA, RNA and proteins--for features never required in nature. We can both speed up the rate and channel the direction of evolution by controlling mutagenesis--the rate and types of changes made--and the accompanying 'selection' pressures. As a result, processes that would take millions of years in nature can in principle be accomplished during the time scale of a Ph.D. thesis. By uncoupling the enzymes from the constraints of function within a living system, we can step into and explore a variety of futures, futures that can include novel environments (evolution in a sea of methanol instead of water?) or even entirely new functions (enzymes to break down hazardous chemicals?). We can explore questions such as 'can one catalytic activity become another, and how?' Furthermore, by evolving new functions and thereby new solutions to molecular design problems, we learn things about these amazing molecular machines that might never be revealed if we were to study only those that exist in nature.</p><p>The possibilities for biotechnology are especially exciting. Directed evolution is a very practical approach to tailor-making enzymes for a wide range of applications. In addition to building enzymes with new features and functions, we can explore important questions such as 'how might an enzyme change its sequence and properties to break down or evade a drug?' We could conceivably anticipate in laboratory experiments what might happen to drug resistances in nature. In directed evolution experiments we could also tune enzymes to function optimally under conditions specified by us, rather than the context of the living organism in which it evolved. New enzymes could be evolved to carry out reactions never required by living organisms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DEVELOPING A WORKING STRATEGY FOR DIRECTED ENZYME EVOLUTION</head><p>In a directed evolution experiment, we first generate a library of many different possible 'solutions' to a problem. The next step is to find the correct solution(s), enzymes that exhibit the desired property. A conceptual challenge comes in planning how to create this library of solutions. The number of possible enzymes one can make is so vast that an exploration of their functions must be carefully guided in order to avoid becoming hopelessly lost. A typical enzyme is a linear polymer of 300 amino acids. With 20 possible amino acids at each position in the chain, there are 20300 possible different linear combinations. If even only a small fraction--say, 1 in 101°--of all F. H. ARNOLD these sequences folds into a well-defined three-dimensional structure, there are still more structured proteins than there are atoms in the universe! (Note that even in three billion years, nature has not had a chance to explore but a tiny fraction of the possibilities. This also means that there are very exciting possibilities for future evolution, including evolution in the test tube.) Because a random sampling of amino acid sequences is unlikely to lead to the desired protein, we must begin our exploration by starting from a point that we hope is close to where we want to be--an enzyme that approximates what we want, but is not ideal. Then we evolve it, by accumulating small changes, similar to what happens in nature.</p><p>Nature is very good at searching mutant libraries for useful solutions. Unfavorable mutations are winnowed out at the same time as beneficial mutations are amplified, by linking the organism's growth rate and reproductive success to the performance of its components. In this process of selection, those organisms which grow faster quickly dominate, allowing an efficient search of very large populations (109 or more for bacteria).</p><p>Unfortunately, many of the features that are of interest to us cannot be linked to the survival or growth of the host organism--the prerequisite to selection. Enzymes, for example, can tolerate a variety of environments that cannot sustain life, so that the organism dies long before the enzyme has a chance to 'show its stuff'. For most problems of practical interest, in fact, mutant enzyme libraries must be screened rather than selected, one enzyme at a time. That is, the enzyme variants must be tested individually (screened) for the property of interest. This unfortunate reality effectively limits the search for improvements to mutant libraries containing perhaps 10'*-106 variants, several orders of magnitude smaller than what one can search when survival depends on Success.</p><p>The strategy for molecular evolution is then illustrated by calculating how many different sequences one can create by starting from a given enzyme and making a few amino acid substitutions, as shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. While there are only 5700 possible single mutants of a 300 amino acid enzyme, there are still more than 30 billion different sequences that differ from the original enzyme at only three positions. While a rapid screen might be able to cover a large fraction of all single mutants, and even some significant fraction of all double mutants, screening would be unable to give more than a very sparse sampling of the enzymes with multiple amino acid substitutions. Unless a vast majority of the mutations led to the desired property, dealing with a library of multiple mutations would be an experiment based on wishful thinking! (As might be expected for a finely tuned molecular machine, most mutations are deleterious or at least neutral; beneficial mutations are generally rare. The frequency with which one can expect to find beneficial mutations will depend on the extent to which the particular feature of interest has already been optimized: the pathways up the mountain necessarily decrease in number as the pinnacle is approached.) Because luck is generally not an acceptable basis for the success of an experiment, the search is effectively limited to proteins with sequences and therefore properties very similar to their parents. In addition, we must be able to tune the rate or mode of mutation to produce libraries of primarily single amino acid substitutions.</p><p>The principles and power of directed evolution are best illustrated with examples. The first example will be the evolution of an enzyme to function in a polar organic solvent. It is well known that subtilisin, which normally cuts up peptides and proteins by cleaving the peptide bonds linking the amino acids together, will also catalyse peptide bond formation. Peptide bond formation is favored in organic media, as water participates in unwanted side reactions as well as hydrolysis of the product. Subtilisin actually remains folded and reasonably stable in high concentrations of polar organic solvents such as dimethylformamide (DMF). Unfortunately, the catalytic activity is very low. There is no fundamental reason, however, why subtilisin could not function in DMF--the enzyme's unhappiness reflects a balance among a very large number of noncovalent interactions in the system-protein, solvent, substrates and products--a balance that is adversely affected when the protein is dissolved in a nonaqueous medium. Because these complex interactions are poorly understood, we could not address this problem by a rational design approach, We therefore took the 'irrational' approach and asked whether we could 'evolve' a subtilisin that would function well in DMF <ref type="bibr">(Chen and</ref><ref type="bibr">Arnold, 1991, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">You and Arnold, 1996)</ref>.</p><p>The arguments set out above led us to the strategy for directing the evolution of an enzyme to perform a new function (or, in this case of subtilisin, an old function but under new conditions) illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>. In comparison to the enzyme performing a function for which it is selected, peptide hydrolysis in aqueous media, the new job is performed poorly indeed. Subtilisin has not been selected for hydrolysis in DMF, and there is, not surprisingly, a great deal of </p><formula xml:id="formula_0">)M 300!,/[(300 -M)!M!].</formula><p>biocatalysts for the future 5097 room for improvement. Because it is feasible to search only those subtilisin mutants with one or two amino acid substitutions, we will create and screen a library of such mutants for progeny slightly better than their parent. The screening method for identifying useful mutations should ensure that the expected small enhancements brought about mainly by single mutations can be measured. Although these progenies will generally resemble their parents, after many generations new features can develop, such that the descendents can be quite different from their ancestor. Therefore, the generation of new, useful enzymes also relies on having an effective strategy for accumulating many such small improvements. One such strategy involves carrying out sequential generations of random mutagenesis on the gene (DNA sequence coding for the enzyme) to create a mutant library, coupled with screening of the resulting proteins. In each generation a single variant is chosen as the parent for the next generation, and sequential cycles allow the evolution of the desired features.</p><p>We implemented this strategy to evolve subtilisin to function in DMF. A powerful molecular biology tool, the polymerase chain reaction (PCR), was used to make millions of copies of the gene that codes for the natural, or wild-type enzyme. By carrying out this (enzymatic) reaction under sub-optimal conditions, we could introduce base substitutions randomly throughout the DNA at a controllable rate. At the end of this reaction we have millions of gene copies, most slightly different from the wild-type one. These genes are placed back into a circular double-stranded piece of DNA (a plasmid) that contains all the instructions the bacterial cells need to translate the DNA into protein. When the bacteria are transformed with these plasmids, we have millions of individual chemical factories, each producing a different variant of the original enzyme. The screening method should ensure that small enhancements brought about mainly by single mutations can be measured. The evolution of a new, useful enzyme requires an effective strategy for accumulating many such small improvements. Next, the bacterial colony or colonies which produce a subtilisin that is more active in DMF must be found. In this early experiment our screening strategy was crude, but effective. Because subtilisin is secreted from the bacilli, the variants could be screened visually on nutrient plates containing a protein (casein), in the presence and absence of DMF. The active enzyme creates a visible 'halo' surrounding the bacterial colony whose size is proportional to the catalytic activity.* Variants with higher hydrolysis activity than wild-type on the DMF-containing plates could be identified from their bigger halos <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Chen and Arnold, 1991)</ref>.</p><p>The results of the directed evolution effort are summarized in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5</ref>. At first we identified three amino acid substitutions that individually improved the wild-type enzyme's activity several-fold. Using sitedirected mutagenesis we combined those three with a fourth mutation reported to improve activity and stability in other subtilisins, to obtain a four amino acid variant about 40-fold more active than wild-type in 60% DMF <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Chen and Arnold, 1991)</ref>. Since the process of sequencing the genes of all the positive variants and then combining the mutations by sitedirected mutagenesis was laborious, we decided to carry out sequential generations of random mutagenesis and screening, no longer stopping on the way to sequence the intermediates. Applying an additional six generations of mutagenesis and screening a few hundred colonies in each generation, we created an *Because halo size also depends on enzyme expression level, enzyme diffusion and colony size, it is useful for a 'rough cut'. Positives were confirmed by a second level of screening in liquid culture <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Chen and Arnold, 1993)</ref>.</p><p>enzyme that is more than 500-fold more active in 60% DMF than the wild-type subtilisin E <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(You and Arnold, 1996)</ref>. This enzyme exhibits substantial activity even in 85% DMF. The whole process was surprisingly rapid: a total of only about 10,000 colonies were screened to obtain a huge improvement in catalytic activity.</p><p>The gene for the final evolved enzyme was sequenced to determine the amino acid substitutions that allowed this enzyme to recover its activity in DMF. Of 275 amino acids, 12 were altered; their positions are indicated in Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>. Although the DNA substitutions are targeted randomly throughout the entire subtilisin gene sequence, the amino acid substitutions that enhance catalytic activity are all positioned on the surface of the enzyme, surrounding the active site and substrate binding pocket. The majority are in evolutionarily variable loops that connect elements of conserved secondary structures (helices and sheets) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Chen and Arnold, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">You and Arnold, 1996)</ref>. This information could of course be utilized in developing more 'rational' design strategies, including narrowing the sequences exposed to random mutagenesis in directed evolution.</p><p>Finally, it is worth noting that the resulting enzyme is indeed a far more efficient catalyst than wild-type subtilisin for the polymerization of amino acids. This evolved enzyme can catalyse, for example, the formation of poly-L-methionine starting from a racemic mixture of methionine methyl ester. The evolved enzyme allows the synthesis of significantly longer polymers and at much higher yields than the native enzyme in 60-70% DMF (Zhao, H. unpublished resuits).</p><p>The advantage of directed evolution over site-directed mutagenesis is clear: the same amount of effort could support the construction and screening of at most a few dozen variants with mutations directed to specific locations. Without a clear mechanism, it would be difficult indeed to pinpoint 12 amino acid substitutions that enhance cataytic activity in DMF. Even then, single site-directed mutations would have to be accumulated to create a useful enzyme, itself a substantial mutagenesis effort involving trial and error to find optimal combinations.</p><p>The most attractive feature of the evolutionary strategy outlined in Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref> is its simplicity. It is possible, however, that this simple 'up-hill climb' approach is not an optimal approach to the evolution of a particular enzyme. There are obviously a great number of pathways possible for the evolution of a protein, and each choice of parent for the next generation represents an irreversible step along one particular pathway. What would happen if we simply repeated the experiment? Depending on which pathway was chosen or which mutation happened to be found first, the enzyme could end up on a local optimum, unable to evolve further. This approach may also appear slow: improvements are small in each step and necessarily become harder to find the closer the enzyme gets to an optimum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SEX IN THE TEST TUBE</head><p>An alternative directed evolution strategy we have recently explored incorporates some important advantages attributed to sex in the evolutionary process. Gene recombination, the cutting and pasting of whole genes or pieces of genes, can significantly increase the speed of molecular evolution by rapidly accumulating beneficial mutations and providing a mechanism to remove deleterious ones. To incorporate recombination into directed evolution, we randomly recombine genes with positive mutations. A search for better combinations of mutations completes a generation of directed evolution.</p><p>We have tested this new 'sexual' approach by creating an enzyme that efficiently catalyses the hydrolysis of the p-nitrobenzyl (pNB) ester of a fl-lactam antibiotic in the presence of DMF. The pNB protecting group is often used during the large-scale synthesis of cephalosporin-type antibiotics. Its selective removal presents problems, however, particularly for recovery and disposal of the zinc catalyst and the large amounts of organic solvents used. Therefore, a major pharmaceutical company devoted significant effort some years ago to finding an enzyme that would perform this selective hydrolysis reaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Brannon et al., 1976;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Zock et al., 1994</ref>). An enzyme with some activity towards pNB ester hydrolysis was identified by screening a large number of microorganisms, but the enzyme's low activity, especially in the solvents required to solubilize these materials, made it a poor competitor to the classical chemical catalyst.</p><p>We were challenged in 1994 to evolve a pNB esterase with much higher activity, particularly in the presence of the polar organic solvents required to achieve high substrate solubility. We had two reasons to believe that this could be done. First, the enzyme's natural function and, therefore, natural substrates are unknown, but they are unlikely to be the antibiotic pNB esters. Second, the natural enzyme's activity is very sensitive to organic solvents. Because these features were never required in the enzyme's natural setting, we could expect considerable improvement through directed evolution.</p><p>The wild-type esterase is not secreted by the E. coli cells in which it is made, nor does it carry out a reaction that is easily measured. Thus, we had to develop screening strategies more sophisticated than those used for the subtilisin. The p-nitrobenzyl ester hydrolysis reaction is assayed laboriously by high performance liquid chromatography, a method unsuitable for screening tens of thousands of colonies. We therefore devised a rapid screening assay using a similar, but not identical, p-nitrophenyl ester substrate, in order to have an easy-to-read colorimetric signal. The screening reactions could then be carried out in the 96 wells of a plastic microtiter plate, using an automatic spectrophotometer to read and analyse the absorbance in all 96 wells at once.</p><p>Using this rapid assay to screen about a thousand colonies per generation, we completed several sequen-biocatalysts for the future 5099 tial cycles of random PCR mutagenesis and screening, as illustrated in Fig. 7 <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Moore and Arnold, 1996)</ref>. After four generations, the enzyme's specific activity in 15% DMF had improved 15-fold. In the fourth generation, we collected not one, but 64 different clones, some of which were better than the parent, and many of which were not. The purpose for this was two-fold. First we wanted to make sure that our screening strategy was working properly to give us an enzyme that would catalyse the desired p-nitrobenzyl hydrolysis reaction, not only the colorimetric p-nitrophenyl screening reaction. The activities of each of the 64 clones in both reactions are compared in Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>. 3.0 e-2,5 ._~ ~t~ 1.5 ~ 1.0 @ 0.5 O.C //f/~ ~ ,:p-DO ,/," o° 0.0 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0 2.5 3.0 Rate of hydrolysis of screening substrate (relative to 3rd generation-parent) Fig. 8. Comparison of activities on target (p-nitrobenzyl)</p><p>and screening (p-nitrophenyl) substrate of 64 pNB esterase variants isolated after fourth generation of random mutagenesis and screening, relative to parent enzyme from the third generation. The five most active variants (inside oval) were pooled for random recombination (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">9</ref>).</p><p>If the screening reaction perfectly mimicked the desired reaction, all the points would lie on the 45 ° line. Although somewhat scattered, there is none the less a reasonable correlation: the rapid screen provides an indication of evolution of the desired activity that is acceptable for making a rough cut of positive clones.</p><p>The second reason for studying this group of variants was to test the alternate, sexual approach for accumulating effective mutations. We thus collected the five best mutants, those in the dotted oval in Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>, and recombined them using a 'sexual' PCR method recently described by <ref type="bibr">Stemmer (1994a, b)</ref>. How the genes are randomly recombined is shown schematically in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">9</ref>(a). The genes are pooled in the test tube and fragmented with an enzyme that cuts the DNA at random positions. In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">9</ref>(b), the polyacrylamide electrophoresis gel that separates the DNA fragments by length shows that the DNA has been digested into a smear of different-sized pieces. We collected the fragments 200-300 base pairs in length by extracting the DNA from the appropriate piece of gel. The full-length gene can be reassembled from this pool of random fragments, again using the PCR technology, to create a new gene library in which the mutations were present in their different possible combinations. These reassembled, recombined genes were inserted back into the plasmid and expressed in the E. coll. The best of those recombined genes were identified, as before, by screening the enzymes they code for and produce in the microorganisms.</p><p>Screening only ~400 colonies yielded eight clones with activity significantly greater than the best of the five parents--this yield of positives is at least 20-fold higher than we found by screening the genes with point mutations alone (typically 1/1500). Recombination can enhance directed evolution by making use of the information present in a population of improved enzymes produced by mutagenesis and screening, information that would otherwise be discarded. Thus far, we have improved the enzyme's specific activity towards the antibiotic substrate more than 30-fold in 15% DMF. The total expressed activity is at least 50-fold greater than the original system we started with.</p><p>Sequencing of the genes coding for improved enzymes once again allowed us to identify the amino acid substitutions responsible for the observed improvements in catalytic performance. Six effective mutations are illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure">10</ref>, on a model of the pNB esterase developed from the X-ray crystal structure of a homologous enzyme <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Moore and Arnold, 1996)</ref>. As for the case of subtilisin, most of the mutations are at or near the solvent-accessible surface. Only one of the six is deeply buried. In contrast to subtilisin, however, none of the effective amino acid substitutions lie in segments of the esterase predicted to interact directly with the bound substrate. It is possible that the homology modeling yielded an incorrect structure, and the mutations do interact with the p-nitrobenzyl substrate. Or, it may be that the amino acid substitutions sampled at positions adjac-F. H. ARNOLD ent to the substrate were all deleterious, and small improvements were only obtained by altering amino acids further away. In any case, the mechanism(s) by which these amino acid substitutions enhance the catalytic activity of the evolved pNB esterases are subtle and would have been very difficult to predict in advance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p>The directed evolution approach clearly allows us to engineer enzymes with novel functions and features. In contrast to 'rational' design approaches, directed evolution can be applied even when very little is known about an enzyme's structure or catalytic mechanism. Since the vast majority of proteins remain largely uncharacterized, this marks a huge advantage for the evolutionary methods. This approach, because it allows us to explore novel solutions to protein design problems, also promises to teach us a great deal about protein structure and function.</p><p>Future research in directed evolution will include development of large-scale screening methods, so that efficient searches of large mutant libraries can be performed. The construction of optimized mutant libraries will also decrease the need for screening. In addition to streamlining efforts to 'tune' enzymes, these improvements will allow larger leaps--such as the evolution of new catalytic activities--to take place. Significant improvements in the ease and power of directed evolution will also come from optimizing the search strategies. The many similarities to optimization problems in other fields make this a fertile ground for collaborative efforts among theoreticians and experimentalists from a wide range of engineering disciplines.  <ref type="bibr">(Stemmer, 1994a, b)</ref> involves random digestion of the gene pool using DNase enzyme, followed by gene reassembly using PCR. Reassembled genes contain the different combinations of mutations.</p><p>........ </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DNase digestion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PCR reassembly of full-length genes</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Structure is conserved during evolution, while amino acid sequences and specific functions are often not. (a) The ~//g barrel enzymes indicated appear to have evolved from a common ancestral ct//~ barrel protein. (b) Three GAPDH enzymes isolated from different organisms have very similar structures, but</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc>Fig.4. A working strategy for directed enzyme evolution. The screening method should ensure that small enhancements brought about mainly by single mutations can be measured. The evolution of a new, useful enzyme requires an effective strategy for accumulating many such small improvements.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>FFig 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig 5. Results of directed evolution of subtilisin for activity in DMF by sequential generations of random mutagenesis and screening. The accumulation of 12 amino acid substitutions in sequential generations of random mutagenesis and screening resulted in an enzyme &gt;500-fold more active than the wild-type enzyme in 60% DMF.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Fig. 7. Directed evolution of pNB esterase in 15% DMF involved four generations of random mutagenesis and screening, followed by one round of recombination of the five best genes from generation 4. The best variant obtained after four generations is 15-fold more active than wild-type. The best variant from screening 400 colonies of the recombination pool is ~30-fold more active than wild-type.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. Recombination of mutations by gene shuffling. (a) 'Sexual' PCR method(Stemmer, 1994a, b)  involves random digestion of the gene pool using DNase enzyme, followed by gene reassembly using PCR. Reassembled genes contain the different combinations of mutations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9. (b) Top polyacrylamide electrophoresis gel shows the separation of the digested gene fragments by size. Fragments 200-300 base pairs long were recovered by extracting the excised gel segment. These were reassembled into the full-length gene (bottom gel, lanes 3-5 and 6-8). First lane on left is a 'ladder' of DNA of known molecular weights.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The molecular evolution 'number problem'</figDesc><table><row><cell>No. of amino acid</cell><cell>No. of possible variants</cell></row><row><cell>changes</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>5700</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>16,190,850</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>30,557,530,900</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>43,109,036,717,100</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>48,489,044,499,400,000</cell></row></table><note><p>Note: Starting with an enzyme of 300 amino acids, the number of sequences containing M amino acid substitutions is (19</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgements--I am grateful to all the students and postdoctoral researchers who have contributed to this effort, especially <rs type="person">Jeffrey Moore</rs>, <rs type="person">Kevin Chen</rs> and <rs type="person">Huimin Zhao</rs>. This work was supported by the <rs type="funder">U.S. Office of Naval Research</rs> and the <rs type="funder">U.S. Department of Energy's program in Biological and Chemical Technologies Research within the Office of Industrial Technologies, Energy Efficiency and Renewables</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-dimensional structure of D-glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Buehner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Moras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Olsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Rossmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="1974">1974</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Buehner, M., Ford, G. C., Moras, D., Olsen, K. W. and Rossmann, M. G., 1974, Three-dimensional structure of D-glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase. J. Mol. Biol. 90, 25-49.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deesterification of cephalosporin para-nitrobenzyl esters by microbial enzymes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Brannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Fukuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Antibiotics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Brannon, D. R., Mabe, J. A. and Fukuda, D. S., 1976, De- esterification of cephalosporin para-nitrobenzyl esters by microbial enzymes. J. Antibiotics 29, 121-124.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tuning the activity of an enzyme for unusual environments: sequential random mutagenesis of subtilisin E for catalysis in dimethylformamide</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5618" to="5622" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chen, K. and Arnold, F. H., 1993, Tuning the activity of an enzyme for unusual environments: sequential random mutagenesis of subtilisin E for catalysis in dimethyl- formamide. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 90, 5618-5622.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enzyme engineering for nonaqueous solvents: random mutagenesis to enhance activity of subtilisin E in polar organic media</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechnology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1073" to="1077" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Chen, K. and Arnold, F. H., 1991, Enzyme engineering for nonaqueous solvents: random mutagenesis to enhance activity of subtilisin E in polar organic media. Biotechno- logy 9, 1073-1077.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Complex between the subtilisin from a mesophilic bacterium and the leech inhibitor eglin-C</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Dauter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Betzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Genov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Pipon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Crystallogr. !</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="707" to="730" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Dauter, Z., Betzel, C., Genov, N., Pipon, N. and Wilson, K. S., 1991, Complex between the subtilisin from a mesophilic bacterium and the leech inhibitor eglin-C. Acta Crystallogr. !147, 707-730.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The crystal structure of hologlyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase from the hyp~rthermophilic bacterium Thermotoga maritima at 2.5 A resolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Korndoerfer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Steipe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tomschy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jaenicke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">246</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="521" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Korndoerfer, I., Steipe, B., Huber, R., Tomschy, A. and Jaenicke, R., 1995, The crystal structure of holo- glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase from the hyp~rthermophilic bacterium Thermotoga maritima at 2.5 A resolution. J. Mol. Biol. 246, 511-521.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Directed evolution of a p-nitrobenzyl esterase for aqueous-organic solvents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="458" to="467" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Moore, J. and Arnold, F. H., 1996, Directed evolution of a p-nitrobenzyl esterase for aqueous-organic solvents. Nature Biotechnol. 14, 458-467.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Protein motifs 4. The structure and evolution ofct/fl barrel proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Reardon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Farber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="497" to="503" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">FASEB d</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Reardon, D. and Farber, G. K., 1995, Protein motifs 4. The structure and evolution ofct/fl barrel proteins. FASEB d. 9, 497-503.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolution in action</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Scanlan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Reid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Scanlan, T. S. and Reid, R. C., 1995, Evolution in action. Chem. Biol. 2, 71-75.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure of holo-glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate .behydrogenase from Bacillus stearothermophilus at 1.8 A resolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Skarzynski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C E</forename><surname>Moody</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wonacott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">987</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="187" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Skarzynski, T., Moody, P. C. E. and Wonacott, A. J., t987, Structure of holo-glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate .behydro- genase from Bacillus stearothermophilus at 1.8 A resolu- tion. J. Mol. Biol. 193, 171-187.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">1994a, DNA shuffling by random mutagenesis and reassembly: in vitro recombination for molecular evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P C</forename><surname>Stemmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">751</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Stemmer, W. P. C., 1994a, DNA shuffling by random mutagenesis and reassembly: in vitro recombination for molecular evolution. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 91, 10,747-10,751.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid evolution of a protein in vitro by DNA shuffling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P C</forename><surname>Stemmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3411</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="391" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Stemmer, W. P. C., 1994b, Rapid evolution of a protein in vitro by DNA shuffling. Nature 3411, 389-391.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Directed evolution of subtilisin E in Bacillus subtilis to enhance total activity in aqueous dimethylformamide</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>You</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Protein Engng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">You, L. and Arnold, F. H., 1996, Directed evolution of subtilisin E in Bacillus subtilis to enhance total activity in aqueous dimethylformamide. Protein Engng 9, 77-83.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Bacillus subtilis pnbA gene encoding pnitrobenzyl esterase: cloning, sequence and high-level expression in E. coli</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cantwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Swartling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hodges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Pohl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rosteck</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mcgilvray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Queener</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">151</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Zock, J., Cantwell, C., Swartling, J., Hodges, R., Pohl, T., Sutton, K., Rosteck, P. Jr., McGilvray, D. and Queener, S., 1994, The Bacillus subtilis pnbA gene encoding p- nitrobenzyl esterase: cloning, sequence and high-level ex- pression in E. coli. Gene 151, 37-43.</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
