<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Biocatalytic Process for (-)-Ambrox Production Using Squalene Hopene Cyclase</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Eric</forename><surname>Eichhorn</surname></persName>
							<email>eric.eichhorn@givaudan.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Givaudan Schweiz AG</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ueberlandstrasse 138</addrLine>
									<postCode>8600</postCode>
									<settlement>Dübendorf</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Esther</forename><surname>Locher</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Givaudan Schweiz AG</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ueberlandstrasse 138</addrLine>
									<postCode>8600</postCode>
									<settlement>Dübendorf</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sabrina</forename><surname>Guillemer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Protéus SA</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>70, allée Graham Bell Parc Georges Besse</addrLine>
									<postCode>30035 Cedex 1</postCode>
									<settlement>Nîmes</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">PCAS</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>2-8 rue de Rouen</addrLine>
									<postCode>78440</postCode>
									<settlement>Porcheville</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Denis</forename><surname>Wahler</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Protéus SA</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>70, allée Graham Bell Parc Georges Besse</addrLine>
									<postCode>30035 Cedex 1</postCode>
									<settlement>Nîmes</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Givaudan France SAS</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>3 rue des Satellites</addrLine>
									<postCode>31400</postCode>
									<settlement>Toulouse</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurent</forename><surname>Fourage</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Protéus SA</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>70, allée Graham Bell Parc Georges Besse</addrLine>
									<postCode>30035 Cedex 1</postCode>
									<settlement>Nîmes</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Total RC Stratégie Développement Recherche</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Boris</forename><surname>Schilling</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Givaudan Schweiz AG</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ueberlandstrasse 138</addrLine>
									<postCode>8600</postCode>
									<settlement>Dübendorf</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Place Jean Millier</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>92078</postCode>
									<settlement>Paris La Défense</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Biocatalytic Process for (-)-Ambrox Production Using Squalene Hopene Cyclase</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">46BF2B1CCE6293142374C2C8BF3B049C</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1002/adsc.201</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: ((will be filled in by the editorial staff</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-25T22:00+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[0], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>(-)-Ambrox</term>
					<term>Biocatalysis</term>
					<term>Fragrances</term>
					<term>Protein engineering</term>
					<term>Isomerases</term>
					<term>Squalene Hopene Cyclase</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Alicyclobacillus acidocaldarius Squalene Hopene</head><p>Cyclase was evolved to a biocatalyst suitable for (-)-Ambrox production at industrial scale. One round of random mutagenesis led to the identification of three variants with (E,E)-homofarnesol conversion properties improved about 1.5-to 10-fold over that of the wild type enzyme. Eight distinct amino acid mutations were identified overall; only one mutation was at the active site of the enzyme. Each of the three variants contained only two or three mutations over the 631 amino acids of the Alicyclobacillus acidocaldarius Squalene Hopene Cyclase polypeptide chain. Mutations responsible for improved (E,E)-homofarnesol conversion were identified. Investigations on reaction conditions led to the selection of one variant, with which reaction parameters were optimized towards process-relevant conditions.</p><p>A whole cell biotransformation process is presented in which Escherichia coli cells producing an improved Squalene Hopene Cyclase variant allows the conversion of 125 g/L (E,E)-homofarnesol in ≤ 72 hours. The developed process for the production of the fragrance ingredient (-)-Ambrox as Ambrofix ® expands the biocatalysis toolbox by setting out a general basis for biocatalytic Squalene Hopene Cyclase cyclization reactions at industrial scale.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.0" lry="842.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="5" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="6" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="7" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="8" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="9" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="10" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="11" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="12" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="13" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
		<surface n="14" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="595.32" lry="841.92"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Ambergris prized for centuries for its qualities and use in fine perfumes or for medicinal purposes, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> is an excretion of the sperm whale Physeter macrocephalus. It is thought to be produced in response to irritation of its intestine caused by beak-like mouthparts, eye lenses and pen of squid, the major part of its diet. Living and feeding in the ocean's depths, the sperm whale's life remains a mystery as is the development of ambergris' odor properties. Having a nauseating odor when it is expelled, as it ages under the action of sea water and air, ambergris develops a characteristic pleasant complex odor profile. This is the result of the oxidative degradation of (-)-ambrein (6) (Scheme 1), the most abundant but odorless component of ambergris. The smell of ambergris is described as well balanced with soft musky, animalic, marine, sweet, earthy, and woody facets. When having the privilege to smell an authentic ambergris alcoholic tincture, one's eyes close and one gets transported on an old wooden raft floating on an open sea, being caressed by a salty breeze. Used in trace amounts in perfumes, it serves like musks as a fixative and for exhaling a perfume's most delicate fragrant notes. Ambergris, a rare and extremely valuable material was at certain times worth more than gold. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> (-)-Ambrox (1) (Scheme 1), the olfactory most important component of ambergris, is recognized as the prototype of all ambergris odorants. It shows a characteristic and memorable ambery and woody smell, historically linked to ambergris, and reminiscent of tobacco and clary sage. The odour of (-)-Ambrox is most often described as triggering a soft, powdery, and almost mineral smoothness wrapping oneself in a pleasant feeling. Its first semisynthesis starting from the diterpene sclareol (7)  (Scheme 1) was reported in 1950; <ref type="bibr">[3]</ref> this major industrial resource for (-)-Ambrox production is currently isolated from clary sage (Salvia sclarea). A biosynthetic route to sclareol was however recently described. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref> Several synthetic and biocatalytic routes to (-)-Ambrox and (±)-Ambrox starting from a variety of other compounds including (E,E)-homofarnesol (EEH) (5) (Scheme 1) have been reviewed. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref> Scheme 1. (-)-Ambrox and compounds for (-)-Ambrox synthesis.</p><p>The yearly use of (-)-Ambrox as one of the most valuable perfumery ingredients is estimated at above 100 tons. It benefits from good ecotoxicological properties, and is biodegradable. It is used in all types of applications ranging from fabric and personal care to fine fragrances. One of its advantages over its low odor threshold and good substantivity is its softness compared to other pungent ambery notes like e.g. Ambermax ® or Amberketal. (-)-Ambrox appears currently in about 30 % of perfume creations at a mean dosage of 0.35 %, but reaching towards 1 % sometimes in fine fragrance applications. Its use appears to be in constant progression. (-)-Ambrox is available from several manufacturers e.g. as Ambrox ® or Ambroxan ® <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref> and is produced by Givaudan SA as Ambrofix <ref type="bibr">®</ref> .</p><p>In 1986 it was reported for the first time that (-)-Ambrox was the product of the enzymatic cyclization of EEH by a Squalene Hopene Cyclase <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref> (SHC, EC 5.4.99.17, Swissprot P33247, PDB 1SQC), a member of the triterpene cyclase family class II <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref> isolated from Alicyclobacillus acidocaldarius. Only a few examples of EEH cyclization to (-)-Ambrox by SHC enzymes have been reported; <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr">9]</ref> the ability of these enzymes to produce (-)-Ambrox has attracted the attention of industry. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[10]</ref> The first characterization of the enzyme reported a 3 % conversion at a substrate concentration of approx. 0.24 g/L using a mixture of the four possible homofarnesol diastereomers. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref> A method for producing (-)-Ambrox from a mixture of (E,E)-, (E,Z)-, (Z,E)-, and (Z,Z)-homofarnesol isomers with approx. 60 % conversion but at only 2 g/L substrate was also described <ref type="bibr">[10a]</ref> where it was stated that (-)-Ambrox and 9-epi-Ambrox (4) (Scheme 2) were detected as products, and that (-)-Ambrox was produced from the EEH isomer. Whilst SHC enzymes from Zymomonas mobilis and Bradyrhizobium japonicum were described as allowing approx. 40 and 22 % conversion respectively at approx. 2.4 g/L of substrate, compared to only 1.2 % conversion with A. acidocaldarius SHC, the homofarnesol isomer necessary for the production of (-)-Ambrox was not used for cyclization. <ref type="bibr">[10b,c]</ref> When homofarnesol was used as a substrate and as reported so far, the concentration ranges used and the conversions achieved were very low. To our knowledge no reports are available showing either a naturally high activity of SHC towards EEH, or on activity improvement studies towards this substrate. SHC enzymes catalyze the most remarkable step in steroid and triterpenoid synthesis. They have attracted the attention of chemists and biochemists for several decades because unlike other terpene cyclases they do not require a phosphorylated precursor, but proceed via a Brønsted acid catalysis-driven mechanism. <ref type="bibr">[11]</ref> A. acidocaldarius SHC has served as a model for detailed mechanistic studies. Structure determination <ref type="bibr">[12]</ref> and mutagenesis studies <ref type="bibr">[13]</ref> not only elucidated the mechanism of C-C, C-N, and C-O bond formation by these enzymes, but also showed their plasticity and ability to be evolved to promiscuous biocatalysts that could serve as a tool in chemical synthesis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[14]</ref> We evolved A. acidocaldarius SHC for (-)-Ambrox production under processrelevant conditions using a substrate consisting of a mixture of only two isomers: (E,E)-homofarnesol (5)  and (E,Z)-homofarnesol (EZH) (6) (Scheme 2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results and Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Evolution of Squalene Hopene Cyclase</head><p>EvoSight TM , a proprietary method of Protéus SA was applied to create SHC variants. It determines both the optimal number of random mutations to be introduced for obtaining an enzyme library with high proportion of improved variants and the minimum number of variants to screen to ensure that all possible independent variants are screened. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[15]</ref> Libraries were created with increasing mutational load; about 100 clones of each library were assayed for EEH conversion to (-)-Ambrox. The average number of mutations per gene in the 7 libraries was 1.9, 4.5, 5.5, 8.1, 9.2, 13.6, and 17.6. The processing of the relationship between the fraction of active variants and the number of mutations indicated that the optimally mutated library was a library of variants with 4 mutations. Consequently the corresponding library of 10 350 variants was screened. 90 hits were selected from microtiter plate assays for validation at milliliter scale. Three improved variants (101A10, 111C8, and 215G2) were identified showing a 1.6-to 3.5-fold better EEH conversion at 24 h of reaction. Their initial rate of (-)-Ambrox production was improved by a factor of 4.6 to 19. The sequencing of the corresponding shc genes indicated a total of 8 distinct amino acid mutations (</p><p>Table 1).</p><p>Table 1. Amino acid mutations in Squalene Hopene Cyclase variants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SHC variant</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Amino acid mutation</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">T77A I92V F129L M132R A224V I432T Q579H F601Y 101A10 x x 111C8 x x x 215G2 x x x 3 x 10 x 26 x x 30 x x 31 x x x 32 x x x 33 x x x x</formula><p>Surprisingly only one of the mutations was located at the active site (F601Y). The other mutations identified in the three improved variants were all but one (Q579H) located in domain 2 of the SHC crystal structure. <ref type="bibr">[12]</ref> Further mutations identified during screening, but not leading to any activity improvement were spread equally over the two domains of the enzyme (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>). In blue, green, and red are the positions mutated in 101A10, 111C8, and 215G2, respectively. The highlighted side chains indicate the positions where the mutations have been identified as beneficial: F601Y, F129L, M132R, and I432T. Other positions with mutations but showing no improvement on activity are in black. In yellow is the cocrystallized substrate analogue lauryl dimethylamine-Noxide. <ref type="bibr">[12]</ref> (prepared using PyMOL, The PyMOL Molecular Graphics System, version 2.0, Schrödinger, LLC).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mutations study</head><p>28 variants were constructed in total based on the mutations present in the 3 parent variants (as single mutations or in combinations) for identifying mutations responsible for activity improvement, and for evaluating the possibility of further activity improvement when combining beneficial mutations. Combination of beneficial mutations (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>) did not improve further EEH cyclization to (-)-Ambrox. Activity assay under validation reaction conditions (55 °C, pH 6.0, 0.05 % (w/v) SDS (Sodium Dodecyl Sulfate)) allowed for the selection of 7 new variants (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>) showing improved initial rates over wild type SHC (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">2A</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Characterization and ranking of SHC variants</head><p>The EEH conversion profiles obtained under validation assay conditions (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">2A</ref>) strongly suggested that setting the reaction parameters to optimum individually for each SHC variant would allow for a first step in activity improvement. Providing optimal reaction conditions to each of the wild type and variant enzymes was a prerequisite for the selection of the best available SHC variant. EEH conversion at 4 g/L was investigated at constant cell concentration (OD650nm of 10, approx. 12.2 g/L wet weight of cells) with wild type and 10 variant SHC enzymes (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>) at various pH, temperature, and [SDS] conditions. Studied ranges and resulting optimal reaction conditions are detailed in Table <ref type="table">S1</ref> (Supporting information). Significant variations in optimal values for the 3 parameters were noted among the variants. Wild type SHC tolerated broad variations while the variants showed rather a distinct optimum for the 3 parameters. All variants showed in particular a temperature optimum between 13 to 23 °C lower than that of wild type SHC. This observation confirmed the hypothesis that the reaction profiles</p><p>10.1002/adsc.201800132 Accepted Manuscript Advanced Synthesis &amp; Catalysis This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>obtained under validation assay conditions (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">2A</ref>) were due to a pronounced sensitivity of the SHC variants towards reaction conditions, and towards temperature in particular. The high temperature (55 °C) led to enzyme inactivation, and, due to its high volatility, promoted (-)-Ambrox evaporation. This explained the apparent decrease in conversion observed with some of the variants. This was in contrast not observed with wild type SHC, which retains its activity at 55 °C: enzyme activity compensated then for (-)-Ambrox evaporation.</p><p>The 10 SHC variants were finally ranked with regard to their performance in EEH cyclization to (-)-Ambrox using E. coli cells that had been grown and induced under strictly the same conditions. (E,E)-homofarnesol cyclization was tested in the standard activity test applying the reaction conditions defined as optimal for each of the variant and wild type enzymes (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">2B</ref>). The SHC content of the cells was analyzed by SDS-PAGE using a sample of the reactions. A very consistent amount of SHC in the E. coli cells producing the wild type and variant SHC enzymes was observed (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>). It was concluded that the differences in activity observed were not biased by strong variations in SHC production levels. The individual optimization of reaction conditions by itself resulted in a ~10-fold activity improvement with variant 215G2 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">2B</ref>).</p><p>The chemical purity of the homofarnesol stock influenced the velocity of EEH conversion. Depending both on the homofarnesol stock used and the reaction time applied, conversion increased overall and reached completion with variant 215G2.</p><p>Variant 215G2 was selected as best variant and chosen for developing process-relevant reaction conditions for (-)-Ambrox production. This variant was the result of a single round of evolution; the introduction of only very few mutations (0.3 % of amino acid chain length) was responsible for activity improvement, and very surprisingly the mutations were not located in the active site of the enzyme. A. acidocaldarius SHC accommodates rather large compounds as substrates and shows decreasing activity with substrates decreasing in size. It is still able to cyclize homogeraniol (C11) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref> but does not cyclize geraniol (C10). <ref type="bibr">[11a]</ref> A Zymomonas mobilis SHC enzyme was recently characterized that accepts (S)-citronellal (C10) and EEH (C16) as substrates. <ref type="bibr">[9]</ref> It shows a preference for short-chain substrates and an improved activity towards EEH compared to the A. acidocaldarius enzyme: 23 % vs. 3.5 % conversion at approx. 2.4 g/L EEH in 5 h.</p><p>The enzyme evolution program we conducted changed dramatically the substrate scope of A. acidocaldarius SHC and created the ability for that enzyme to efficiently cyclize the short-chain substrate EEH. This is an additional example that the biocatalysis toolbox can be expanded not only by discovering new biocatalysts (strains or enzymes) but also by enzyme engineering to improve the performance of natural enzymes, which are often reported as not suited for most industrial processes. Recent reviews outlined the achievements obtained in various industrial applications when evolution approaches were considered to address enzyme stability, substrate specificity or activity. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[16]</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Biocatalyst production</head><p>Wild type and variant SHC enzymes were produced from plasmids where the shc gene was under the control of an IPTG-inducible promoter (T7 in pET-24a(+) and pET-28a(+), T5 in pJExpress441). The influence on the specific activity of the composition of the cultivation medium, of the isopropyl--D-1thiogalctopyranoside (IPTG) concentration, and of the temperature for induction of SHC production was investigated (Supporting information, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1</ref>).</p><p>E. coli strains producing the variants were grown and induced both in complex medium (LB-Lennox, Terrific broth (TB)), and in minimal media such as M9 or M63. <ref type="bibr">[17]</ref> The cultivation medium affected not only the growth profile but also the amount of SHC enzyme produced, and the specific activity of the resulting biocatalyst. The minimal medium used for biocatalyst production in fermenters was the best medium for biocatalyst production also at small scale.</p><p>IPTG for induction was applied in the range of 25 M to 1 mM at temperatures between 23 and 46 °C. SHC production increased with increasing IPTG concentration and increasing temperature. The optimal IPTG concentration was at 300-1000 M; the optimal induction temperature was 37-40 °C. The relatively high temperature optimum for induction of SHC production may be explained by the mesophilic origin of the parent microorganism A. acidocaldarius. Temperatures higher than 41 °C impaired growth and reduced the specific activity of the cells. The enzyme was equally well produced from T7 and T5 promoters, with or without N-terminal HisTag.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(E,E)-homofarnesol bioconversion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Role of the surfactant</head><p>To evaluate if solubilizing agents other than SDS could be used, various surfactants and detergents were tested for EEH cyclization with variant 215G2 (standard activity assay). These included the non-10.1002/adsc.201800132</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Accepted Manuscript</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Advanced Synthesis &amp; Catalysis</head><p>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>ionic surfactant Triton X-100 mostly used in SHC studies (Supporting information, Table <ref type="table">S2</ref>).</p><p>SDS was confirmed as the only surfactant allowing for EEH cyclization to (-)-Ambrox and it was found that Triton X-100 did not promote EEH cyclization. Triton X-100 and the other compounds tested (Table <ref type="table">S2</ref>) allowed for the conversion, which was obtained in a reaction in the absence of any solubilizing agent. No activity improvement was obtained when combining SDS with any of the other compounds.</p><p>In addition to the compounds listed in Table S2 some deep eutectic solvents and ionic liquids <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[18]</ref> were tested as well, but with no positive result. This confirmed that under the conditions applied, SDS and only SDS could be used for EEH cyclization.</p><p>The influence of SDS was investigated at 4 g/L EEH and constant cell concentration (OD650nm of 5.0, approx. 6.1 g/L wet weight of cells) at SDS concentrations from 0.010 to 0.070 % (w/v). It was recognized that maximal activity was obtained only when the SDS concentration was properly set. The importance of this parameter was investigated further and confirmed during the optimization of reaction conditions towards process-relevant conditions.</p><p>One of the commonly cited and prominent disadvantages of whole cell biocatalysts is limitation in mass transfer due to the membrane. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[19]</ref> The use of a whole cell biocatalyst in the present process together with SDS as an emulsifying agent facilitates EEH dissolution into the membrane of the cells and access to the non-polar channel connecting the active site to the membrane-immersed region of the enzyme. <ref type="bibr">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">20]</ref> The benefits, recent advances, and ways to overcome the limitations of whole cell biocatalysis were recently reviewed. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[19]</ref> Productivity metrics often suffer from low substrate load and product titer, reactions being either tested at low substrate concentration or in aqueous systems where many synthetic hydrophobic substrates show low solubility. In the present case the use of a whole cell system in combination with SDS as a surfactant adequately addresses these limitations: it allows a high conversion of the water-immiscible EEH at high concentration in an aqueous system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Optimization of bioconversion conditions</head><p>The screening for the identification of an SHC variant with improved EEH conversion properties was carried out at a low substrate concentration of only 4 g/L. Preliminary studies were run to evaluate the possibility of evolving the reaction conditions towards process-relevant conditions. They showed that the parameters "[EEH]", "[cells]", and "[SDS]" were interconnected, higher substrate concentrations requiring apparently higher [SDS] and [cells]. The sensitivity of the reaction towards changes in pH was recognized; acetic acid/sodium acetate buffers were most appropriate for running reactions in small volumes without requirement for pH regulation. A reaction with EEH and cells both at approx. 66 g/L suggested that the probability for full conversion of at least 50 g/L EEH was high. These parameters, including temperature and pH were studied through design of experiment to define a response surface. Because the operating ranges were originally not clearly defined, a Doehlert matrix was chosen for the possibilities it offers for an easy extension (adaptation of parameters, change of design space).</p><p>In a first set of experiments (DOE1) only the 3 parameters "[cells]", "[EEH]", and "[SDS]" in the range 40 -80 g/L, 40 -80 g/L, and 0.1 -0.5 % (w/v), respectively, were studied. Temperature and pH were fixed at their central points (35 °C and 5.0). The discontinuous performance of the reaction in the chosen operating range did not allow for modelling of the reaction. This was explained by a strong interaction between "[cells]" and "[SDS]". Maximal activity was obtained only when the ratio [SDS]:[cells] was properly set. When [SDS] was too low, the system underperformed, when it was too high, activity was impaired (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>). This result confirmed that the ratio between [cells] and [SDS] must be carefully set to ensure maximal activity. The analysis of DOE1 results indicated a strong effect of the concentration of the cells, whereas the effect of the EEH concentration was weaker. Consequently a new series of experiments (DOE2) was designed according to the Doehlert matrix by expanding the operating range, replacing the parameter "[SDS]" by "[SDS]:[cells]", and adding pH and temperature as new parameters. [cells], [SDS]:[cells], and [EEH] were in the range 40 -120 g/L, 0.018 -0.054, and 30 -90 g/L, pH at 4.8 -5.2 and temperature at 30 -40 °C. Data processing allowed calculation of a polynomial model, which correlated well with experimental data. This model was validated with experimental data belonging to the first set of DOE experiments.</p><p>Desirable features were defined for optimizing reaction conditions in the studied space towards process-relevant conditions. Minimal achievement and optimal target for EEH conversion, (-)-Ambrox titer, and biocatalyst productivity were set to find a compromise suited for industrialization purposes. Optimal conditions were chosen at 50 g/L EEH, 110 g/L cells, [SDS]:[cells] of 0.041, at pH 5.1 and 37 °C. Some experiments were implemented at this</p><p>10.1002/adsc.201800132 Accepted Manuscript Advanced Synthesis &amp; Catalysis This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.  A thorough analysis of the model allowed for a better understanding of the behaviour of the parameters and their interactions. Some rules were determined and extrapolation was done outside the operating range studied. Successive 2 3 factorial designs were run in order to increase the EEH load with the following approach: (i) target the proper relative amounts of cells and EEH, which were identified as the most impacting parameters, (ii) adjust optimal [SDS]: A last step of extrapolation outside of the design space was done in an additional set of experiments by drastically increasing [EEH] to 125 and 150 g/L at a ratio of cells to EEH of 2. Two [SDS]:[cells] ratios per concentration of cells were tested as well as two levels of pH (4.9 and 5.1); the temperature was slightly increased to 38 °C. The best performance was obtained at the lowest pH value and highest [SDS]:[cells], which still suggested the possibility for further optimization. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref> shows the performance achieved during the whole optimization procedure. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Confirmation and scale up of (E,E)-homofarnesol bioconversion conditions</head><p>Upscaling of the optimized reaction conditions was tested at 150 mL-scale in 0.1M acetic acid/sodium acetate buffer with 125 g/L EEH, 250 g/L cells, 1.55 % (w/v) SDS, at pH 4.9 and 35 °C. The biotransformation conditions resulted in high conversion at high substrate load (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref>). Crystalline (-)-Ambrox was produced, which is an advantage for product recovery.</p><p>EEH cyclization at 125 g/L substrate and 250 g/L cells was compared between best variant 215G2 and wild type SHC enzymes. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref> shows the time course of EEH cyclization and the improvement in activity as a result of engineering both enzyme and reaction conditions. The maximal productivity observed was about 10 g.L -1 .h -1 , with an approx. 10fold improvement for the variant vs. parent wild type enzyme. An 11-fold increase in specific activity (initial rate) and a 7-fold increase at full substrate conversion with the variant were achieved over the wild type enzyme. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Robustness of bioconversion conditions</head><p>For the setting of process-relevant EEH bioconversion conditions were used acetic acid/sodium acetate buffers in which the pH of the reaction was stable, and no pH regulation was required. The robustness of the developed bioconversion conditions at high concentrations of substrate and cells was characterized in terms of the requirement for a buffering medium, the pH of the reaction, the sensitivity towards reaction medium composition, and the concentration of SDS. Reactions were run at 125 g/L EEH with 250 g/L cells in either a buffer (0.1 M citric acid/sodium citrate, acetic acid/sodium acetate, succinic acid/NaOH) with pH ranging from 4.6 to 5.8, or at pH 5.4 in water (tap or deionized) or in NaCl solutions (0.5 -1.8 % (w/v)) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">8</ref>).</p><p>The medium/pH combination influenced EEH conversion (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">8A</ref>). The biotransformation did not depend on a buffering agent as it ran equally well</p><p>10.1002/adsc.201800132</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Accepted Manuscript</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Advanced Synthesis &amp; Catalysis</head><p>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>in various buffers at a pH value of as low as 4.6 (acetic acid buffer), or at pH 5.4 in tap or deionized water supplemented with or without NaCl (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">8B</ref>). The bioconversion tolerated NaCl concentrations of up to 1.8 % (w/v). When using a succinic acid/NaOH buffer at pH 5.4, the reaction ran equally well at 50, 75, and 100 mM succinic acid.</p><p>The biotransformation tolerated some variation in SDS concentration but the importance of carefully setting the [SDS]:[cells] ratio was confirmed. A too low SDS concentration does not enable maximal performance whereas a too high SDS concentration is detrimental to the bioconversion (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">8C</ref>).</p><p>As an alternative to harvesting cells and running EEH cyclization in a defined medium, the biotransformation was run as efficiently directly in the fermentation medium containing the required amount of biocatalyst (250 g/L wet weight of cells) by adjusting the pH to 5.4, and adding the required amount of SDS and of homofarnesol stock for 125 g/L EEH to start the reaction. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Volumetric productivity</head><p>To increase further the volumetric productivity, a 1.5fold concentrated bioconversion was run at 188 g/L EEH with 375 g/L cells. A control bioconversion was run at 125 g/L EEH, 250 g/L cells. 72 h after the start was EEH conversion 88 % in the 1.5-fold bioconversion vs. 95 % in the control. 96 h after the start was conversion 93 % in the 1.5-fold bioconversion vs. 97 % in the control reaction (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">9</ref>). The stirring in the 1.5-fold concentrated bioconversion became more difficult over time as the oily EEH was converted to crystalline (-)-Ambrox. Stirring efficiency appeared as the only limitation of the system. The physical property per se of the 1.5fold concentrated reaction may be responsible for the slightly lower conversion; a setup allowing for a better mixing would further improve EEH conversion in the concentrated reaction. The results clearly indicated the possibility of running bioconversions at 188 g/L EEH or higher provided efficient mixing is achieved. Volumetric productivity improvement was in the range of 18 -30 % (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).</p><p>Table 2. Volumetric productivity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reaction time (h)</head><p>Productivity (g.L -1 .h -1 )</p><p>125 g/L EEH <ref type="bibr">[a]</ref> 188 g/L EEH <ref type="bibr">[b]</ref> 1. 25  10.3 12.2 8.25 6.3 8.2 <ref type="bibr">[a]</ref> 250 g/L cells; <ref type="bibr">[b]</ref> 375 g/L cells.</p><p>The whole cell system we developed for (-)-Ambrox production as Ambrofix ® allows conversion of almost 200 g/L substrate in approx. 96h. It is well positioned among biocatalytic processes in terms of productivity. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">19]</ref> Cost contribution of the biocatalyst to the final process is an important milestone. Guidelines for suitable biocatalysts have been developed. Minimum productivities for feasibility in different types of processes and products have been suggested. <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[21]</ref> General rules for cost analysis have been established for biocatalyst production based on biocatalyst format (whole cells, soluble or immobilized enzyme),</p><p>10.1002/adsc.201800132 Accepted Manuscript Advanced Synthesis &amp; Catalysis This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p><p>product cost, market size and value, and the requirements for the implementation of biocatalytic processes have been carefully analyzed. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[22]</ref> The applicability of the biotransformation presented here was not limited by its high biocatalyst load.</p><p>Enzymes still are the exception rather than the rule in the synthesis of fine chemicals and pharmaceuticals; biocatalysis is often regarded as second generation process. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[23]</ref> Although it holds great promise as a powerful tool for application in process chemistry, the number of applications at commercial scale is still disproportionately low. Enzymes are not naturally evolved to work with substrates of interest or not adapted to process-relevant conditions, and are unable to meet the needs of synthetic industry. <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[21]</ref> By means of both enzyme and reaction engineering we developed a cost-effective process for the production of a fragrance ingredient.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(-)-Ambrox recovery</head><p>Crystalline (-)-Ambrox, which was present in the biotransformation at high EEH conversion was collected from the reaction broth by means of solvent extraction or filtration (solid/liquid separation).</p><p>Hexane, xylene, and toluene allowed efficient extraction of (-)-Ambrox in 3 successive extractions (0.5 vol. each). 85 % of (-)-Ambrox was recovered in the first extraction. Hexane performed slightly less well as after the third extraction the reaction broth still contained 2.3 % of total (-)-Ambrox vs. 0.6 % and 0.9 % when using toluene or xylene.</p><p>(-)-Ambrox was extracted from the solid phase of the reaction broth using toluene or water miscible ethanol. After 6 consecutive extractions with ½ vol. of the solid phase with toluene (1.35 vol. of the initial reaction broth volume), &gt; 99.5 % (-)-Ambrox was recovered. 99 % of (-)-Ambrox was recovered in 4 extractions (3.2 vol. of initial reaction broth) when ethanol was used.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reaction products</head><p>EEH was cyclized for the first time from a mixture of the two isomers (E,E)-homofarnesol ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) and (E,Z)-homofarnesol (6). Gas chromatography analysis of reaction mixtures identified four reaction products (Scheme 2). They were always observed when cyclizing a mixture of (E,E)-and (E,Z)-homofarnesol with either wild type or variant SHC enzymes. Conversion of neat (E,E)-or (E,Z)-homofarnesol allowed assigning the products to the corresponding substrate. NMR analysis elucidated their structure (details and NMR spectra in Supporting information).</p><p>For the first time it was shown that EEH ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) was cyclized to (-)-Ambrox (1) and 2 ((3aS,5aS,9aS,9bS)-3a,6,6,9a-tetramethyldodeca-hydronaphtho[2,1b]furan) in a ratio of approx. 97:3. 2 was not disclosed in the original work on enzymatic cyclization of EEH. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref> This highly constrained Ambrox stereoisomer was also postulated as unlikely to exist. <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[24]</ref> Cyclization of (E,Z)-homofarnesol ( <ref type="formula">6</ref>) produced 3 ((7aS,11aS,Z)-5,8,8,11a-tetramethyl-2,3,6,7,7a,8,9,-10,11,11adecahydrobenzo[b]oxonine), which we describe here for the first time, and (-)-9b-epi-Ambrox ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) ((3aR,5aS,9aS,9bS)-3a,6,6,9a-tetramethyldodecahydronaphtho[2,1-b]furan)) in a ratio of approx. 30:70. 1: 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl3) δ 3.94 -3.88 (m, 1H), 3.82 (q, J = 8.2 Hz, 1H), 1.94 (dt, J = 11.5, 3.0 Hz, 1H), 1.77 -1.66 (m, 4H), 1.49-1.37 (m, 5H), 1.35 -1.14 (m, 2H), 1.09 -0.95 (m, 2H), 1.09 (s, 3H), 0.88 (s, 3H), 0.84 (s, 3H), 0.83 (s, 3H). <ref type="bibr">13</ref> C NMR (100 MHz, CDCl3) δ 80.0, 65. 1, 60.3, 57.4, 42.6, 40.1, 39.9,  36.3, 33.7, 33.2, 22.8, 21.3, 21.3, 20.8, 18.5, 15.2.  2: 1 H NMR (600 MHz, C6D6) δ 3.83 -3.80 (m, 2H), 2.04 -2.01 (m, 1H), 1.78 -1.74 (m, 1H), 1.65 -1.60 (m, 2H) 1.52 -1.48 (m, 2H), 1.45 -1.36 (m, 5H), 1.22 (s, 3H), 1.20 -1.18 (m, 2H), 1.10 -1.05 (m, 1H), 0.90 (s, 3H), 0.82 (s, 3H), 0.82 (s, 3H). <ref type="bibr">13</ref> C NMR (150MHz, C6D6, 13 C-shifts extracted from the HSQCspectrum) δ 80.0, 65. 2, 55.8, 48.4, 41.9, 37.1, 34.6,  34.7, 34.0, 33.6, 25.4, 23.4, 22.6, 21.7, 20.1, 17.9.  3: 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl3) δ 5.53 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 1H), 3.48 (ddd, J = 11, 4.5, 1.5 Hz, 1H), 3.37 (t, J = 10.5 H, 1H), 3. 14 -3.06 (m, 1H), 2.34 -2.25 (m, 1H),  1.86 (ddd, J = 13.4, 8.8, 4.4 Hz, 1H), 1.77 (dt, J = 12.0, 4.0 Hz, 1H), 1.66 (s, 3H), 1.61 -1.54 (m, 3H),  1.50 -1.38 (m, 3H), 1.37 -1.24 (m, 2H), 1.24 (s, 3H), 1.14 (td, J = 13.0, 4.0 Hz, 1H), 0.92 (s, 3H), 0.83 (s, 3H). <ref type="bibr">13</ref> C NMR (100 MHz, CDCl3) δ 138.3, 124.4,  78.4, 62.1, 44.2, 42.3, 37.1, 34.6, 33.4, 31.7, 29.1,  24.2, 23.1, 22.8, 21.9, 20.2.  4: 1 H NMR (400, MHz CDCl3) δ 3.85 (td, J = 8.3, 3.2 Hz, 1H), 3.77 (q, J = 8.3 Hz, 1H), 2.04 (tt, J = 12.2, 9.1 Hz, 1H), 1.90 (dtd, J = 12, 8.1, 3.2 Hz, 1H), 1.67 -1.53 (m, 5H), 1.43 -1.37 (m, 2H), 1.37 (s, 3H), 1.29 -1.08 (m, 5H), 1.10 (s, 3H), 0.89 (s, 3H), 0.82 (s, 3H). <ref type="bibr">13</ref> C NMR (100 MHz, CDCl3) δ 80.9, 64. 1, 59.1,  46.8, 42.4, 38.8, 36.1, 35.9, 33.7, 33.0, 28.9, 27.8,  22.9, 21.9, 20.5, 18.6.  The NMR data of 1 and 4 are consistent with literature values. <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[25]</ref> EEH conversion profiles in reactions run at constant 4 g/L homofarnesol but with varying (E,E):(E,Z) ratio showed that (E,Z)-homofarnesol entered in competition with EEH for cyclization (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">10</ref>). At identical concentration (4 g/L) (E,Z)-homofarnesol cyclization was 3 to 3.5 times slower than that of EEH.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>SHC enzymes have attracted the interest of the scientific community decades ago but no reports are so far available on industrial processes based on these enzymes. The work presented here is the very first example of an SHC reaction that was brought to process-relevant and viable conditions by engineering both enzyme and reaction conditions. Ongoing studies indicate that this process can be scaled-up for the production of (-)-Ambrox as Ambrofix ® at industrial scale. Together with the evidence published over the past years that SHC enzymes are highly evolvable through enzyme engineering, we set out with the described process <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[26]</ref> a general basis for biocatalytic SHC cyclization reactions at industrial scale, and demonstrate that these enzymes are amenable to industrial scale biocatalysts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental Section</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chemicals</head><p>All reagents except homofarnesol <ref type="bibr">[27]</ref> were from commercial sources and used without additional purification. Homofarnesol used in this study was a mixture of (E,E)-and (E,Z)-homofarnesol in a ratio 80:20 or 90:10. Any reference to EEH in the various activity assays or bioconversions in this study is a reference to the final (E,E)-homofarnesol concentration in the reaction. Depending on the chemical purity and on the (E,E):(E,Z) ratio of the homofarnesol stock used, the total homofarnesol concentration (EEH + EZH) varied slightly between the reactions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Strains and plasmids</head><p>The wild type and variant SHC enzymes were produced in E. coli MC1061(DE3) <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[28]</ref> for library screening, otherwise in E. coli BL21(DE3) <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[29]</ref> with or without N-terminal HisTag. The shc gene (NdeI-HindIII insert) was under the control of a T7 promoter in plasmids pET-28a(+) or pET-24a(+) (Novagen). Alternatively the shc gene was under the control of a T5 promoter in pJExpress441 (ATUM).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis</head><p>SDS-PAGE was performed on a Mini-PROTEAN II system (Bio-Rad) with 10 % polyacrylamide gels under denaturing conditions. <ref type="bibr">[17a]</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Enzyme evolution</head><p>EvoSight TM <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[15]</ref> was applied to the A. acidocaldarius shc gene (Genbank accession number AB007002.1).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>High throughput production and screening of SHC variants, validation of selected hits, validation assay</head><p>The production of SHC variants was carried out in Luria-Bertani (LB) medium in 96-wells deep well plates. 1 mL cultures were incubated at 37 °C under constant agitation (orbital shaking, 180 rpm). Protein production was induced for 15 h by the addition of IPTG to 0.1 mM when the cultures had reached an OD600nm of 0.2.</p><p>SHC activity was assayed in microtiter plates with whole cells that had produced the variants (validation assay). The reactions contained cells to an OD600nm of 10 (approx. 10.3 g/L wet weight of cells), 0.05 % (w/v) SDS, and 4 g/L EEH in 0.1M citric acid/sodium citrate buffer pH 6.0. The reactions were incubated at 55 °C under constant agitation (200 rpm, orbital shaking) for 24 h. Formation of (-)-Ambrox at 24 h was quantified by sampling 100 L of reaction mixture, extraction with 200 L hexane:2-propanol (2:1), phase separation, and GC-FID analysis of the organic phase.</p><p>Hits selected from the screening step were cultivated in Erlenmeyer flasks (LB medium) and validated at 1 mL scale with whole cells to an OD600nm of 10, and under constant magnetic stirring (all other reaction conditions unchanged). Reactions were incubated for 24 h and sampled over time. Samples were solvent-extracted as above for GC-FID analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Production of variants, standard activity assay</head><p>SHC variants were produced in 300 or 350 mL LB or minimal medium cultures. A 15 mL seed culture (LB medium, 100 mL Erlenmeyer flask) supplemented with kanamycin (50 g/mL) was inoculated from an overnight preculture to an OD650nm of 0.050 and grown to an OD650nm of 0.50. A 350 mL main culture was then inoculated with 3.5 mL seed culture and grown to an OD650nm of approx. 0.50. Enzyme production was induced by the addition of IPTG at 300 M and lasted for 5 -6 h at 37 -40 °C and 280 rpm. Cells were collected by centrifugation (8280 g, 4 °C, 15 min) and stored as pellets at 4 °C or -20 °C until further use. Up to 4 -6 g wet weight of cells were obtained from total 1 liter of culture.</p><p>The standard activity assay (5 or 10 mL) was run in 0.1 M citric acid/sodium citrate or acetic acid/sodium acetate or succinic acid/NaOH buffer with 4 g/L EEH, and cells to an OD650nm of 10 (approx. 12.2 g/L wet weight of cells) under constant agitation (900 rpm) on a Heidolph Synthesis 1 Liquid 16 device. Optimal temperature, pH, and SDS concentration depended on the SHC enzyme considered (Supporting information, Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Biocatalyst production</head><p>Fermentations were run in 750 mL InforsHT reactors. To the fermentation vessel was added 168 mL of deionized water. The reaction vessel was equipped with probes (pO2, pH, antifoam, sampling device), carbon/nitrogen feed bottle (glucose solution: 35 g glucose + 143 mL deionized water) and sodium hydroxide bottle (10 % (w/v)), and sterilized by autoclaving. To the reactor was then added: 20 mL 10x phosphate/citric acid buffer (133 g/L KH2PO4, 40 g/L (NH4)2HPO4, 17 g/L citric acid.H2O with pH adjusted to 6.3), 14 mL 50 % (w/v) glucose in deionized water, 0.53 mL MgSO4 solution (50 % (w/v) MgSO4.7H2O in deionized water), 2 mL (NH4)2SO4 solution (50 % (w/v) (NH4)2SO4 in deionized water), 20 L trace elements solution (50 g/L Na2EDTA.2H2O, 20 g/L FeSO4.7H2O, 3 g/L H3BO3, 0.9 g/L MnSO4.2H2O, 1.1 g/L CoCl2, 80 g/L CuCl2, 240 g/L NiSO4.7H2O, 100 g/L KI, 1.4 g/L (NH4)6Mo7O24.4H2O, 1 g/L ZnSO4.7H2O), 400 L thiamine solution (2.25 g/L Thiamin.HCl), and 200 L kanamycin stock (50 g/L). The running parameters were: pH = 6.95, pO2 = 40 %, T = 30 °C, stirring at 300 rpm. Cascade: agitation set point at 300 rpm (min. 300, max. 1000), flow set point 0.1 L/min (min. 0, max. 0.6), antifoam control: 1:9.</p><p>The fermenter was inoculated from a seed culture (LB medium supplemented with 50 mg/L kanamycin, 37 °C, 220 rpm, 8 h) to an OD650nm of 0.4-0.5. The fermentation was run first in batch mode for approx. 11.5 h, where after was started the carbon/nitrogen feed. The feed consisted of a sterilized glucose solution to which had been added after sterilization: 17.5 mL (NH4)2SO4 solution, 1.8 mL MgSO4 solution, 18 L trace elements solution, 360 L thiamine solution, and 180 L kanamycin stock. The feed was run at a constant flow rate of approx. 4.2 mL/h. Glucose and NH4 + measurements were done externally to evaluate availability of the carbon and nitrogen sources in the culture using Quantofix ® Ammonium (Sigma Aldrich) and MQuant TM Glucose Test (Merck) according to the manufacturer's directions.</p><p>Cultures were grown for approx. 25 h reaching typically an OD650nm of 40 -45. SHC production was then started by adding IPTG to a concentration of 1 mM (as pulse or over a period of 3 -4 hours), setting the temperature to 40 °C and pO2 to 20 %. Induction of SHC production lasted for 16 h. At the induction end the OD650nm was 50 -70; cells were collected by centrifugation and stored as pellets at 4 °C or -20 °C until further use. Up to 30 -40 g wet weight of cells were collected from a total fermentation volume of approx. 440 mL corresponding to 70 -90 g/L of cells.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Optimization of (E,E)-homofarnesol bioconversion conditions</head><p>Most of the optimization steps were run through design of experiments using the NemrodW ® software (NemrodW SAS, France, <ref type="url" target="www.nemrodw.com">www.nemrodw.com</ref>). For response surface modelling, a Doehlert matrix was used. Otherwise 2 3 factorial designs were used to study parameter impacts and interactions.</p><p>Reactions (1.2 -7.2 mL volume) were run in tightly sealed glass vials (screw caps) in 0.1 M acetic acid/sodium acetate buffer (pH 4.8 -5.2). The biocatalyst load was between 40 and 300 g/L cells (wet weight), that of EEH varied between 30 and 150 g/L. SDS varied between 0.1 and 2.08 % (w/v). The reactions were incubated with constant mechanical agitation at temperatures between 30 and 40 °C.</p><p>A performance index summarizing the achievements towards all features defined as desirable (product titre, conversion, yield, and reaction time) was defined for monitoring the progress of the bioconversion optimization process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(E,E)-homofarnesol bioconversion</head><p>EEH bioconversions (150 mL volume) were run at 125 g/L EEH, 250 g/L cells (wet weight), 1.30 -1.55 % (w/v) SDS, 35 °C, with constant stirring (700 rpm) in 750 mL InforsHT reactors. Cells were suspended to homogeneity in reaction medium; cell concentration was determined by centrifuging an aliquot of cell suspension (17210 g, 10 min, 4 °C). Once the required amounts of cell suspension, homofarnesol stock (chemical purity, (E,E):(E,Z) ratio), and 31 % (w/v) SDS solution was determined, then the required volume of reaction medium was deduced. To the reactor was added: homofarnesol stock, SDS solution, reaction medium, and cell suspension.</p><p>Reactions were run either in 0.1 M citric acid/sodium citrate, 0.1 M acetic acid/sodium acetate or 0.1 M succinic acid/NaOH buffer pH 4.6 -5.8, or in 0.5, 0.9 -1.8 % (w/v) NaCl or water (tap or deionized) at pH 5.4. pH was carefully set to the desired value dropwise with 85 % H3PO4. pH in the reaction was monitored in situ and controlled at an external electrode. If required automatic pH regulation occurred with 10 % H3PO4 and 20 % NaOH.</p><p>Alternatively EEH bioconversions were run directly in the fermentation medium. Fermentations were carried out in 750 mL InforsHT reactors and the cell concentration (wet weight) determined as described above. The amounts of homofarnesol stock and SDS were then determined for setting the ratios [SDS]:[cells] and [cells]: [EEH] at the same values as in the standard EEH bioconversion (125 g/L EEH, 250 g/L cells, and 1.30 -1.55 % (w/v) SDS). SDS and EEH was added, the pH set to 5.4, and temperature to 35 °C. For running a true 125 g/L EEH bioconversion, the required amount of cells collected from several fermenters was added to one fermenter to a cell concentration of 250 g/L. The reaction was then started as above.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(-)-Ambrox recovery</head><p>The initial (-)-Ambrox content of the reaction broth was determined after extraction of 1 g material with methyl tert-butyl ether (MTBE) followed by GC-FID analysis.</p><p>Whole reaction broth extraction: 200 mL reaction broth (~125 g/L (-)-Ambrox) was extracted by vigorous shaking for 30 s with 100 -150 mL hexane, toluene, or xylene. The solvent phase was collected by centrifugation (4225 g, 10 min, 10 °C). The cells were resuspended in the aqueous phase; (-)-Ambrox was quantified by extracting 1 g suspension with MTBE and GC-FID analysis. Extraction was repeated until (-)-Ambrox in the solvent phase was ≤ 1.0 % of that of the initial (-)-Ambrox content of the reaction broth.</p><p>Solid phase extraction: 200 mL reaction broth (~125 g/L (-)-Ambrox) was centrifuged as above to separate 80 mL solid pellet from 120 mL liquid phase. The solid phase was extracted with 160 mL ethanol 99 % (vigorous shaking), and centrifugation (as above but at room temperature). The ethanolic phase was analyzed by GC-FID for its (-)-Ambrox content. The extraction was repeated until (-)-Ambrox in the solvent phase was ≤ 1.0 % of the initial (-)-Ambrox content of the reaction broth. As an alternative to absolute ethanol, the extractions were done with toluene.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sample preparation for GC-analysis</head><p>4 g/L EEH reactions: 100 -300 μL reaction was extracted with 200 μL hexane:2-propanol (2:1) or 700 μL MTBE. After centrifugation (Eppendorf centrifuge 5415C, 13000 rpm) the solvent phase was analyzed by GC-FID. Up to 16 g/L EEH: 150 -300 μL reaction mixture was extracted into 700 μL of MTBE. After phase separation, the solvent phase was analyzed by GC-FID. 30 -188 g/L EEH: 1 mL reaction mixture was extracted with 5 mL of MTBE by vigorous shaking. After decantation 1 mL of solvent phase was centrifuged; 100 μL of the supernatant was diluted into 900 μL MTBE for GC-FID analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gas chromatography analysis</head><p>High throughput library screening: 1 L of solvent phase was injected (split ratio 1/10) onto a 30 m x 0.32 mm x 0.25 m HP-5 column (Surveyor gas chromatograph, Thermo). The column was developed at constant pressure (85 kPa, 5.2 mL/min H2) and temperature (170 °C); detector temperature: 250 °C.</p><p>Standard assay and bioconversions: 1 L of solvent phase was injected (split ratio 1/10) onto a 30 m x 0.32 mm x 0.25 m Zebron ZB-5 column (Trace Focus gas chromatograph, Thermo). The column was developed at 4 mL/min H2 constant flow: 100 °C, 15 °C/min to 200 °C, 120 °C/min to 240 °C, 4 min at 240 °C; detector temperature: 300 °C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Structure elucidation of reaction products by NMR</head><p>1 H and 13 C NMR spectra were recorded on a BrukerAvance 400 MHz ( 1 H NMR) and 125 MHz spectrometer ( 13 C NMR) in CDCl3, if not mentioned otherwise. The chemical shifts are given in ppm relative to the TMS signal ( 0 ppm). 13 C spectra were referenced to CDCl3 ( 77.16 ppm) and C6D6 (δ 128.06 ppm).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Location of amino acid mutations in the Squalene Hopene Cyclase crystal structure (PDB 1SQC).In blue, green, and red are the positions mutated in 101A10, 111C8, and 215G2, respectively. The highlighted side chains indicate the positions where the mutations have been identified as beneficial: F601Y, F129L, M132R, and I432T. Other positions with mutations but showing no improvement on activity are in black. In yellow is the cocrystallized substrate analogue lauryl dimethylamine-Noxide.[12]  (prepared using PyMOL, The PyMOL Molecular Graphics System, version 2.0, Schrödinger, LLC).</figDesc><graphic coords="4,106.50,342.20,157.50,195.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2. Influence of reaction conditions on activity of variant and wild type Squalene Hopene Cyclases. 4 g/L (E,E)-homofarnesol was cyclized at pH 6.0 and 55 °C in presence of 0.05 % (w/v) SDS (A), or at individually optimized temperature, pH, and [SDS] (B).</figDesc><graphic coords="4,343.40,155.25,193.15,255.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3. SDS-PAGE analysis of the SHC content of E. coli cells producing wild type and variant SHC enzymes. Reaction samples were loaded equivalent to an OD650nm of cells of 2.0 (M: BioRAD broad range marker).</figDesc><graphic coords="5,98.55,531.90,169.05,88.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Figure 4. Performance index as a function of [SDS]:[cells].</figDesc><graphic coords="6,345.40,326.60,184.85,129.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><figDesc>optimum and their performance compared to the benchmark conditions 66 g/L cells, 65.7 g/L EEH, [SDS]:[cells] of 0.050, pH 5.2, 33 °C. The calculated model allowed for a very good prediction (Figure5).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Figure 5. Comparison of experimental (light grey) and calculated (dark grey) data. Reaction time: 18 h.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,76.90,112.25,214.10,117.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><figDesc>[cells], (iii) keep pH at 5.1 and temperature at 37 °C. A new optimum was identified at 180 g/L cells, 90 g/L EEH, [SDS]:[cells] of 0.048, pH 5.1, 37 °C. Analyzing the result of successive sets of experiments showed that best results were obtained at a ratio of cells to EEH of approximately 2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Figure 6. (-)-Ambrox titer (columns) and performance index (closed circles). 66 g/L EEH: benchmark, 50 g/L EEH: response surface optimum, 90 g/L EEH: intermediate optimum, 125 g/L EEH: final condition. Reaction time: 18 h.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,89.80,601.10,189.55,120.05" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Figure 7. (E,E)-homofarnesol cyclization with wild type and 215G2 SHC. Reactions were run at 125 g/L EEH and 250 g/L cells, at pH 5.4 and 35 °C with variant 215G2, and at pH 6.0 and 55 °C with wild type SHC.</figDesc><graphic coords="7,357.85,332.15,173.65,138.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Figure 8. Robustness of (E,E)-homofarnesol bioconversion conditions (125 g/L EEH, 250 g/L cells). Conversion at 72 h is indicated with reference to a reaction run at pH 5.4 in citric acid buffer (between 92 and 99 % EEH conversion). A: buffer and pH (Acet: acetic acid/sodium acetate, Citric: citric acid/sodium citrate, Succ: succinic acid/NaOH), B: reaction medium (pH 5.4), C: SDS concentration (pH 5.4).</figDesc><graphic coords="8,86.95,312.25,183.80,353.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Figure 9. Volumetric productivity.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,356.25,188.50,158.55,128.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Scheme 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Scheme 2. Homofarnesol cyclization from a mixture of isomers. (E,E):(E,Z) ratio: 90:10 or 80:20.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><figDesc>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Figure 10. Cyclization of homofarnesol. Reactions were run at constant 4 g/L homofarnesol (EEH + EZH) with (E,E):(E,Z) ratios between 100:0 and 0:100. Conversion refers to EEH except for the curve in dotted line (EZH conversion), where neat (E,Z)-homofarnesol was used.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,82.50,57.80,189.65,148.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><figDesc>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors thank <rs type="person">V. Zelenay</rs> for NMR structure elucidation of reaction products.</p></div>
			</div>
			<div type="funding">
<div><head>FULL PAPER</head><p>Biocatalytic Process for (-)-<rs type="institution">Ambrox Production Using Squalene Hopene Cyclase Journal. Year, Volume, Page -Page Eric Eichhorn</rs>, <rs type="person">* Esther Locher</rs>, <rs type="person">Sabrina Guillemer</rs>, <rs type="person">Denis Wahler</rs>, <rs type="person">Laurent Fourage</rs>, Boris Schilling 10.1002/adsc.201800132 Accepted Manuscript Advanced Synthesis &amp; Catalysis This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p></div>
			</div>			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Accepted Manuscript</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Advanced Synthesis &amp; Catalysis</head><p>This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Brito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jordão</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pierce</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mar. Biol. Assoc. U.K</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="585" to="596" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">C. Brito, V. C. Jordão, G. J. Pierce, J. Mar. Biol. Assoc. U.K. 2016, 96, 585-596.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kemp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Floating gold: a natural (and unnatural) history of Ambergris</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">C. Kemp in: Floating gold: a natural (and unnatural) history of Ambergris, University of Chicago Press, 2012.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stoll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hinder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Helv. Chim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1251" to="1260" />
			<date type="published" when="1950">1950</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Stoll, M. Hinder, Helv. Chim. Acta 1950, 33, 1251-1260;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stoll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hinder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Helv. Chim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1308" to="1312" />
			<date type="published" when="1950">1950</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Stoll, M. Hinder, Helv. Chim. Acta 1950, 33, 1308-1312.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schalk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pastore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mirata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Khim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schouwey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Deguerry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Pineda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Rocci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Daviet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18900" to="18903" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Schalk, L. Pastore, M. A. Mirata, S. Khim, M. Schouwey, F. Deguerry, V. Pineda, L. Rocci, L. Daviet, J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2012, 134, 18900-18903.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schäfer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. unserer Zeit</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="374" to="388" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">B. Schäfer, Chem. unserer Zeit 2011, 45, 374-388.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ambrox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Trademark of Firmenich SA; Ambroxan ® : Trademark of Kao Kabushiki Kaisha</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ambrox ® : Trademark of Firmenich SA; Ambroxan ® : Trademark of Kao Kabushiki Kaisha.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Neumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Chem. Hoppe-Seyler</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">367</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="723" to="729" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. Neumann, H. Simon, Biol. Chem. Hoppe-Seyler 1986, 367, 723-729.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Christianson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3412" to="3442" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">a) D. W. Christianson, Chem. Rev. 2006, 106, 3412- 3442;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Abe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Prod. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1311" to="1331" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">I. Abe, Nat. Prod. Rep. 2007, 24, 1311-1331;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Racolta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Juhl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sirim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pleiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteins</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2012. 2009-2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. Racolta, P. B. Juhl, D. Sirim, J. Pleiss, Proteins 2012, 80, 2009-2019.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Seitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Klebensberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Siebenhaller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Breuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Siedenburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Jendrossek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Catal. B Enzym</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Seitz, J. Klebensberger, S. Siebenhaller, M. Breuer, G. Siedenburg, D. Jendrossek, B. Hauer, J. Mol. Catal. B Enzym. 2012, 84, 72-77;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Seitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<pubPlace>Stuttgart</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Univ</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Dissertation</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Seitz, Dissertation, Univ. Stuttgart, 2013.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">)</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hayase</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Igarashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JP</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009. 2009060799</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">a) A. Hayase, K. Igarashi, 2009, JP2009060799;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Breuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hörster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010. 2010/139719</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Breuer, A. Hörster, B. Hauer, 2010, WO2010/139719;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Breuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hörster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>US0135477A1</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Breuer, A. Hörster, B. Hauer, 2012, US0135477A1;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Breuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Jendrossek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/adsc.201800132</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Breuer, B. Hauer, D. Jendrossek, 10.1002/adsc.201800132</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Siedenburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pleiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Demet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Racolta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012. 2012/066059</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">G. Siedenburg, J. Pleiss, S. Demet, S. Racolta, 2012, WO2012/066059.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hoshino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kumai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kudo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nakano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ohashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Org. Biomol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2650" to="2657" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">T. Hoshino, Y. Kumai, I. Kudo, S. Nakano, S. Ohashi, Org. Biomol. Chem. 2004, 2, 2650-2657;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Siedenburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Jendrossek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Environ. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3905" to="3915" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">G. Siedenburg, D. Jendrossek, Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2011, 77, 3905-3915;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Abe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rohmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Prestwitch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2189" to="2206" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">I. Abe, M. Rohmer, G. D. Prestwitch, Chem. Rev. 1993, 93, 2189-2206.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Wendt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Poralla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Schulz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">277</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1811" to="1815" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">K. U. Wendt, K. Poralla, G. E. Schulz, Science 1997, 277, 1811-1815;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Wendt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lenhart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Schulz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">286</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="187" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">K. U. Wendt, A. Lenhart, G. E. Schulz, J. Mol. Biol. 1999, 286, 175-187.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Pale-Grosdemange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Merkofer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rohmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Poralla</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tetrahedron Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6009" to="6012" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">C. Pale-Grosdemange, T. Merkofer, M. Rohmer, K. Poralla, Tetrahedron Lett. 1999, 40, 6009-6012;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hoshino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sato</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="291" to="301" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">T. Hoshino, T. Sato, Chem. Commun. 2002, 291-301.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P.-O</forename><surname>Syrén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Henche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Eichler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Nestl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">a) P.-O. Syrén, S. Henche, A. Eichler, B. Nestl, B. Hauer, Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol. 2016, 41, 73-82;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P.-O</forename><surname>Syrén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Seitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nestl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. C. Hammer, P.-O. Syrén, M. Seitz, B. M. Nestl, B. Hauer, Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol. 2013, 17, 293-300;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Marjanovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dominicus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nestl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="126" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. C. Hammer, A. Marjanovic, J. M. Dominicus, B. M. Nestl, B. Hauer, Nat. Chem. Biol. 2015, 11, 121-126.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chodorge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fourage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ullmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Duvivier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Masson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Lefèvre</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Synth. Catal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">347</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1022" to="1026" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">a) M. Chodorge, L. Fourage, C. Ullmann, V. Duvivier, J.-M. Masson, F. Lefèvre, Adv. Synth. Catal. 2005, 347, 1022-1026;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Chodorge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fourage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Lefèvre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Masson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006. 2006/003298</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Chodorge, L. Fourage, F. Lefèvre, J.-M. Masson, 2006, WO2006/003298.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jemli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ayadi-Zouari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hlima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bejar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Crit. Rev. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="246" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">a) S. Jemli, D. Ayadi-Zouari, H. B. Hlima, S. Bejar, Crit. Rev. Biotechnol. 2016, 36, 246-258;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.bmc.2017.06.043</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmc.2017.06.043" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">press</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">H. Sun, H. Zhang, E. L. Ang, H. Zhao, Bioorg. Med. Chem. 2017, in press, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmc.2017.06.043.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Maniatis in: Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sambrook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Fritsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<pubPlace>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, Cold Spring Harbor, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">J. Sambrook, E. F. Fritsch, T. Maniatis in: Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual, Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, Cold Spring Harbor, NY, 1989;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Tartoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hobbs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bethesda Research Laboratories Focus</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">K. D. Tartoff, C. A. Hobbs, Bethesda Research Laboratories Focus 1987, 9, 12;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A short course in bacterial genetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
			<pubPlace>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, Cold Spring Harbor, N.Y.</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">J. H. Miller in: A short course in bacterial genetics. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, Cold Spring Harbor, N.Y., 1992.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Van Spronsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Dai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Verberne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hollmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">W C E</forename><surname>Arends</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G.-J</forename><surname>Witkamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Verpoorte</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plant Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">156</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1701" to="1705" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">a) Y. H. Choi, J. van Spronsen, Y. Dai, M. Verberne, F. Hollmann, I. W. C. E. Arends, G.-J. Witkamp, R. Verpoorte, Plant Physiol. 2011, 156, 1701-1705;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dominguez De Maria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Maugeri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="220" to="225" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">P. Dominguez de Maria, Z. Maugeri, Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol. 2011, 15, 220-225.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wachtmeister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rother</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="169" to="177" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">J. Wachtmeister, D. Rother, Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. 2016, 42, 169-177.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Reinert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Balliano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Schulz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="126" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">D. J. Reinert, G. Balliano, G. E. Schulz, Chem. Biol. 2004, 11, 121-126.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lütz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Giver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lalonde</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechnol. Bioeng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="647" to="653" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. Lütz, L. Giver, J. Lalonde, Biotechnol. Bioeng. 2008, 101, 647-653.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tüfvesson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lima-Ramos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nordblad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Woodley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Oprd</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="274" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">a) P. Tüfvesson, J. Lima-Ramos, M. Nordblad, J. M. Woodley OPRD 2011, 15, 266-274;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tüfvesson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lima-Ramos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Al Haque</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Gernaey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Woodley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Oprd</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1233" to="1238" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">P. Tüfvesson, J. Lima-Ramos, N. Al Haque, K. V. Gernaey, J. M. Woodley OPRD 2013, 17, 1233-1238.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-P</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Eichhorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hanlon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lütz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schürmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wohlgemuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Coppolecchia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Catal. Sci. Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">H.-P. Meyer, E. Eichhorn, S. Hanlon, S. Lütz, M. Schürmann, R. Wohlgemuth, R. Coppolecchia, Catal. Sci. Technol. 2013, 3, 29-40.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Escher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Giersch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Niclass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bernardinello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ohloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Helv. Chim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1935" to="1947" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">S. Escher, W. Giersch, Y. Niclass, G. Bernardinello, G. Ohloff, Helv. Chim. Acta 1990, 73, 1935-1947.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Barrero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Altarejos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Alvarez-Manzaneda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ramos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Salido</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tetrahedron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6251" to="6262" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">a) A. F. Barrero, J. Altarejos, E. J. Alvarez- Manzaneda, J. M. Ramos, S. Salido, Tetrahedron 1993, 49, 6251-6262;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Maleczka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Paquette</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Org. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6538" to="6546" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">R. E. Maleczka, L. A. Paquette, J. Org. Chem. 1991, 56, 6538-6546.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Eichhorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schilling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wahler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fourage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Locher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2016/170099</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">a) E. Eichhorn, B. Schilling, D. Wahler, L. Fourage, E. Locher, 2016, WO2016/170099;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Eichhorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2016/170106</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">E. Eichhorn, 2016, WO2016/170106;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sanhaji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rousseaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Noel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Eichhorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 2017/182542</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">G. Sanhaji, A. Rousseaux, S. Noel, E. Eichhorn, 2017, WO2017/182542.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rüthi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Schröder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 2015/059290</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">F. Rüthi, F. Schröder, 2015, WO 2015/059290;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Schröder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 2015/059293</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">F. Schröder, 2015, WO2015/059293;</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bonnekessel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ernst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Siegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Winterfeldt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hoffmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2013/156398</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">M. Bonnekessel, H. Ernst, W. Siegel, E. Winterfeldt, R. W. Hoffmann, 2013, WO2013/156398.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Wertman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wyman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Botstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="262" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">K. F. Wertman, A. R. Wyman, D. Botstein, Gene 1986, 49, 253-262.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Studier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Rosenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Dubendorff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/adsc.201800132</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">D. V. Goeddel)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>San Diego</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">185</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="89" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">F. W. Studier, A. H. Rosenberg, J. J. Dunn, J. W. Dubendorff in: Methods in Enzymology, Vol. 185 (Ed.: D. V. Goeddel), San Diego: Academic Press, 1990, pp. 60-89. 10.1002/adsc.201800132</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Accepted Manuscript</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Accepted Manuscript</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
