<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Phenolic Resins</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Janis</forename><surname>Robins</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<addrLine>3M, St. Paul</addrLine>
									<postCode>55144</postCode>
									<region>MN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Phenolic Resins</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">9D35DABC0E7CC7C3205A0F3D6025D274</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-24T12:35+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[0], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Phenolic resins are the reaction products of phenol and formaldehyde. A large variety of resins are possible, depending on the choice of phenol, the phenol/ formaldehyde molar ratio, the type and amount of catalyst, and the time and temperature of the reaction.</p><p>The phenol/ formaldehyde molar ratio, coupled with the type of catalyst used, determines whether the polymer is phenol terminated or methylol terminated; phenol-terminated resins are referred to as novolacs, or two-step resins. Because phenol is nominally trifunctional and formaldehyde is difunctional, novo lacs are produced from a reaction mixture having a formaldehyde/phenol molar ratio between 0.5 and 0.8 in the presence of an acid catalyst. Such resins are not heat reactive until a second ingredient is added that supplies additional formaldehyde needed for a cure. Novolacs are employed as solid products.</p><p>Methylol-terminated resins are referred to as resoles, or one-step resins. Formaldehyde/phenol molar ratios between 1.0 and 3.0 and a basic catalyst are used to produce resoles, which will cure to a thermoset structure upon the application of heat. These resins, therefore, have to be stored under refrigerated conditions. The largest volume usage for resoles is in liquid form.</p><p>Recently a new class of heat-reactive phenolic resins has been developed, based on the anhydrous reaction of paraformaldehyde and phenol in the presence of metal carboxylates. These resins contain a large JANIS ROBINS • Adhesives, Coatings and Sealers Division,</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="430.866" lry="649.134"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="430.866" lry="649.134"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>number of benzylic ether linkages and have essentially open para positions; they are also referred to as "high ortho-ortho" resoles. They are characterized by good room temperature stability and relatively low viscosity owing to the ortho-benzylic ether linkages, which also act as a latent source of formaldehyde that can be released at higher temperatures to crosslink the resm.</p><p>Resins based on para-substituted phenols can be either one-step or two-step, but they cannot cure to a thermoset state. In the manufacture of phenolic resins, smaller quantities of acetaldehyde and furfuraldehyde are used in addition to formaldehyde. Furthermore, resorcinol, bisphenol A, and p-alkylphenols are employed, in addition to phenol, when special properties are desired. Formaldehyde concentrations of 37-50 weight % in aqueous solutions are most commonly employed. The catalysts most frequently used are acids such as oxalic, hydrochloric, sulfuric, p-toluenesulfonic, and phosphoric; and bases such as sodium, calcium, and barium hydroxide. In the weakly acidic range metal carboxylates are employed. Thermoset phenolic resins are employed as structural adhesives for laminating and bonding applications. Para-alkyl-substituted resins are employed as tackifiers in contact adhesives, pressure-sensitive adhesives, and hot-melt adhesives.</p><p>The reaction conditions, particularly the acidity and the temperature, have a profound effect on the character of the resultant products. In general, three stages can be identified: formaldehyde addition to phenol, prepolymer formation below 100°C, and crosslinking at temperatures above 100°C. The reactions between phenols and aldehydes were first described by Bayer,1 who also obtained the first patent on the preparation of methylolphenols. 2</p><p>The first kinetic studies in alkaline media were reported by Lederer 3 and Manasse. 4 The first patents on resin products were issued to Smith,5 for an ebonite and wood substitute, and to Blumer,6 for a shellac substitute. However, not until Baekeland's7 famous "heat and pressure" patent did phenolic resins become prominent and widely used polymers.</p><p>Since the cured resins are infusible and insoluble in most solvents, little progress was made initially in determining structural features. It was only after analysis of the uncured resinous condensation products was attempted that some progress was realized in elucidating the structures of these resin systems. <ref type="bibr">8</ref> The research of Baekeland and Bender involved the synthesis of phenolic resins from various substituted phenols and the application of different condensation methods. <ref type="bibr">9</ref> The earlier workers established some of the structural features of novo lacs 10,11 and resoles, 12,13 but only work published around 1940 provided the knowledge necessary to make significant advances in phenolic resin chemistry. This had to do mostly with the complexity of products which resulted from the reactions of phenolic alcohols. 14</p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
