<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Privalov</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johns Hopkins University Baltimore</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>21219</postCode>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">10C5FDEA5412EAFBB50AFE45DB210B76</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-24T14:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[0], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="612.0" lry="792.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The rapid rise of interest in biology in general and in proteins in particular is a unique feature of current science. This is both a consequence of and a reason for new developments in protein science. It has led to new approaches to study these biological molecules, as well as the realization of their fundamental role in all living processes, and the understanding that many diseases are due to defects in the structure of specific proteins. The prospect of modifying proteins to correct their structure and designing new molecules with new features and functions opens protein science to its most challenging and exciting phase. Thus, the number of students wanting to learn more about proteins to use them for practical purposes is increasing rapidly. Consequently there is a rising demand for books about proteins, particularly those describing the most recent advances.</p><p>At the present time there are several excellent textbooks on proteins. Nevertheless, the appearance of Alan Fersht's book ``Structure and Mechanism in Protein Science'' is certainly a significant event. This book represents an expansion of his previous book ``Enzyme Structure and Mechanism''. This expansion, inspired by new developments in protein science, entails both an increase in coverage and also in depth, and concentrates on the basic principles, emphasizing the fundamental physical and chemical processes behind them. Professor Fersht is one of the pioneers in the development of site directed mutagenesis, a technique which opened the prospect of protein engineering. To look at proteins from the point of view of this outstanding scientist gives the reader a unique insight, particularly as the book highlights many aspects of proteins and their function that are so new that they not considered in existing textbooksÐ and protein science is certainly developing very fast.</p><p>The twenty chapters of this 631 page book are packed with the essential information on proteins, almost all given in a very succinct style. It is, essentially, an encyclopedia of proteins with the extensive references to original papers making it a very useful guide to the basic level of the living world, the protein kingdom. But it is more than an uncritical collection of existing information on proteins. The book focuses attention on the latest ideas and new approaches, concentrating on the basic chemistry, kinetics, thermodynamics and structure, and how these are related. Especially interesting are accounts of the developments in which the author himself played an essential role, namely the use of site directed replacement of amino acids in the polypeptide chains of proteins. This has provided vital insights into the mechanism and pathways of folding, the stabilization of the native protein conformation and the forces responsible for this, the dynamics of the native structure and the use of protein engineering in enzymology to understand mechanisms at the structural level. It is important that the author is not merely an observer, who has gleaned this information from published literature and condensed it into a book, but is an active player himself, a leader who played a prime role in raising the problems and also in their solution. In consequence, he succeeds in explaining complicated notions in just a few sentences. One such example is the explanation of first and second order phase transitions without using specialized physical terminology or equations. The skill of the author in presenting complex ideas in a simple, clear, way stimulates in the reader an intuitive feel for the handling of the formulae, kinetics and thermodynamics that describe the various aspects of protein molecules.</p><p>This book should certainly be on the personal library shelf of every protein scientist. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc>BioEssays 22:591, ß 2000 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc. BioEssays 22.6 591 Book reviews</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
