<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">ENZYME STABILIZATION BY DIRECTED EVOLUTION</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anne</forename><surname>Gershenson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Chemistry &amp; Chemical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">California Institute of Technology Pasadena</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210-41 91125</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Frances</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Chemistry &amp; Chemical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">California Institute of Technology Pasadena</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>210-41 91125</postCode>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">ENZYME STABILIZATION BY DIRECTED EVOLUTION</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D6CDFCE1ED868723A071B2D11E253858</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-24T14:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[0], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="504.57" lry="720.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="504.57" lry="720.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Engineered enzymes are widely used in industrial processes, where they provide distinct advantages over the naturally-occurring ones (1, 2). Engineering a useful enzyme is particularly difficult when the target functions--for example, the environment in which it must work or the substrates it must accept--differ significantly from the natural ones.</p><p>'Rational' design approaches depend on detailed knowledge of enzyme structure and function. Unfortunately, the three-dimensional conformations of most enzymes are unknown, and, even when a structure is available, the relationship of structure to function is often not apparent. Further complicating the design problem is the fact that the effects of mutations can be propagated over long distances, such that mutations far from the active site can affect catalytic activity (3-5) and even single mutations can generate large structural changes (6, 7).</p><p>Evolutionary approaches to protein design require no structural information or assumptions about where mutations will be most effective. In laboratory evolutIon experiments, libraries of mutants are generated by random mutagenesis or recombination techniques, and variants displaying improvements in the property or properties of interest are chosen by screening or selection <ref type="bibr">(8,</ref><ref type="bibr">9)</ref>. Improved variants are then used to generate the next library. The only requirements are the ability to express the protein in functional form and an appropriate screen or selection. This 'directed evolution' approach has been used to improve a wide range of enzyme properties <ref type="bibr">(10,</ref><ref type="bibr">11)</ref>. This chapter will focus on evolutionary approaches to increasing enzyme stability.</p><p>Proteins are only marginally stable, with free energy differences between the native and denatured states equivalent to only a few weak intermolecular interactions <ref type="bibr">(12,</ref><ref type="bibr">13)</ref>. While this instability may help organisms respond to their environments, for example, by selectively expressing and degrading proteins ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>), it is a disadvantage for almost all commercial enzyme applications. Thus improving stability is the focus of much engineering effort. Changing protein stability can also help elucidate molecular mechanisms of stabilization and how stability influences other properties, such as activity or folding.</p><p>Various evolutionary strategies have been successfully applied to protein stabilization (15-51). Methods for evolution of stability with the use of phage display were recently reviewed (52). This chapter will therefore focus solely on enzyme stabilization by selection In thermophilic host cells and laboratory evolution by mutagenesis/recombination and screening.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>QUANTIFYING STABILITY</head><p>To discuss stabilizing an enzyme, we must first define what we mean by stability. The appropriate measure of stability depends on the enzyme's intended use. Enzymes used in industrial reactions must be active for hundreds of hours under conditions of constant turnover, whereas those in pharmaceutical products or diagnostics must catalyze reactions even after long term storage. For these applications, an operational measure of stability is more relevant than thermodynamic stability. One useful measure is the melting temperature (Tro), the midpoint of the thermal unfolding transition, as judged by structural probes such as circular dichroism (CD), differential scanning calorimetry (DSC) or fluorescence spectroscopy. Of practical use are operational measures such as the Tso (the temperature at which the enzyme loses 50% of its activity following incubation for a set time) and the tl/2 (half-life, or time it takes for the enzyme to lose half of its activity under a specified set of conditions). T m, T so and tl/2 are all influenced by the local environment, and proteases, organic solvents or chaotropic agents will reduce these values.</p><p>Thermodynamic parameters help us understand the molecular mechanisms of stabilization and interactions with other molecules. Thermodynamic stability also may correlate with operational stability. For reversible unfolding transitions, the temperature dependence of structural probes provides a measure of the Gibbs free energy, enthalpy and entropy differences between the native and denatured states and how these parameters depend on temperature <ref type="bibr">(53,</ref><ref type="bibr">54)</ref>. Unlike other measures of stability, thermodynamic parameters allow stability comparisons among proteins regardless of differences in structure, function or other properties. For strictly additive mutations, the change in ilG of unfolding due to multiple mutations is equal to the sum of the ililG's for the single mutations. Thus, thermodynamic parameters provide a direct measure of the additivity and cooperativity among mutations. Most enzymes, however, do not unfold reversibly, making thermodynamic measurements and quantitative comparisons, particularly of mutational additivity, between the progenitor and stabilized mutant difficult, ifnot impossible.</p></div>			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>J. K. Setlow (ed.), Genetic Engineering © Kluwer Academic/Plenum Publishers 2000</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
