<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Preparation of (S)-piperazine-2-carboxylic acid, (R)-piperazine-2-carboxylic acid, and (S)-piperidine-2-carboxylic acid by kinetic resolution of the corresponding racemic carboxamides with stereoselective amidases in whole bacterial cells</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">~</forename><forename type="middle">)</forename><surname>Pergamon</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Eric</forename><surname>Eichhorn</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Biotechnoiogy Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Lonza AG</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CH-3930</postCode>
									<settlement>Visp</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jean-Paul</forename><surname>Roduit</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Chemistry Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Lonza AG</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CH-3930</postCode>
									<settlement>Visp</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nicholas</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Biotechnoiogy Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Lonza AG</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CH-3930</postCode>
									<settlement>Visp</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Klaus</forename><surname>Heinzmann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Biotechnoiogy Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Lonza AG</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>CH-3930</postCode>
									<settlement>Visp</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Kiener</surname></persName>
							<email>andreas.kiener@lonza.ch</email>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Preparation of (S)-piperazine-2-carboxylic acid, (R)-piperazine-2-carboxylic acid, and (S)-piperidine-2-carboxylic acid by kinetic resolution of the corresponding racemic carboxamides with stereoselective amidases in whole bacterial cells</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">88D2DEFAE95B4DB26D1C0F8F9839E1CC</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-08-24T14:47+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=0, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[0], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Whole bacterial cells containing stereospecific amidases were used for the kinetic resolution of racemic piperazine-2-carboxamide and piperidine-2-carboxamide to (S)and (R)-piperazine-2-carboxylic acid, and (S)-piperidine-2-carboxylic acid, respectively.</p><p>(S)-Piperazinecarboxylic acid dihydrochloride produced with the biocatalysts Klebsiella terrigena DSM 9174 had an ee value of 99.4% (41% yield), and the ee value of (R)piperazinecarboxylic acid dihydrochloride obtained with Burkholderia sp. DSM 9925 was 99.0% (22% yield). Using Pseudomonas fluorescens DSM 9924 (S)-piperidine-2carboxylic acid with an ee value of 97.3% (20% yield) was isolated.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<surface n="1" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="526.0" lry="699.0"/>
		<surface n="2" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="526.0" lry="699.0"/>
		<surface n="3" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="526.0" lry="699.0"/>
		<surface n="4" ulx="0.0" uly="0.0" lrx="526.0" lry="699.0"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Non-proteinogenic amino acids such as piperidine-2-carboxylic acid (pipecolic acid), 6 and piperazine-2-carboxylic acid 3 are precursors of numerous bio-active compounds. Derivatives of pipecolic acid include the immunosuppressant FK506,1 local anesthetics, 2 an antipsychotic drug, 3 and a K-opioid analgesic. 4 (S)-Piperazine-2-carboxylic acid can be used for the synthesis of the HIV protease inhibitor Crixivan from Merck 5, an N-methyl-D-aspartate antagonist, 6 and a cardioprotective nucleoside transport blocker. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> The best current route to the pure enantiomers of these amino acids is classical resolution of the racemate by fractional crystallization of diastereomeric salts. 8'9 Asymmetric syntheses for (S)-pipecolic acid have been developed 1° as well as a kinetic resolution of (R,S)-n-octylpipecolate using a partially purified Aspergillus niger lipase. II (S)-Piperazine-2-carboxylic acid has also been prepared by kinetic resolution of racemic 4-(tert-butoxycarbonyl)piperazine-2-carboxamide with leucine aminopeptidase. 7 Both of these biocatalytical processes have practical disadvantages in that the preparation of the racemic starting materials is complicated and the availability of the biocatalysts for large scale production is limited.</p><p>In this paper we report the efficient kinetic resolution of racemic piperazine-2-carboxamide 2 and racemic piperidine-2-carboxamide 5 to the corresponding enantiomerically pure carboxylic acids with whole cells of wild-type micro-organisms that contain stereospecific amidases. 12</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results and discussion</head><p>A primary screening for micro-organisms with amidase activity was done starting from soil samples using growth media containing one of the racemic carboxamides 2 and 5 as sole nitrogen source. Micro-organisms forming stereospecific amidases were identified as follows. Individual clones were grown for 3 days in media containing 2 gL -1 of one of the racemic carboxamides 2 or 5 as Nsource. Samples of the cell-free growth medium were then analysed on TLC plates to estimate the</p><p>2534 E. EICHHORN et aL amount of carboxylic acid formed. Micro-organisms hydrolysing approximately 50% of the racemic carboxamides were chosen for further investigation to determine the stereoselectivity of the amidases. As a result of this screening the strains Klebsiella terrigena DSM 9174, Burkholderia sp. DSM 9925, and Pseudomonasfluorescens DSM 9924 were used for the preparation of (S)-piperazine-2-carboxylic acid, (R)-piperazine-2-carboxylic acid, and (S)-pipecolic acid, respectively (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). N N..~ ~N~'~CN I~N~,/NH2 O 1 ,eOs,o,,a ( + DSM 917~,-I L~N~/OH H .N. ~ H IIo .f'l M. NH 2 N 2 0 OSM 9925 L'N/L"'I~'OH O (S)-3 (R)-3 NH3 NH3 Pseudomonas -% OSM,, , .%, NH, NH 2 NH 2 OH O O O 4 5 (s)-6</p><p>For the production of samples smaller than 10 g, the micro-organisms were grown on the appropriate medium, harvested by centrifugation, and washed in physiological salt solution. The cells were then re-suspended for various periods of time in buffer typically containing 10-20 gL -l of the corresponding racemic carboxamide. The ee-values of piperazine-2-carboxylic acid and pipecolic acid were analyzed by capillary electrophoresis and HPLC, respectively. Piperazine-2-carboxylic acid was isolated from the cell free solution as the dihydrochloride salt. Pipecolic acid was isolated using anion chromatography (adsorbance on Duolite A 147 and subsequent elution with 10% acetic acid). No attempts were made to purify the carboxamides after the bioconversion. However, following the biotransformation with Klebsiella terrigena, the carboxamide remaining in aqueous solution after the (S)-piperazine-2-carboxylic acid had been precipitated with HCI, was hydrolysed for 4 h at 80°C, and after cooling (R)-piperazine-2-carboxylic acid was isolated. The ee-value of the recrystallized (R)-3 was 99.2% {[ot]2°589=+4.74 (c 1.2; H20)}.</p><p>Larger samples of (S)-piperazine-2-carboxylic acid were produced in a 1 L fermenter by growing cells of Klebsiella terrigena in the presence of 22 gL-l of racemic 2.</p><p>The kinetic resolutions presented in this paper are particularly attractive because the starting materials 2 and 5 can be easily prepared from 2-cyanopyrazine 1 and 2-cyanopyridine 3 via the corresponding aromatic carboxamides. Furthermore, the micro-organisms can be grown in fermenters on the racemic carboxamides at the same time as the biotransformations are taking place.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental (RS)-Piperazine-2-carboxamide 2</head><p>A solution of pyrazinecarboxamide (I 200 g, 9.747 moles) in absolute ethanol (6 L) was hydrogenated at 85°C under 20 bars of pressure in the presence of 240 g of 10% Pd/C. A considerable exotherm was observed at the beginning. After completion of the reaction (5 h), the warm solution was concentrated to 2.5 L, whereupon the product began to crystallise. The stirred suspension was cooled to 2°C and filtered. The filter cake was washed with 1 L of cold ethyl acetate and dried in vacuum at 50°C. A yield of 1035 g of racemic piperazine-2-carboxamide was obtained as a white crystalline powder, m.p. 143-144°C (82.2% of theoretical yield). A second crop could be obtained from the mother liquor.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(RS)-Piperidine-2-carboxamide S</head><p>Pyridine-2-carboxamide (350 g, 2.866 moles) in 3 L of absolute ethanol was hydrogenated at 110°C and 20 bars in the presence of 14 g of 10% Pd/C. The product was isolated as described above and the yield of crystalline racemic piperidine-2-carboxamide, m.p. 147-148°C, was 337 g (91.7%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Micro-organisms</head><p>The micro-organisms have been deposited at the Deutsche Sammlung fiir Mikroorganismen, Mascheroder Weg 1B, D-38124 Braunschweig, Germany.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analytical methods</head><p>Thin layer chromatography: pre-coated silica gel 60 plates (Merck) were developed with ethanol:chloroform:25% NH4OH (11:6:6). The compounds were detected with ninhydrin (Rf 2 and 5~0.8, Rf 3 and 6~0.2).</p><p>Capillary electrophoresis of (R)-3 and (S)-3" aqueous solutions or isolated products were first derivatized with 2,3,4,6-tetra-O-acetyl-13-D-glucopyranosyl isothiocyanate. The CE system (Hewlett-Packard HP 3DCE, capillary column: HP G1600-61211) was operated at 20 kV and a current of 24-301aA at 20°C oven temperature. The buffer (pH 9.0) contained 10 mM Na2HPO4, 10 mM H3BO3, and 150 mM sodium dodecyl sulfate. The electrolyte was buffer:methanol (9:1). The UV detector was set at 210 nm. The migration times of (S)-3 and (R)-3 were 17.1 and 17.7 min, respectively.</p><p>HPLC of (S)-6: Samples were first derivatized with 2,3,4,6-tetra-O-acetyl-[~-D-glucopyranosyl isothiocyanate. The HPLC system (Hewlett-Packard 1090) was operated with a reverse phase column (Machery Nagel, Nucleosil 120-3 Cl8 AB) at 40°C. The UV detector was set at 250 nm. The solvents were A: H20, B: CH3CN, C: 250 mM KH2PO4 (pH 2.3). Solvent C was kept constant at 20%. The compounds were eluted by increasing solvent B from 30% to 50%. The retention times of (S)-6 and (R)-6 were 9.2 and 9.9 min, respectively. Reference samples of (R)-6 and (S)-6 were obtained from Fluka Chemicals, Buchs, Switzerland.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cultivation for small scale bioconversions</head><p>For the growth of Klebsiella terrigena DSM 9174 and Burkholderia sp. DSM 9925 a mineral salts medium 13 was supplemented with 500 mgL -1 yeast extract, l0 gL -I glycerine, and 2 gL -l 2. The mineral salts medium for Pseudomonas fluorescens DSM 9924 was supplemented with 500 mgL-1 yeast extract, 4 gL-i glucose, and 1 gL-l 5. Growth was at 30°C and pH 7.0.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Preparative scale formation of (S )-piperazine-2-carboxylic acid</head><p>Klebsiella terrigena DSM 9174 was grown in a 1.5 L fermenter (1 L working volume) in the mineral salts medium 13 supplemented with 500 mgL -I yeast extract, 30 gL -1 glycerine, and 22 gL -1 2 at 30°C, pH 7.0, and an aeration rate of 0.5 Lmin -1 for 16 h. After this period the temperature was increased to 40°C and the pH adjusted to 8.0 to enhance the enzymatic hydrolysis rate. The</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Substrate specificity, stereospecificity and reaction conditions of isolated micro-organisms Piperazine-2-carboxylic acids were isolated as dihydrochloride salts.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Strain</cell><cell>Substrate</cell><cell>Product</cell><cell>Reaction</cell><cell>% e¢</cell><cell>isolated</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>conditions</cell><cell></cell><cell>yield*</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Klebsiella terrigena (RS)-piperazine-</cell><cell>(S)-piperazine-</cell><cell>40°C -47°C</cell><cell>99.4%</cell><cell>41%</cell></row><row><cell>DSM 9174</cell><cell>2-carboxamide</cell><cell cols="2">2-carboxylic acid pH 8.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Burkholderia sp.</cell><cell>(RS)-piperazine-</cell><cell>(R)-piperazine-</cell><cell>40°C-47°C</cell><cell>99.0%</cell><cell>22%</cell></row><row><cell>DSM 9925</cell><cell>2-carboxamide</cell><cell cols="2">2-carboxylic acid pH 8.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P. fluorescens</cell><cell>(RS)-pipeddine-</cell><cell>(S)-piperidine-</cell><cell>30°C</cell><cell>97.3%</cell><cell>20%</cell></row><row><cell>DSM 9924</cell><cell>2-carboxamide</cell><cell cols="2">2-carboxylic acid pH 7.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>*:</p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>biotransformation was followed by TLC and capillary electrophoresis and stopped after 36-72 h by removing the cells by centrifugation. For the isolation of (S)-3 the cell free solution was concentrated 10-fold at 60°C under reduced pressure and acidified with conc. HCI (pH 1.0) to precipitate the product. (S)-3 was re-crystallized in 0.1 M HCI. IH-NMR (400 MHz, D20): 4.46 ppm (dd, 1H, H-2, J2,3A=4.1 Hz, J2,3B=l 1.0 Hz); 4.00 ppm (dd, 1H, H-3A, J2,3A=4.1 Hz, J3A,3B=14.2 HZ); 3.70-3.83 ppm (m, 2H, H-5A und H-6A); 3.56 ppm (dd, 1H, H-3B, J2.3B=l 1.0 Hz, J3A.3B=14.2 Hz); 3.40-3.56 ppm (m, 2H, H-5B und H-6B). [ot]2°589=-4.85 (c 1.2; H20).</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Reamer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Askin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Desmond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Volante</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Shinkai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1157" to="1159" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Jones, T. K.; Mills, S. G.; Reamer, R. A.; Askin, D.; Desmond, R.; Volante, R. P.; Shinkai, I. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 1989, 111, 1157-1159.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Af Ekenstam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bovin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Us</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Patent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987, 4,695,576</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Af Ekenstam, B. T.; Bovin, C. US Patent, 1987, 4,695,576.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Patrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Singletary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chirality</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="208" to="211" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Patrick, K. S.; Singletary, J. L. Chirality 1991, 3, 208-211.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vecchietti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Giordani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Giardina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Colle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Clarke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="403" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Vecchietti, V.; Giordani, A.; Giardina, G.; Colle, R.; Clarke, G. D. J. Med. Chem. 1991, 34, 397-403.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Askin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Eng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Rossen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Purick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wells</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Volante</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Reider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tetrahedron Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="673" to="676" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Askin, D.; Eng, K. K.; Rossen, K.; Purick, R. M.; Wells, R. P.; Volante, R. P.; Reider, P. J. Tetrahedron Lett. 1994, 35, 673-676.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E;</forename><surname>Bigge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ortwine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Drummond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Retz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brahce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Marcoux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Probert</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Med. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1371" to="1384" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bigge, C. E; Johnson, G.; Ortwine, D. E; Drummond, J. T.; Retz, D. M.; Brahce, L. J.; Marcoux, F. W.; Probert Jr., A. W. J. Med. Chem. 1992, 35, 1371-1384.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bruce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>St</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Laurent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Poindexter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Monkovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Balasubramanian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Synth. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2673" to="2684" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Bruce, M. A.; St. Laurent, D. R.; Poindexter, G. S.; Monkovic, I.; Huang, S.; Balasubramanian, N. Synth. Commun. 1995, 25, 2673-2684.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Aebischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Frey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Haerter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Herrling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Mueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Olverman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Watkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Helv. Chim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1043" to="1051" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Aebischer, B.; Frey, P.; Haerter, H. P.; Herrling, P. L.; Mueller, W.; Olverman, H. J.; Watkins, J. C. Helv. Chim. Acta 1989, 72, 1043-1051.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Shiraiwa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Shinjo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kurokawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bull. Chem. Soc. Jpn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3251" to="3255" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Shiraiwa, T.; Shinjo, K.; Kurokawa, H. Bull. Chem. Soc. Jpn. 1991, 64, 3251-3255.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kisfaludy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E;</forename><surname>Korenczki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Katho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
			<biblScope unit="page">163</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kisfaludy, L.; Korenczki, E; Katho, A. Synthesis 1982, 163.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ng-Youn-Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Serreqi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kazlauskas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Org. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2075" to="2081" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="raw_reference">Ng-Youn-Chen, M. C.; Serreqi, A. N.; Huang, Q.; Kazlauskas, R. J. J. Org. Chem. 1994, 59, 2075-2081.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">European Patent Application</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kiener</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Roduit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kohr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kiener</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Roduit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Heinzmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PCT Application WO</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">0686</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">35775</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">698</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995. 1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Eric Eichhorn is not coinventor of these patent applications</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">a) Kiener, A.; Roduit, J. P.; Kohr, J.; Shaw, N. 1995, European Patent Application, 0686 698. (b) Kiener, A.; Roduit, J. P.; Heinzmann, K. 1996, PCT Application WO 96/35775 (Eric Eichhorn is not coinventor of these patent applications).</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kulla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E;</forename><surname>Klausener</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liideke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Leisinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">135</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
			<date type="published" when="1983-04-07">1983. 7 April 1997. June 1997</date>
			<pubPlace>UK</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Received in</note>
	<note type="raw_reference">Kulla, H. G.; Klausener, E; Meyer, U.; Liideke, B.; Leisinger, T. Arch. Microbiol. 1983, 135, 1-7. (Received in UK 7 April 1997; accepted 13 June 1997)</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
